Contributing guidelines

Chatting

If you have a question, looking for an interactive troubleshooting help or want to chat with other Patroni users, join us on channel #patroni [https://postgresteam.slack.com/archives/C9XPYG92A] in the PostgreSQL Slack [https://pgtreats.info/slack-invite].

Reporting bugs

Before reporting a bug please make sure to reproduce it with the latest Patroni version! Also please double check if the issue already exists in our Issues Tracker [https://github.com/patroni/patroni/issues].

Running tests

Requirements for running behave tests:

PostgreSQL packages including contrib [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/contrib.html] modules need to be installed.

PostgreSQL binaries must be available in your

PATH

. You may need to add them to the path with something like

PATH=/usr/lib/postgresql/11/bin:$PATH python -m behave

.

If you’d like to test with external DCSs (e.g., Etcd, Consul, and Zookeeper) you’ll need the packages installed and respective services running and accepting unencrypted/unprotected connections on localhost and default port. In the case of Etcd or Consul, the behave test suite could start them up if binaries are available in the

PATH

.

Install dependencies:

# You may want to use Virtualenv or specify pip3.
pip install -r requirements.txt
pip install -r requirements.dev.txt

After you have all dependencies installed, you can run the various test suites:

# You may want to use Virtualenv or specify python3.

# Run flake8 to check syntax and formatting:
python setup.py flake8

# Run the pytest suite in tests/:
python setup.py test

# Moreover, you may want to run tests in different scopes for debugging purposes,
# the -s option include print output during test execution.
# Tests in pytest typically follow the pattern: FILEPATH::CLASSNAME::TESTNAME.
pytest -s tests/test_api.py
pytest -s tests/test_api.py::TestRestApiHandler
pytest -s tests/test_api.py::TestRestApiHandler::test_do_GET

# Run the behave (https://behave.readthedocs.io/en/latest/) test suite in features/;
# modify DCS as desired (raft has no dependencies so is the easiest to start with):
DCS=raft python -m behave

Testing with tox

To run tox tests you only need to install one dependency (other than Python)

pip install tox>=4

If you wish to run

behave

tests then you also need docker installed.

Tox configuration in

tox.ini

has “environments” to run the following tasks:

lint: Python code lint with

flake8

test: unit tests for all available python interpreters with

pytest

, generates XML reports or HTML reports if a TTY is detected

dep: detect package dependency conflicts using

pipdeptree

type: static type checking with

pyright

black: code formatting with

black

docker-build: build docker image used for the

behave

env

docker-cmd: run arbitrary command with the above image

docker-behave-etcd: run tox for behave tests with above image

py*behave: run behave with available python interpreters (without docker, although this is what is called inside docker containers)

docs: build docs with

sphinx

Running tox

To run the default env list; dep, lint, test, and docs, just run:

tox

The

test

envs can be run with the label

test

:

tox -m test

The

behave

docker tests can be run with the label

behave

:

tox -m behave

Similarly, docs has the label

docs

.

All other envs can be run with their respective env names:

tox -e lint
tox -e py39-test-lin

It is also possible to select partial env lists using

factors

. For example, if you want to run all envs for python 3.10:

tox -f py310

This is equivalent to running all the envs listed below:

$ tox -l -f py310
py310-test-lin
py310-test-mac
py310-test-win
py310-type-lin
py310-type-mac
py310-type-win
py310-behave-etcd-lin
py310-behave-etcd-win
py310-behave-etcd-mac

You can list all configured combinations of environments with tox (>=v4) like so

tox l

The envs

test

and

docs

will attempt to open the HTML output files when the job completes, if tox is run with an active terminal. This is intended to be for benefit of the developer running this env locally. It will attempt to run

open

on a mac and

xdg-open

on Linux. To use a different command set the env var

OPEN_CMD

to the name or path of the command. If this step fails it will not fail the run overall. If you want to disable this facility set the env var

OPEN_CMD

to the

:

no-op command.

OPEN_CMD=: tox -m docs

Behave tests

Behave tests with

-m behave

will build docker images based on PG_MAJOR version 11 through 16 and then run all behave tests. This can take quite a long time to run so you might want to limit the scope to a select version of Postgres or to a specific feature set or steps.

To specify the version of postgres include the full name of the dependent image build env that you want and then the behave env name. For instance if you want Postgres 14 use:

tox -e pg14-docker-build,pg14-docker-behave-etcd-lin

If on the other hand you want to test a specific feature you can pass positional arguments to behave. This will run the watchdog behave feature test scenario with all versions of Postgres.

tox -m behave -- features/watchdog.feature

Of course you can combine the two.

Contributing a pull request

Fork the repository, develop and test your code changes.

Reflect changes in the user documentation.

Submit a pull request with a clear description of the changes objective. Link an existing issue if necessary.

You’ll get feedback about your pull request as soon as possible.

Happy Patroni hacking ;-)

DCS Failsafe Mode

The problem

Patroni is heavily relying on Distributed Configuration Store (DCS) to solve the task of leader elections and detect network partitioning. That is, the node is allowed to run Postgres as the primary only if it can update the leader lock in DCS. In case the update of the leader lock fails, Postgres is immediately demoted and started as read-only. Depending on which DCS is used, the chances of hitting the “problem” differ. For example, with Etcd which is only used for Patroni, chances are close to zero, while with K8s API (backed by Etcd) it could be observed more frequently.

Reasons for the current implementation

The leader lock update failure could be caused by two main reasons:

Network partitioning

DCS being down

In general, it is impossible to distinguish between these two from a single node, and therefore Patroni assumes the worst case - network partitioning. In the case of a partitioned network, other nodes of the Patroni cluster may successfully grab the leader lock and promote Postgres to primary. In order to avoid a split-brain, the old primary is demoted before the leader lock expires.

DCS Failsafe Mode

We introduce a new special option, the failsafe_mode. It could be enabled only via global dynamic configuration stored in the DCS /config key. If the failsafe mode is enabled and the leader lock update in DCS failed due to reasons different from the version/value/index mismatch, Postgres may continue to run as a primary if it can access all known members of the cluster via Patroni REST API.

Low-level implementation details

We introduce a new, permanent key in DCS, named /failsafe.

The /failsafe key contains all known members of the given Patroni cluster at a given time.

The current leader maintains the /failsafe key.

The member is allowed to participate in the leader race and become the new leader only if it is present in the /failsafe key.

If the cluster consists of a single node the /failsafe key will contain a single member.

In the case of DCS “outage” the existing primary connects to all members presented in the /failsafe key via the POST /failsafe REST API and may continue to run as the primary if all replicas acknowledge it.

If one of the members doesn’t respond, the primary is demoted.

Replicas are using incoming POST /failsafe REST API requests as an indicator that the primary is still alive. This information is cached for ttl seconds.

F.A.Q.

Why MUST the current primary see ALL other members? Can’t we rely on quorum here?

This is a great question! The problem is that the view on the quorum might be different from the perspective of DCS and Patroni. While DCS nodes must be evenly distributed across availability zones, there is no such rule for Patroni, and more importantly, there is no mechanism for introducing and enforcing such a rule. If the majority of Patroni nodes ends up in the losing part of the partitioned network (including primary) while minority nodes are in the winning part, the primary must be demoted. Only checking ALL other members allows detecting such a situation.

What if node/pod gets terminated while DCS is down?

If DCS isn’t accessible, the check “are ALL other cluster members accessible?” is executed every cycle of the heartbeat loop (every loop_wait seconds). If pod/node is terminated, the check will fail and Postgres will be demoted to a read-only and will not recover until DCS is restored.

What if all members of the Patroni cluster are lost while DCS is down?

Patroni could be configured to create the new replica from the backup even when the cluster doesn’t have a leader. But, if the new member isn’t present in the /failsafe key, it will not be able to grab the leader lock and promote.

What will happen if the primary lost access to DCS while replicas didn’t?

The primary will execute the failsafe code and contact all known replicas. These replicas will use this information as an indicator that the primary is alive and will not start the leader race even if the leader lock in DCS has expired.

How to enable the Failsafe Mode?

Before enabling the failsafe_mode please make sure that Patroni version on all members is up-to-date. After that, you can use either the PATCH /config REST API or patronictl edit-config -s failsafe_mode=true

Dynamic Configuration Settings

Dynamic configuration is stored in the DCS (Distributed Configuration Store) and applied on all cluster nodes.

In order to change the dynamic configuration you can use either patronictl edit-config tool or Patroni REST API.

loop_wait: the number of seconds the loop will sleep. Default value: 10, minimum possible value: 1

ttl: the TTL to acquire the leader lock (in seconds). Think of it as the length of time before initiation of the automatic failover process. Default value: 30, minimum possible value: 20

retry_timeout: timeout for DCS and PostgreSQL operation retries (in seconds). DCS or network issues shorter than this will not cause Patroni to demote the leader. Default value: 10, minimum possible value: 3

Warning

when changing values of loop_wait, retry_timeout, or ttl you have to follow the rule:

loop_wait + 2 * retry_timeout <= ttl

maximum_lag_on_failover: the maximum bytes a follower may lag to be able to participate in leader election.

maximum_lag_on_syncnode: the maximum bytes a synchronous follower may lag before it is considered as an unhealthy candidate and swapped by healthy asynchronous follower. Patroni utilize the max replica lsn if there is more than one follower, otherwise it will use leader’s current wal lsn. Default is -1, Patroni will not take action to swap synchronous unhealthy follower when the value is set to 0 or below. Please set the value high enough so Patroni won’t swap synchrounous follower frequently during high transaction volume.

max_timelines_history: maximum number of timeline history items kept in DCS. Default value: 0. When set to 0, it keeps the full history in DCS.

primary_start_timeout: the amount of time a primary is allowed to recover from failures before failover is triggered (in seconds). Default is 300 seconds. When set to 0 failover is done immediately after a crash is detected if possible. When using asynchronous replication a failover can cause lost transactions. Worst case failover time for primary failure is: loop_wait + primary_start_timeout + loop_wait, unless primary_start_timeout is zero, in which case it’s just loop_wait. Set the value according to your durability/availability tradeoff.

primary_stop_timeout: The number of seconds Patroni is allowed to wait when stopping Postgres and effective only when synchronous_mode is enabled. When set to > 0 and the synchronous_mode is enabled, Patroni sends SIGKILL to the postmaster if the stop operation is running for more than the value set by primary_stop_timeout. Set the value according to your durability/availability tradeoff. If the parameter is not set or set <= 0, primary_stop_timeout does not apply.

synchronous_mode: turns on synchronous replication mode. Possible values: off, on, quorum. In this mode the leader takes care of management of synchronous_standby_names, and only the last known leader, or one of synchronous replicas, are allowed to participate in leader race. Synchronous mode makes sure that successfully committed transactions will not be lost at failover, at the cost of losing availability for writes when Patroni cannot ensure transaction durability. See replication modes documentation for details.

synchronous_mode_strict: prevents disabling synchronous replication if no synchronous replicas are available, blocking all client writes to the primary. See replication modes documentation for details.

synchronous_node_count: if synchronous_mode is enabled, this parameter is used by Patroni to manage the precise number of synchronous standby instances and adjusts the state in DCS and the synchronous_standby_names parameter in PostgreSQL as members join and leave. If the parameter is set to a value higher than the number of eligible nodes, it will be automatically adjusted. Defaults to 1.

failsafe_mode: Enables DCS Failsafe Mode. Defaults to

false

.

postgresql:

use_pg_rewind: whether or not to use pg_rewind. Defaults to

false

. Note that either the cluster must be initialized with data page checksums (--data-checksums option for initdb) and/or wal_log_hints must be set to on, or pg_rewind will not work.

use_slots: whether or not to use replication slots. Defaults to

true

on PostgreSQL 9.4+.

recovery_conf: additional configuration settings written to recovery.conf when configuring follower. There is no recovery.conf anymore in PostgreSQL 12, but you may continue using this section, because Patroni handles it transparently.

parameters: configuration parameters (GUCs) for Postgres in format {max_connections: 100, wal_level: "replica", max_wal_senders: 10, wal_log_hints: "on"}. Many of these are required for replication to work.

pg_hba: list of lines that Patroni will use to generate pg_hba.conf. Patroni ignores this parameter if hba_file PostgreSQL parameter is set to a non-default value.

- host all all 0.0.0.0/0 md5

- host replication replicator 127.0.0.1/32 md5: A line like this is required for replication.

pg_ident: list of lines that Patroni will use to generate pg_ident.conf. Patroni ignores this parameter if ident_file PostgreSQL parameter is set to a non-default value.

- mapname1 systemname1 pguser1

- mapname1 systemname2 pguser2

standby_cluster: if this section is defined, we want to bootstrap a standby cluster.

host: an address of remote node

port: a port of remote node

primary_slot_name: which slot on the remote node to use for replication. This parameter is optional, the default value is derived from the instance name (see function

slot_name_from_member_name

).

create_replica_methods: an ordered list of methods that can be used to bootstrap standby leader from the remote primary, can be different from the list defined in PostgreSQL

restore_command: command to restore WAL records from the remote primary to nodes in a standby cluster, can be different from the list defined in PostgreSQL

archive_cleanup_command: cleanup command for standby leader

recovery_min_apply_delay: how long to wait before actually apply WAL records on a standby leader

member_slots_ttl: retention time of physical replication slots for replicas when they are shut down. Default value:

30min

. Set it to

0

if you want to keep the old behavior (when the member key expires from DCS, the slot is immediately removed). The feature works only starting from PostgreSQL 11.

slots: define permanent replication slots. These slots will be preserved during switchover/failover. Permanent slots that don’t exist will be created by Patroni. With PostgreSQL 11 onwards permanent physical slots are created on all nodes and their position is advanced every loop_wait seconds. For PostgreSQL versions older than 11 permanent physical replication slots are maintained only on the current primary. The logical slots are copied from the primary to a standby with restart, and after that their position advanced every loop_wait seconds (if necessary). Copying logical slot files performed via libpq connection and using either rewind or superuser credentials (see postgresql.authentication section). There is always a chance that the logical slot position on the replica is a bit behind the former primary, therefore application should be prepared that some messages could be received the second time after the failover. The easiest way of doing so - tracking confirmed_flush_lsn. Enabling permanent replication slots requires postgresql.use_slots to be set to true. If there are permanent logical replication slots defined Patroni will automatically enable the hot_standby_feedback. Since the failover of logical replication slots is unsafe on PostgreSQL 9.6 and older and PostgreSQL version 10 is missing some important functions, the feature only works with PostgreSQL 11+.

my_slot_name: the name of the permanent replication slot. If the permanent slot name matches with the name of the current node it will not be created on this node. If you add a permanent physical replication slot which name matches the name of a Patroni member, Patroni will ensure that the slot that was created is not removed even if the corresponding member becomes unresponsive, situation which would normally result in the slot’s removal by Patroni. Although this can be useful in some situations, such as when you want replication slots used by members to persist during temporary failures or when importing existing members to a new Patroni cluster (see Convert a Standalone to a Patroni Cluster for details), caution should be exercised by the operator that these clashes in names are not persisted in the DCS, when the slot is no longer required, due to its effect on normal functioning of Patroni.

type: slot type. Could be physical or logical. If the slot is logical, you have to additionally define database and plugin. If the slot is physical, you can optionally define cluster_type.

database: the database name where logical slots should be created.

plugin: the plugin name for the logical slot.

cluster_type: the type of cluster (primary or standby) the slot should only be created on, otherwise it will not be created or an already existing slot will be dropped.

ignore_slots: list of sets of replication slot properties for which Patroni should ignore matching slots. This configuration/feature/etc. is useful when some replication slots are managed outside of Patroni. Any subset of matching properties will cause a slot to be ignored.

name: the name of the replication slot.

type: slot type. Can be physical or logical. If the slot is logical, you may additionally define database and/or plugin.

database: the database name (when matching a logical slot).

plugin: the logical decoding plugin (when matching a logical slot).

Note: slots is a hashmap while ignore_slots is an array. For example:

slots:
  permanent_logical_slot_name:
    type: logical
    database: my_db
    plugin: test_decoding
  permanent_physical_slot_name:
    type: physical
  ...
ignore_slots:
  - name: ignored_logical_slot_name
    type: logical
    database: my_db
    plugin: test_decoding
  - name: ignored_physical_slot_name
    type: physical
  ...

Note: When running PostgreSQL v11 or newer Patroni maintains physical replication slots on all nodes that could potentially become a leader, so that replica nodes keep WAL segments reserved if they are potentially required by other nodes. In case the node is absent and its member key in DCS gets expired, the corresponding replication slot is dropped after member_slots_ttl (default value is

30min

). You can increase or decrease retention based on your needs. Alternatively, if your cluster topology is static (fixed number of nodes that never change their names) you can configure permanent physical replication slots with names corresponding to the names of the nodes to avoid slots removal and recycling of WAL files while replica is temporarily down:

slots:
  node_name1:
    type: physical
  node_name2:
    type: physical
  node_name3:
    type: physical
  ...

Warning

Permanent replication slots are synchronized only from the primary/standby_leader to replica nodes. That means, applications are supposed to be using them only from the leader node. Using them on replica nodes will cause indefinite growth of pg_wal on all other nodes in the cluster. An exception to that rule are physical slots that match the Patroni member names (created and maintained by Patroni). Those will be synchronized among all nodes as they are used for replication among them.

Warning

Setting nostream tag on standby disables copying and synchronization of permanent logical replication slots on the node itself and all its cascading replicas if any.

Environment Configuration Settings

It is possible to override some of the configuration parameters defined in the Patroni configuration file using the system environment variables. This document lists all environment variables handled by Patroni. The values set via those variables always take precedence over the ones set in the Patroni configuration file.

Global/Universal

PATRONI_CONFIGURATION: it is possible to set the entire configuration for the Patroni via PATRONI_CONFIGURATION environment variable. In this case any other environment variables will not be considered!

PATRONI_THREAD_POOL_SIZE: size of thread pool used by Patroni to execute asynchronous tasks and communicate via REST API with other members during leader race or failsafe checks. Minimal value is 5, default value is 5.

PATRONI_THREAD_STACK_SIZE: specifies the stack size to be used for threads started by Patroni. Value must be aligned by 64kB. Minimal value is 64kB, default value (set by Patroni) is 512kB.

PATRONI_NAME: name of the node where the current instance of Patroni is running. Must be unique for the cluster.

PATRONI_NAMESPACE: path within the configuration store where Patroni will keep information about the cluster. Default value: “/service”

PATRONI_SCOPE: cluster name

PG_MALLOC_ARENA_MAX: custom value for MALLOC_ARENA_MAX environment variable for postmaster process. If not set, postmaster will inherit MALLOC_ARENA_MAX value.

Log

PATRONI_LOG_TYPE: sets the format of logs. Can be either plain or json. To use json format, you must have the jsonlogger installed. The default value is plain.

PATRONI_LOG_LEVEL: sets the general logging level. Default value is INFO (see the docs for Python logging [https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#levels])

PATRONI_LOG_TRACEBACK_LEVEL: sets the level where tracebacks will be visible. Default value is ERROR. Set it to DEBUG if you want to see tracebacks only if you enable PATRONI_LOG_LEVEL=DEBUG.

PATRONI_LOG_FORMAT: sets the log formatting string. If the log type is plain, the log format should be a string. Refer to the LogRecord attributes [https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#logrecord-attributes] for available attributes. If the log type is json, the log format can be a list in addition to a string. Each list item should correspond to LogRecord attributes. Be cautious that only the field name is required, and the %( and ) should be omitted. If you wish to print a log field with a different key name, use a dictionary where the dictionary key is the log field, and the value is the name of the field you want to be printed in the log. Default value is %(asctime)s %(levelname)s: %(message)s

PATRONI_LOG_DATEFORMAT: sets the datetime formatting string. (see the formatTime() documentation [https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#logging.Formatter.formatTime])

PATRONI_LOG_STATIC_FIELDS: add additional fields to the log. This option is only available when the log type is set to json. Example PATRONI_LOG_STATIC_FIELDS="{app: patroni}"

PATRONI_LOG_MAX_QUEUE_SIZE: Patroni is using two-step logging. Log records are written into the in-memory queue and there is a separate thread which pulls them from the queue and writes to stderr or file. The maximum size of the internal queue is limited by default by 1000 records, which is enough to keep logs for the past 1h20m.

PATRONI_LOG_DIR: Directory to write application logs to. The directory must exist and be writable by the user executing Patroni. If you set this env variable, the application will retain 4 25MB logs by default. You can tune those retention values with

PATRONI_LOG_FILE_NUM

and

PATRONI_LOG_FILE_SIZE

(see below).

PATRONI_LOG_MODE: Permissions for log files (for example, 0644). If not specified, permissions will be set based on the current umask value.

PATRONI_LOG_FILE_NUM: The number of application logs to retain.

PATRONI_LOG_FILE_SIZE: Size of patroni.log file (in bytes) that triggers a log rolling.

PATRONI_LOG_LOGGERS: Redefine logging level per python module. Example PATRONI_LOG_LOGGERS="{patroni.postmaster: WARNING, urllib3: DEBUG}"

PATRONI_LOG_DEDUPLICATE_HEARTBEAT_LOGS: If set to true, successive heartbeat logs that are identical shall not be output. Default value is false.

Warning

The time the HA loop executes at can be very valuable information in diagnosing failovers due to resource exhaustion and similar problems. When PATRONI_LOG_DEDUPLICATE_HEARTBEAT_LOGS is set to true there will be no log generated for the HA loop execution (unless the leader changes) and hence this potentially useful information will not be available from the logs.

Citus

Enables integration Patroni with Citus [https://docs.citusdata.com]. If configured, Patroni will take care of registering Citus worker nodes on the coordinator. You can find more information about Citus support here.

PATRONI_CITUS_GROUP: the Citus group id, integer. Use 0 for coordinator and 1, 2, etc… for workers

PATRONI_CITUS_DATABASE: the database where citus extension should be created. Must be the same on the coordinator and all workers. Currently only one database is supported.

Consul

PATRONI_CONSUL_HOST: the host:port for the Consul local agent.

PATRONI_CONSUL_URL: url for the Consul local agent, in format: http(s)://host:port

PATRONI_CONSUL_PORT: (optional) Consul port

PATRONI_CONSUL_SCHEME: (optional) http or https, defaults to http

PATRONI_CONSUL_TOKEN: (optional) ACL token

PATRONI_CONSUL_VERIFY: (optional) whether to verify the SSL certificate for HTTPS requests

PATRONI_CONSUL_CACERT: (optional) The ca certificate. If present it will enable validation.

PATRONI_CONSUL_CERT: (optional) File with the client certificate

PATRONI_CONSUL_KEY: (optional) File with the client key. Can be empty if the key is part of certificate.

PATRONI_CONSUL_DC: (optional) Datacenter to communicate with. By default the datacenter of the host is used.

PATRONI_CONSUL_CONSISTENCY: (optional) Select consul consistency mode. Possible values are default, consistent, or stale (more details in consul API reference [https://www.consul.io/api/features/consistency.html/])

PATRONI_CONSUL_CHECKS: (optional) list of Consul health checks used for the session. By default an empty list is used.

PATRONI_CONSUL_REGISTER_SERVICE: (optional) whether or not to register a service with the name defined by the scope parameter and the tag master, primary, replica, or standby-leader depending on the node’s role. Defaults to false

PATRONI_CONSUL_SERVICE_TAGS: (optional) additional static tags to add to the Consul service apart from the role (primary/replica/standby-leader). By default an empty list is used.

PATRONI_CONSUL_SERVICE_CHECK_INTERVAL: (optional) how often to perform health check against registered url

PATRONI_CONSUL_SERVICE_CHECK_TLS_SERVER_NAME: (optional) override SNI host when connecting via TLS, see also consul agent check API reference [https://www.consul.io/api-docs/agent/check#tlsservername].

Etcd

PATRONI_ETCD_PROXY: proxy url for the etcd. If you are connecting to the etcd using proxy, use this parameter instead of PATRONI_ETCD_URL

PATRONI_ETCD_URL: url for the etcd, in format: http(s)://(username:password@)host:port

PATRONI_ETCD_HOSTS: list of etcd endpoints in format ‘host1:port1’,’host2:port2’,etc…

PATRONI_ETCD_USE_PROXIES: If this parameter is set to true, Patroni will consider hosts as a list of proxies and will not perform a topology discovery of etcd cluster but stick to a fixed list of hosts.

PATRONI_ETCD_PROTOCOL: http or https, if not specified http is used. If the url or proxy is specified - will take protocol from them.

PATRONI_ETCD_HOST: the host:port for the etcd endpoint.

PATRONI_ETCD_SRV: Domain to search the SRV record(s) for cluster autodiscovery. Patroni will try to query these SRV service names for specified domain (in that order until first success): _etcd-client-ssl, _etcd-client, _etcd-ssl, _etcd, _etcd-server-ssl, _etcd-server. If SRV records for _etcd-server-ssl or _etcd-server are retrieved then ETCD peer protocol is used do query ETCD for available members. Otherwise hosts from SRV records will be used.

PATRONI_ETCD_SRV_SUFFIX: Configures a suffix to the SRV name that is queried during discovery. Use this flag to differentiate between multiple etcd clusters under the same domain. Works only with conjunction with PATRONI_ETCD_SRV. For example, if PATRONI_ETCD_SRV_SUFFIX=foo and PATRONI_ETCD_SRV=example.org are set, the following DNS SRV query is made:_etcd-client-ssl-foo._tcp.example.com (and so on for every possible ETCD SRV service name).

PATRONI_ETCD_USERNAME: username for etcd authentication.

PATRONI_ETCD_PASSWORD: password for etcd authentication.

PATRONI_ETCD_CACERT: The ca certificate. If present it will enable validation.

PATRONI_ETCD_CERT: File with the client certificate.

PATRONI_ETCD_KEY: File with the client key. Can be empty if the key is part of certificate.

Etcdv3

Environment names for Etcdv3 are similar as for Etcd, you just need to use ETCD3 instead of ETCD in the variable name. Example: PATRONI_ETCD3_HOST, PATRONI_ETCD3_CACERT, and so on.

Warning

Keys created with protocol version 2 are not visible with protocol version 3 and the other way around, therefore it is not possible to switch from Etcd to Etcdv3 just by updating Patroni configuration. In addition, Patroni uses Etcd’s gRPC-gateway (proxy) to communicate with the V3 API, which means that TLS common name authentication is not possible.

ZooKeeper

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_HOSTS: Comma separated list of ZooKeeper cluster members: “‘host1:port1’,’host2:port2’,’etc…’”. It is important to quote every single entity!

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_USE_SSL: (optional) Whether SSL is used or not. Defaults to false. If set to false, all SSL specific parameters are ignored.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_CACERT: (optional) The CA certificate. If present it will enable validation.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_CERT: (optional) File with the client certificate.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_KEY: (optional) File with the client key.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_KEY_PASSWORD: (optional) The client key password.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_VERIFY: (optional) Whether to verify certificate or not. Defaults to true.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_SET_ACLS: (optional) If set, configure Kazoo to apply a default ACL to each ZNode that it creates. ACLs will assume ‘x509’ schema and should be specified as a dictionary with the principal as the key and one or more permissions as a list in the value. Permissions may be one of CREATE, READ, WRITE, DELETE or ADMIN. For example, set_acls: {CN=principal1: [CREATE, READ], CN=principal2: [ALL]}.

PATRONI_ZOOKEEPER_AUTH_DATA: (optional) Authentication credentials to use for the connection. Should be a dictionary in the form that

scheme

is the key and

credential

is the value. Defaults to empty dictionary.

Note

It is required to install kazoo>=2.6.0 to support SSL.

Exhibitor

PATRONI_EXHIBITOR_HOSTS: initial list of Exhibitor (ZooKeeper) nodes in format: ‘host1,host2,etc…’. This list updates automatically whenever the Exhibitor (ZooKeeper) cluster topology changes.

PATRONI_EXHIBITOR_PORT: Exhibitor port.

Kubernetes

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_BYPASS_API_SERVICE: (optional) When communicating with the Kubernetes API, Patroni is usually relying on the

kubernetes

service, the address of which is exposed in the pods via the

KUBERNETES_SERVICE_HOST

environment variable. If

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_BYPASS_API_SERVICE

is set to true, Patroni will resolve the list of API nodes behind the service and connect directly to them.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_NAMESPACE: (optional) Kubernetes namespace where the Patroni pod is running. Default value is

default

.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_LABELS: Labels in format {label1: value1, label2: value2}. These labels will be used to find existing objects (Pods and either Endpoints or ConfigMaps) associated with the current cluster. Also Patroni will set them on every object (Endpoint or ConfigMap) it creates.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_SCOPE_LABEL: (optional) name of the label containing cluster name. Default value is

cluster-name

.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_BOOTSTRAP_LABELS: (optional) Labels in format {label1: value1, label2: value2}. These labels will be assigned to a Patroni pod when its state is either initializing new cluster, running custom bootstrap script, starting after custom bootstrap or creating replica.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_ROLE_LABEL: (optional) name of the label containing role (

primary

,

replica

or other custom value). Patroni will set this label on the pod it runs in. Default value is role.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_LEADER_LABEL_VALUE: (optional) value of the pod label when Postgres role is

primary

. Default value is

primary

.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_FOLLOWER_LABEL_VALUE: (optional) value of the pod label when Postgres role is

replica

. Default value is

replica

.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_STANDBY_LEADER_LABEL_VALUE: (optional) value of the pod label when Postgres role is standby_leader. Default value is primary.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_TMP_ROLE_LABEL: (optional) name of the temporary label containing role (

primary

or

replica

). Value of this label will always use the default of corresponding role. Set only when necessary.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_USE_ENDPOINTS: (optional) if set to true, Patroni will use Endpoints instead of ConfigMaps to run leader elections and keep cluster state.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_POD_IP: (optional) IP address of the pod Patroni is running in. This value is required when

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_USE_ENDPOINTS

is enabled and is used to populate the leader endpoint subsets when the pod’s PostgreSQL is promoted.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_PORTS: (optional) if the Service object has the name for the port, the same name must appear in the Endpoint object, otherwise service won’t work. For example, if your service is defined as {Kind: Service, spec: {ports: [{name: postgresql, port: 5432, targetPort: 5432}]}}, then you have to set PATRONI_KUBERNETES_PORTS='[{"name": "postgresql", "port": 5432}]' and Patroni will use it for updating subsets of the leader Endpoint. This parameter is used only if

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_USE_ENDPOINTS

is set.

PATRONI_KUBERNETES_CACERT: (optional) Specifies the file with the CA_BUNDLE file with certificates of trusted CAs to use while verifying Kubernetes API SSL certs. If not provided, patroni will use the value provided by the ServiceAccount secret.

PATRONI_RETRIABLE_HTTP_CODES: (optional) list of HTTP status codes from K8s API to retry on. By default Patroni is retrying on 500, 503, and 504, or if K8s API response has retry-after HTTP header.

Raft (deprecated)

PATRONI_RAFT_SELF_ADDR: ip:port to listen on for Raft connections. The self_addr must be accessible from other nodes of the cluster. If not set, the node will not participate in consensus.

PATRONI_RAFT_BIND_ADDR: (optional) ip:port to listen on for Raft connections. If not specified the self_addr will be used.

PATRONI_RAFT_PARTNER_ADDRS: list of other Patroni nodes in the cluster in format "'ip1:port1','ip2:port2'". It is important to quote every single entity!

PATRONI_RAFT_DATA_DIR: directory where to store Raft log and snapshot. If not specified the current working directory is used.

PATRONI_RAFT_PASSWORD: (optional) Encrypt Raft traffic with a specified password, requires cryptography python module.

PostgreSQL

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_LISTEN: IP address + port that Postgres listens to. Multiple comma-separated addresses are permitted, as long as the port component is appended after to the last one with a colon, i.e. listen: 127.0.0.1,127.0.0.2:5432. Patroni will use the first address from this list to establish local connections to the PostgreSQL node.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_CONNECT_ADDRESS: IP address + port through which Postgres is accessible from other nodes and applications.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_PROXY_ADDRESS: IP address + port through which a connection pool (e.g. pgbouncer) running next to Postgres is accessible. The value is written to the member key in DCS as proxy_url and could be used/useful for service discovery.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_DATA_DIR: The location of the Postgres data directory, either existing or to be initialized by Patroni.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_CONFIG_DIR: The location of the Postgres configuration directory, defaults to the data directory. Must be writable by Patroni.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_DIR: Path to PostgreSQL binaries. (pg_ctl, initdb, pg_controldata, pg_basebackup, postgres, pg_isready, pg_rewind) The default value is an empty string meaning that PATH environment variable will be used to find the executables.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_PG_CTL: (optional) Custom name for pg_ctl binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_INITDB: (optional) Custom name for initdb binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_PG_CONTROLDATA: (optional) Custom name for pg_controldata binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_PG_BASEBACKUP: (optional) Custom name for pg_basebackup binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_POSTGRES: (optional) Custom name for postgres binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_IS_READY: (optional) Custom name for pg_isready binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_PG_REWIND: (optional) Custom name for pg_rewind binary.

PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_PGPASS: path to the .pgpass [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/static/libpq-pgpass.html] password file. Patroni creates this file before executing pg_basebackup and under some other circumstances. The location must be writable by Patroni.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_USERNAME: replication username; the user will be created during initialization. Replicas will use this user to access the replication source via streaming replication

PATRONI_REPLICATION_PASSWORD: replication password; the user will be created during initialization.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLMODE: (optional) maps to the sslmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLMODE] connection parameter, which allows a client to specify the type of TLS negotiation mode with the server. For more information on how each mode works, please visit the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-ssl.html#LIBPQ-SSL-SSLMODE-STATEMENTS]. The default mode is prefer.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLKEY: (optional) maps to the sslkey [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLKEY] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the secret key used with the client’s certificate.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLPASSWORD: (optional) maps to the sslpassword [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLPASSWORD] connection parameter, which specifies the password for the secret key specified in PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLKEY.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLCERT: (optional) maps to the sslcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the client certificate.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLROOTCERT: (optional) maps to the sslrootcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLROOTCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing one or more certificate authorities (CA) certificates that the client will use to verify a server’s certificate.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLCRL: (optional) maps to the sslcrl [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRL] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLCRLDIR: (optional) maps to the sslcrldir [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRLDIR] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a directory with files containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_SSLNEGOTIATION: (optional) maps to the sslnegotiation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLNEGOTIATION] connection parameter, which controls how SSL encryption is negotiated with the server, if SSL is used.

PATRONI_REPLICATION_GSSENCMODE: (optional) maps to the gssencmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-GSSENCMODE] connection parameter, which determines whether or with what priority a secure GSS TCP/IP connection will be negotiated with the server

PATRONI_REPLICATION_CHANNEL_BINDING: (optional) maps to the channel_binding [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-CHANNEL-BINDING] connection parameter, which controls the client’s use of channel binding.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_USERNAME: name for the superuser, set during initialization (initdb) and later used by Patroni to connect to the postgres. Also this user is used by pg_rewind.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_PASSWORD: password for the superuser, set during initialization (initdb).

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLMODE: (optional) maps to the sslmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLMODE] connection parameter, which allows a client to specify the type of TLS negotiation mode with the server. For more information on how each mode works, please visit the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-ssl.html#LIBPQ-SSL-SSLMODE-STATEMENTS]. The default mode is prefer.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLKEY: (optional) maps to the sslkey [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLKEY] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the secret key used with the client’s certificate.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLPASSWORD: (optional) maps to the sslpassword [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLPASSWORD] connection parameter, which specifies the password for the secret key specified in PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLKEY.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLCERT: (optional) maps to the sslcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the client certificate.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLROOTCERT: (optional) maps to the sslrootcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLROOTCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing one or more certificate authorities (CA) certificates that the client will use to verify a server’s certificate.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLCRL: (optional) maps to the sslcrl [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRL] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLCRLDIR: (optional) maps to the sslcrldir [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRLDIR] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a directory with files containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_SSLNEGOTIATION: (optional) maps to the sslnegotiation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLNEGOTIATION] connection parameter, which controls how SSL encryption is negotiated with the server, if SSL is used.

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_GSSENCMODE: (optional) maps to the gssencmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-GSSENCMODE] connection parameter, which determines whether or with what priority a secure GSS TCP/IP connection will be negotiated with the server

PATRONI_SUPERUSER_CHANNEL_BINDING: (optional) maps to the channel_binding [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-CHANNEL-BINDING] connection parameter, which controls the client’s use of channel binding.

PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME: (optional) name for the user for pg_rewind; the user will be created during initialization of postgres 11+ and all necessary permissions [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/11/app-pgrewind.html#id-1.9.5.8.8] will be granted.

PATRONI_REWIND_PASSWORD: (optional) password for the user for pg_rewind; the user will be created during initialization.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLMODE: (optional) maps to the sslmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLMODE] connection parameter, which allows a client to specify the type of TLS negotiation mode with the server. For more information on how each mode works, please visit the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-ssl.html#LIBPQ-SSL-SSLMODE-STATEMENTS]. The default mode is prefer.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLKEY: (optional) maps to the sslkey [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLKEY] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the secret key used with the client’s certificate.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLPASSWORD: (optional) maps to the sslpassword [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLPASSWORD] connection parameter, which specifies the password for the secret key specified in PATRONI_REWIND_SSLKEY.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLCERT: (optional) maps to the sslcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the client certificate.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLROOTCERT: (optional) maps to the sslrootcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLROOTCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing one or more certificate authorities (CA) certificates that the client will use to verify a server’s certificate.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLCRL: (optional) maps to the sslcrl [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRL] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLCRLDIR: (optional) maps to the sslcrldir [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRLDIR] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a directory with files containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

PATRONI_REWIND_SSLNEGOTIATION: (optional) maps to the sslnegotiation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLNEGOTIATION] connection parameter, which controls how SSL encryption is negotiated with the server, if SSL is used.

PATRONI_REWIND_GSSENCMODE: (optional) maps to the gssencmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-GSSENCMODE] connection parameter, which determines whether or with what priority a secure GSS TCP/IP connection will be negotiated with the server

PATRONI_REWIND_CHANNEL_BINDING: (optional) maps to the channel_binding [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-CHANNEL-BINDING] connection parameter, which controls the client’s use of channel binding.

REST API

PATRONI_RESTAPI_THREAD_POOL_SIZE: size of thread pool used by Patroni to process REST API requests. Minimal value is 5, default value is 5.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_CONNECT_ADDRESS: IP address and port to access the REST API.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_LISTEN: IP address and port that Patroni will listen to, to provide health-check information for HAProxy.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_USERNAME: Basic-auth username to protect unsafe REST API endpoints.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_PASSWORD: Basic-auth password to protect unsafe REST API endpoints.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_CERTFILE: Specifies the file with the certificate in the PEM format. If the certfile is not specified or is left empty, the API server will work without SSL.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_KEYFILE: Specifies the file with the secret key in the PEM format.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_KEYFILE_PASSWORD: Specifies a password for decrypting the keyfile.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_CAFILE: Specifies the file with the CA_BUNDLE with certificates of trusted CAs to use while verifying client certs.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_CIPHERS: (optional) Specifies the permitted cipher suites (e.g. “ECDHE-RSA-AES256-GCM-SHA384:DHE-RSA-AES256-GCM-SHA384:ECDHE-RSA-AES128-GCM-SHA256:DHE-RSA-AES128-GCM-SHA256:!SSLv1:!SSLv2:!SSLv3:!TLSv1:!TLSv1.1”)

PATRONI_RESTAPI_VERIFY_CLIENT: none (default), optional or required. When none REST API will not check client certificates. When required client certificates are required for all REST API calls. When optional client certificates are required for all unsafe REST API endpoints. When required is used, then client authentication succeeds, if the certificate signature verification succeeds. For optional the client cert will only be checked for PUT, POST, PATCH, and DELETE requests.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_ALLOWLIST: (optional): Specifies the set of hosts that are allowed to call unsafe REST API endpoints. The single element could be a host name, an IP address or a network address using CIDR notation. By default allow all is used. In case if allowlist or allowlist_include_members are set, anything that is not included is rejected.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_ALLOWLIST_INCLUDE_MEMBERS: (optional): If set to true it allows accessing unsafe REST API endpoints from other cluster members registered in DCS (IP address or hostname is taken from the members api_url). Be careful, it might happen that OS will use a different IP for outgoing connections.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_HTTP_EXTRA_HEADERS: (optional) HTTP headers let the REST API server pass additional information with an HTTP response.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_HTTPS_EXTRA_HEADERS: (optional) HTTPS headers let the REST API server pass additional information with an HTTP response when TLS is enabled. This will also pass additional information set in http_extra_headers.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_REQUEST_QUEUE_SIZE: (optional): Sets request queue size for TCP socket used by Patroni REST API. Once the queue is full, further requests get a “Connection denied” error. The default value is 5.

PATRONI_RESTAPI_SERVER_TOKENS: (optional) Configures the value of the Server HTTP header. Original (default) will expose the original behaviour and display the BaseHTTP and Python versions, e.g. BaseHTTP/0.6 Python/3.12.3. Minimal: The header will contain only the Patroni version, e.g. Patroni/4.0.0. ProductOnly: The header will contain only the product name, e.g. Patroni.

Warning

The PATRONI_RESTAPI_CONNECT_ADDRESS must be accessible from all nodes of a given Patroni cluster. Internally Patroni is using it during the leader race to find nodes with minimal replication lag.

If you enabled client certificates validation (PATRONI_RESTAPI_VERIFY_CLIENT is set to required), you also must provide valid client certificates in the PATRONI_CTL_CERTFILE, PATRONI_CTL_KEYFILE, PATRONI_CTL_KEYFILE_PASSWORD. If not provided, Patroni will not work correctly.

CTL

PATRONICTL_CONFIG_FILE: (optional) location of the configuration file.

PATRONI_CTL_USERNAME: (optional) Basic-auth username for accessing protected REST API endpoints. If not provided patronictl will use the value provided for REST API “username” parameter.

PATRONI_CTL_PASSWORD: (optional) Basic-auth password for accessing protected REST API endpoints. If not provided patronictl will use the value provided for REST API “password” parameter.

PATRONI_CTL_INSECURE: (optional) Allow connections to REST API without verifying SSL certs.

PATRONI_CTL_CACERT: (optional) Specifies the file with the CA_BUNDLE file or directory with certificates of trusted CAs to use while verifying REST API SSL certs. If not provided patronictl will use the value provided for REST API “cafile” parameter.

PATRONI_CTL_CERTFILE: (optional) Specifies the file with the client certificate in the PEM format.

PATRONI_CTL_KEYFILE: (optional) Specifies the file with the client secret key in the PEM format.

PATRONI_CTL_KEYFILE_PASSWORD: (optional) Specifies a password for decrypting the client keyfile.

Convert a Standalone to a Patroni Cluster

This section describes the process for converting a standalone PostgreSQL instance into a Patroni cluster.

To deploy a Patroni cluster without using a pre-existing PostgreSQL instance, see Running and Configuring instead.

Procedure

You can find below an overview of steps for converting an existing Postgres cluster to a Patroni managed cluster. In the steps we assume all nodes that are part of the existing cluster are currently up and running, and that you do not intend to change Postgres configuration while the migration is ongoing. The steps:

Create the Postgres users as explained for authentication section of the Patroni configuration. You can find sample SQL commands to create the users in the code block below, in which you need to replace the usernames and passwords as per your environment. If you already have the relevant users, then you can skip this step.

-- Patroni superuser
-- Replace PATRONI_SUPERUSER_USERNAME and PATRONI_SUPERUSER_PASSWORD accordingly
CREATE USER PATRONI_SUPERUSER_USERNAME WITH SUPERUSER ENCRYPTED PASSWORD 'PATRONI_SUPERUSER_PASSWORD';

-- Patroni replication user
-- Replace PATRONI_REPLICATION_USERNAME and PATRONI_REPLICATION_PASSWORD accordingly
CREATE USER PATRONI_REPLICATION_USERNAME WITH REPLICATION ENCRYPTED PASSWORD 'PATRONI_REPLICATION_PASSWORD';

-- Patroni rewind user, if you intend to enable use_pg_rewind in your Patroni configuration
-- Replace PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME and PATRONI_REWIND_PASSWORD accordingly
CREATE USER PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME WITH ENCRYPTED PASSWORD 'PATRONI_REWIND_PASSWORD';
GRANT EXECUTE ON function pg_catalog.pg_ls_dir(text, boolean, boolean) TO PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME;
GRANT EXECUTE ON function pg_catalog.pg_stat_file(text, boolean) TO PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME;
GRANT EXECUTE ON function pg_catalog.pg_read_binary_file(text) TO PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME;
GRANT EXECUTE ON function pg_catalog.pg_read_binary_file(text, bigint, bigint, boolean) TO PATRONI_REWIND_USERNAME;

Perform the following steps on all Postgres nodes. Perform all steps on one node before proceeding with the next node. Start with the primary node, then proceed with each standby node:

If you are running Postgres through systemd, then disable the Postgres systemd unit. This is performed as Patroni manages starting and stopping the Postgres daemon.

Create a YAML configuration file for Patroni. You can use Patroni configuration generation and validation tooling for that.

Note (specific for the primary node): If you have replication slots being used for replication between cluster members, then it is recommended that you enable use_slots and configure the existing replication slots as permanent via the slots configuration item. Be aware that Patroni automatically creates replication slots for replication between members, and drops replication slots that it does not recognize, when use_slots is enabled. The idea of using permanent slots here is to allow your existing slots to persist while the migration to Patroni is in progress. See Dynamic Configuration Settings for details.

Start Patroni using the patroni systemd service unit. It automatically detects that Postgres is already running and starts monitoring the instance.

Hand over Postgres “start up procedure” to Patroni. In order to do that you need to restart the cluster members through patronictl restart cluster-name member-name command. For minimal downtime you might want to split this step into:

Immediate restart of the standby nodes.

Scheduled restart of the primary node within a maintenance window.

If you configured permanent slots in step 1.2., then you should remove them from slots configuration through patronictl edit-config cluster-name command once the restart_lsn of the slots created by Patroni is able to catch up with the restart_lsn of the original slots for the corresponding members. By removing the slots from slots configuration you will allow Patroni to drop the original slots from your cluster once they are not needed anymore. You can find below an example query to check the restart_lsn of a couple slots, so you can compare them:

-- Assume original_slot_for_member_x is the name of the slot in your original
-- cluster for replicating changes to member X, and slot_for_member_x is the
-- slot created by Patroni for that purpose. You need restart_lsn of
-- slot_for_member_x to be >= restart_lsn of original_slot_for_member_x
SELECT slot_name,
       restart_lsn
FROM pg_replication_slots
WHERE slot_name IN (
    'original_slot_for_member_x',
    'slot_for_member_x'
)

Major Upgrade of PostgreSQL Version

The only possible way to do a major upgrade currently is:

Stop Patroni

Upgrade PostgreSQL binaries and perform pg_upgrade [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/pgupgrade.html] on the primary node

Update patroni.yml

Remove the initialize key from DCS or wipe complete cluster state from DCS. The second one could be achieved by running patronictl remove cluster-name . It is necessary because pg_upgrade runs initdb which actually creates a new database with a new PostgreSQL system identifier.

If you wiped the cluster state in the previous step, you may wish to copy patroni.dynamic.json from old data dir to the new one. It will help you to retain some PostgreSQL parameters you had set before.

Start Patroni on the primary node.

Upgrade PostgreSQL binaries, update patroni.yml and wipe the data_dir on standby nodes.

Start Patroni on the standby nodes and wait for the replication to complete.

Running pg_upgrade on standby nodes is not supported by PostgreSQL. If you know what you are doing, you can try the rsync procedure described in https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/pgupgrade.html instead of wiping data_dir on standby nodes. The safest way is however to let Patroni replicate the data for you.

FAQ

During Patroni startup, Patroni complains that it cannot bind to the PostgreSQL port.

You need to verify listen_addresses and port in postgresql.conf and postgresql.listen in patroni.yml. Don’t forget that pg_hba.conf should allow such access.

After asking Patroni to restart the node, PostgreSQL displays the error message could not open configuration file "/etc/postgresql/10/main/pg_hba.conf": No such file or directory

It can mean various things depending on how you manage PostgreSQL configuration. If you specified

postgresql.config_dir

, Patroni generates the pg_hba.conf based on the settings in the bootstrap section only when it bootstraps a new cluster. In this scenario the PGDATA was not empty, therefore no bootstrap happened. This file must exist beforehand.

FAQ

In this section you will find answers for the most frequently asked questions about Patroni. Each sub-section attempts to focus on different kinds of questions.

We hope that this helps you to clarify most of your questions. If you still have further concerns or find yourself facing an unexpected issue, please refer to Chatting and Reporting bugs for instructions on how to get help or report issues.

Comparison with other HA solutions

Why does Patroni require a separate cluster of DCS nodes while other solutions like repmgr do not?

There are different ways of implementing HA solutions, each of them with their pros and cons.

Software like repmgr performs communication among the nodes to decide when actions should be taken.

Patroni on the other hand relies on the state stored in the DCS. The DCS acts as a source of truth for Patroni to decide what it should do.

While having a separate DCS cluster can make you bloat your architecture, this approach also makes it less likely for split-brain scenarios to happen in your Postgres cluster.

What is the difference between Patroni and other HA solutions in regards to Postgres management?

Patroni does not just manage the high availability of the Postgres cluster but also manages Postgres itself.

If Postgres nodes do not exist yet, it takes care of bootstrapping the primary and the standby nodes, and also manages Postgres configuration of the nodes. If the Postgres nodes already exist, Patroni will take over management of the cluster.

Besides the above, Patroni also has self-healing capabilities. In other words, if a primary node fails, Patroni will not only fail over to a replica, but also attempt to rejoin the former primary as a replica of the new primary. Similarly, if a replica fails, Patroni will attempt to rejoin that replica.

That is way we call Patroni as a “template for HA solutions”. It goes further than just managing physical replication: it manages Postgres as a whole.

DCS

Can I use the same etcd cluster to store data from two or more Patroni clusters?

Yes, you can!

Information about a Patroni cluster is stored in the DCS under a path prefixed with the namespace and scope Patroni settings.

As long as you do not have conflicting namespace and scope across different Patroni clusters, you should be able to use the same DCS cluster to store information from multiple Patroni clusters.

What occurs if I attempt to use the same combination of namespace and scope for different Patroni clusters that point to the same DCS cluster?

The second Patroni cluster that attempts to use the same namespace and scope will not be able to manage Postgres because it will find information related with that same combination in the DCS, but with an incompatible Postgres system identifier. The mismatch on the system identifier causes Patroni to abort the management of the second cluster, as it assumes that refers to a different cluster and that the user has misconfigured Patroni.

Make sure to use different namespace / scope when dealing with different Patroni clusters that share the same DCS cluster.

What occurs if I lose my DCS cluster?

The DCS is used to store basically status and the dynamic configuration of the Patroni cluster.

They very first consequence is that all the Patroni clusters that rely on that DCS will go to read-only mode – unless DCS Failsafe Mode is enabled.

What should I do if I lose my DCS cluster?

There are three possible outcomes upon losing your DCS cluster:

The DCS cluster is fully recovered: this requires no action from the Patroni side. Once the DCS cluster is recovered, Patroni should be able to recover too;

The DCS cluster is re-created in place, and the endpoints remain the same. No changes are required on the Patroni side;

A new DCS cluster is created with different endpoints. You will need to update the DCS endpoints in the Patroni configuration of each Patroni node.

If you face scenario 2. or 3. Patroni will take care of creating the status information again based on the current status of the cluster, and recreate the dynamic configuration on the DCS based on a backup file named patroni.dynamic.json which is stored inside the Postgres data directory of each member of the Patroni cluster.

What occurs if I lose majority in my DCS cluster?

The DCS will become unresponsive, which will cause Patroni to demote the current read/write Postgres node.

Remember: Patroni relies on the state of the DCS to take actions on the cluster.

You can use the DCS Failsafe Mode to alleviate that situation.

patronictl

Do I need to run patronictl in the Patroni host?

No, you do not need to do that.

Running patronictl in the Patroni host is handy if you have access to the Patroni host because you can use the very same configuration file from the patroni agent for the patronictl application.

However, patronictl is basically a client and it can be executed from remote machines. You just need to provide it with enough configuration so it can reach the DCS and the REST API of the Patroni member(s).

Why did the information from one of my Patroni members disappear from the output of patronictl list command?

Information shown by patronictl list is based on the contents of the DCS.

If information about a member disappeared from the DCS it is very likely that the Patroni agent on that node is not running anymore, or it is not able to communicate with the DCS.

As the member is not able to update the information, the information eventually expires from the DCS, and consequently the member is not shown anymore in the output of patronictl list.

Why is the information about one of my Patroni members not up-to-date in the output of patronictl list command?

Information shown by patronictl list is based on the contents of the DCS.

By default, that information is updated by Patroni roughly every loop_wait seconds. In other words, even if everything is normally functional you may still see a “delay” of up to loop_wait seconds in the information stored in the DCS.

Be aware that that is not a rule, though. Some operations performed by Patroni cause it to immediately update the DCS information.

Configuration

What is the difference between dynamic configuration and local configuration?

Dynamic configuration (or global configuration) is the configuration stored in the DCS, and which is applied to all members of the Patroni cluster. This is primarily where you should store your configuration.

Settings that are specific to a node, or settings that you would like to overwrite the global configuration with, you should set only on the desired Patroni member as a local configuration. That local configuration can be specified either through the configuration file or through environment variables.

See more in Patroni configuration.

What are the types of configuration in Patroni, and what is the precedence?

The types are:

Dynamic configuration: applied to all members;

Local configuration: applied to the local member, overrides dynamic configuration;

Environment configuration: applied to the local member, overrides both dynamic and local configuration.

Note: some Postgres GUCs can only be set globally, i.e., through dynamic configuration. Besides that, there are GUCs which Patroni enforces a hard-coded value.

See more in Patroni configuration.

Is there any facility to help me create my Patroni configuration file?

Yes, there is.

You can use patroni --generate-sample-config or patroni --generate-config commands to generate a sample Patroni configuration or a Patroni configuration based on an existing Postgres instance, respectively.

Please refer to Sample Patroni configuration and Patroni configuration for a running instance for more details.

I changed my parameters under bootstrap.dcs configuration but Patroni is not applying the changes to the cluster members. What is wrong?

The values configured under bootstrap.dcs are only used when bootstrapping a fresh cluster. Those values will be written to the DCS during the bootstrap.

After the bootstrap phase finishes, you will only be able to change the dynamic configuration through the DCS.

Refer to the next question for more details.

How can I change my dynamic configuration?

You need to change the configuration in the DCS. That is accomplished either through:

patronictl edit-config; or

A PATCH request to Config endpoint.

How can I change my local configuration?

You need to change the configuration file of the corresponding Patroni member and signal the Patroni agent with SIHGUP. You can do that using either of these approaches:

Send a POST request to the REST API Reload endpoint; or

Run patronictl reload; or

Locally signal the Patroni process with SIGHUP:

If you started Patroni through systemd, you can use the command systemctl reload PATRONI_UNIT.service, PATRONI_UNIT being the name of the Patroni service; or

If you started Patroni through other means, you will need to identify the patroni process and run kill -s HUP PID, PID being the process ID of the patroni process.

Note: there are cases where a reload through the patronictl reload may not work:

Expired REST API certificates: you can mitigate that by using the -k option of the patronictl;

Wrong credentials: for example when changing restapi or ctl credentials in the configuration file, and using that same configuration file for Patroni and patronictl.

How can I change my environment configuration?

The environment configuration is only read by Patroni during startup.

With that in mind, if you change the environment configuration you will need to restart the corresponding Patroni agent.

Take care to not cause a failover in the cluster! You might be interested in checking patronictl pause.

How can I reduce repetitive heartbeat log lines during normal operation?

If your logs are too noisy because of repeated lines like Lock owner: ... and no action. I am ..., configure log.deduplicate_heartbeat_logs: true.

You can set it either in the Patroni YAML file (Log) or with PATRONI_LOG_DEDUPLICATE_HEARTBEAT_LOGS=true.

Keep in mind this reduces log volume by suppressing repeated heartbeat messages, but you also lose per-loop heartbeat visibility that can help during failover diagnostics.

What occurs if I change a Postgres GUC that requires a reload?

When you change the dynamic or the local configuration as explained in the previous questions, Patroni will take care of reloading the Postgres configuration for you.

What occurs if I change a Postgres GUC that requires a restart?

Patroni will mark the affected members with a flag of pending restart.

It is up to you to determine when and how to restart the members. That can be accomplished either through:

patronictl restart; or

A POST request to Restart endpoint.

Note: some Postgres GUCs require a special management in terms of the order for restarting the Postgres nodes. Refer to PostgreSQL parameters that touch shared memory for more details.

What is the difference between etcd and etcd3 in Patroni configuration?

etcd uses the API version 2 of etcd, while etcd3 uses the API version 3 of etcd.

Be aware that information stored by the API version 2 is not manageable by API version 3 and vice-versa.

We recommend that you configure etcd3 instead of etcd because:

API version 2 is disabled by default from Etcd v3.4 onward;

API version 2 will be completely removed on Etcd v3.6.

I have use_slots enabled in my Patroni configuration, but when a cluster member goes offline for some time, the replication slot used by that member is dropped on the upstream node. What can I do to avoid that issue?

There are two options:

You can tune member_slots_ttl (default value 30min, available since Patroni 4.0.0 and PostgreSQL 11 onwards) and replication slots for absent members will not be removed when the members downtime is shorter than the configured threshold.

You can configure permanent physical replication slots for the members.

Since Patroni 3.2.0 it is now possible to have member slots as permanent slots managed by Patroni.

Patroni will create the permanent physical slots on all nodes, and make sure to not remove the slots, as well as to advance the slots’ LSN on all nodes according to the LSN that has been consumed by the member.

Later, if you decide to remove the corresponding member, it’s your responsibility to adjust the permanent slots configuration, otherwise Patroni will keep the slots around forever.

Note: on Patroni older than 3.2.0 you could still have member slots configured as permanent physical slots, however they would be managed only on the current leader. That is, in case of failover/switchover these slots would be created on the new leader, but that wouldn’t guarantee that it had all WAL segments for the absent node.

Note: even with Patroni 3.2.0 there might be a small race condition. In the very beginning, when the slot is created on the replica it could be ahead of the same slot on the leader and in case if nobody is consuming the slot there is still a chance that some files could be missing after failover. With that in mind, it is recommended that you configure continuous archiving, which makes it possible to restore required WALs or perform PITR.

What is the difference between loop_wait, retry_timeout and ttl?

Patroni performs what we call a HA cycle from time to time. On each HA cycle it takes care of performing a series of checks on the cluster to determine its healthiness, and depending on the status it may take actions, like failing over to a standby.

loop_wait determines for how long, in seconds, Patroni should sleep before performing a new cycle of HA checks.

retry_timeout sets the timeout for retry operations on the DCS and on Postgres. For example: if the DCS is unresponsive for more than retry_timeout seconds, Patroni might demote the primary node as a security action.

ttl sets the lease time on the leader lock in the DCS. If the current leader of the cluster is not able to renew the lease during its HA cycles for longer than ttl, then the lease will expire and that will trigger a leader race in the cluster.

Note: when modifying these settings, please keep in mind that Patroni enforces the rule and minimal values described in Dynamic Configuration Settings section of the docs.

Postgres management

Can I change Postgres GUCs directly in Postgres configuration?

You can, but you should avoid that.

Postgres configuration is managed by Patroni, and attempts to edit the configuration files may end up being frustrated by Patroni as it may eventually overwrite them.

There are a few options available to overcome the management performed by Patroni:

Change Postgres GUCs through $PGDATA/postgresql.base.conf; or

Define a postgresql.custom_conf which will be used instead of postgresql.base.conf so you can manage that externally; or

Change GUCs using ALTER SYSTEM / ALTER DATABASE / ALTER USER.

You can find more information about that in the section Important rules.

In any case we recommend that you manage all the Postgres configuration through Patroni. That will centralize the management and make it easier to debug Patroni when needed.

Can I restart Postgres nodes directly?

No, you should not attempt to manage Postgres directly!

Any attempt of bouncing the Postgres server without Patroni can lead your cluster to face failovers.

If you need to manage the Postgres server, do that through the ways exposed by Patroni.

Is Patroni able to take over management of an already existing Postgres cluster?

Yes, it can!

Please refer to Convert a Standalone to a Patroni Cluster for detailed instructions.

How does Patroni manage Postgres?

Patroni takes care of bringing Postgres up and down by running the Postgres binaries, like pg_ctl and postgres.

With that in mind you MUST disable any other sources that could manage the Postgres clusters, like the systemd units, e.g. postgresql.service. Only Patroni should be able to start, stop and promote Postgres instances in the cluster. Not doing so may result in split-brain scenarios. For example: if the node running as a primary failed and the unit postgresql.service is enabled, it may bring Postgres back up and cause a split-brain.

Concepts and requirements

Which are the applications that make part of Patroni?

Patroni basically ships a couple applications:

patroni: This is the Patroni agent, which takes care of managing a Postgres node;

patronictl: This is a command-line utility used to interact with a Patroni cluster (perform switchovers, restarts, changes in the configuration, etc.). Please find more information in patronictl.

What is a standby cluster in Patroni?

It is a cluster that does not have any primary Postgres node running, i.e., there is no read/write member in the cluster.

These kinds of clusters exist to replicate data from another cluster and are usually useful when you want to replicate data across data centers.

There will be a leader in the cluster which will be a standby in charge of replicating changes from a remote Postgres node. Then, there will be a set of standbys configured with cascading replication from such leader member.

Note: the standby cluster doesn’t know anything about the source cluster which it is replicating from – it can even use restore_command instead of WAL streaming, and may use an absolutely independent DCS cluster.

Refer to Standby cluster for more details.

What is a leader in Patroni?

A leader in Patroni is like a coordinator of the cluster.

In a regular Patroni cluster, the leader will be the read/write node.

In a standby Patroni cluster, the leader (AKA standby leader) will be in charge of replicating from a remote Postgres node, and cascading those changes to the other members of the standby cluster.

Does Patroni require a minimum number of Postgres nodes in the cluster?

No, you can run Patroni with any number of Postgres nodes.

Remember: Patroni is decoupled from the DCS.

What does pause mean in Patroni?

Pause is an operation exposed by Patroni so the user can ask Patroni to step back in regards to Postgres management.

That is mainly useful when you want to perform maintenance on the cluster, and would like to avoid that Patroni takes decisions related with HA, like failing over to a standby when you stop the primary.

You can find more information about that in Pause/Resume mode for the cluster.

Automatic failover

How does the automatic failover mechanism of Patroni work?

Patroni automatic failover is based on what we call leader race.

Patroni stores the cluster’s status in the DCS, among them a leader lock which holds the name of the Patroni member which is the current leader of the cluster.

That leader lock has a time-to-live associated with it. If the leader node fails to update the lease of the leader lock in time, the key will eventually expire from the DCS.

When the leader lock expires, it triggers what Patroni calls a leader race: all nodes start performing checks to determine if they are the best candidates for taking over the leader role. Some of these checks include calls to the REST API of all other Patroni members.

All Patroni members that find themselves as the best candidate for taking over the leader lock will attempt to do so. The first Patroni member that is able to take the leader lock will promote itself to a read/write node (or standby leader), and the others will be configured to follow it.

Can I temporarily disable automatic failover in the Patroni cluster?

Yes, you can!

You can achieve that by temporarily pausing the cluster. This is typically useful for performing maintenance.

When you want to resume the automatic failover of the cluster, you just need to unpause it.

You can find more information about that in Pause/Resume mode for the cluster.

Bootstrapping and standbys creation

How does Patroni create a primary Postgres node? What about a standby Postgres node?

By default Patroni will use initdb to bootstrap a fresh cluster, and pg_basebackup to create standby nodes from a copy of the leader member.

You can customize that behavior by writing your custom bootstrap methods, and your custom replica creation methods.

Custom methods are usually useful when you want to restore backups created by backup tools like pgBackRest or Barman, for example.

For detailed information please refer to Bootstrap and Building replicas.

Monitoring

How can I monitor my Patroni cluster?

Patroni exposes a couple handy endpoints in its Patroni REST API:

/metrics: exposes monitoring metrics in a format that can be consumed by Prometheus;

/patroni: exposes the status of the cluster in a JSON format. The information shown here is very similar to what is shown by the /metrics endpoint.

You can use those endpoints to implement monitoring checks.

MySQL backend

Where is the MySQL HA documentation?

See the MySQL chapter:

MySQL architecture and model — components and DCS model

MySQL HA mechanisms and sequences — failover / demote / semi-sync / MGR sequences

MySQL operations and FAQ — install, deploy, HAProxy, FAQ

Does MySQL support the same standby cluster feature as PostgreSQL?

Yes, with a MySQL-native implementation. Configure DCS standby_cluster with host / port of the remote primary. The standby leader is bootstrapped with a full physical/logical clone (default xtrabackup, then mysqldump) because remote binlogs alone may not cover the full dataset; then it streams via GTID cascade (CHANGE MASTER … MASTER_AUTO_POSITION=1) and stays super_read_only. Local members cascade from the standby leader. Promote with patronictl promote-cluster (removes standby_cluster). PostgreSQL restore_command / replication-slot standby modes are not used.

For promote / demote drills and cross-site cutover checklists, see MySQL operations and FAQ (section Standby cluster).

Installation

Pre-requirements for Mac OS

To install requirements on a Mac, run the following:

brew install postgresql etcd haproxy libyaml python

Psycopg

Starting from psycopg2-2.8 [http://initd.org/psycopg/articles/2019/04/04/psycopg-28-released/] the binary version of psycopg2 will no longer be installed by default. Installing it from the source code requires C compiler and postgres+python dev packages. Since in the python world it is not possible to specify dependency as psycopg2 OR psycopg2-binary you will have to decide how to install it.

There are a few options available:

Use the package manager from your distro

sudo apt-get install python3-psycopg2  # install psycopg2 module on Debian/Ubuntu
sudo yum install python3-psycopg2      # install psycopg2 on RedHat/Fedora/CentOS

Specify one of

psycopg

,

psycopg2

, or

psycopg2-binary

in the list of dependencies when installing Patroni with pip.

General installation for pip

Patroni can be installed with pip:

pip install patroni[dependencies]

where dependencies can be either empty, or consist of one or more of the following:

etcd or etcd3

python-etcd

module in order to use Etcd as Distributed Configuration Store (DCS)

consul

py-consul

module in order to use Consul as DCS

zookeeper

kazoo

module in order to use Zookeeper as DCS

exhibitor

kazoo

module in order to use Exhibitor as DCS (same dependencies as for Zookeeper)

kubernetes

kubernetes

module in order to use Kubernetes as DCS in Patroni

raft

pysyncobj

module in order to use python Raft implementation as DCS

aws

boto3

in order to use AWS callbacks

jsonlogger

python-json-logger

module in order to enable logging in json format

systemd

systemd-python

in order to use sd_notify integration

mysql

pymysql

in order to use the MySQL backend (database.type: mysql)

all

all of the above (except psycopg family)

psycopg3

psycopg[binary]>=3.0.0

module

psycopg2

psycopg2>=2.5.4

module

psycopg2-binary

psycopg2-binary

module

For example, the command in order to install Patroni together with psycopg3, dependencies for Etcd as a DCS, and AWS callbacks is:

pip install patroni[psycopg3,etcd3,aws]

To install MySQL support with etcd3:

pip install 'patroni[mysql,etcd3]'

Note that external tools to call in the replica creation or custom bootstrap scripts (i.e. WAL-E) should be installed independently of Patroni.

Package installation on Linux

Patroni packages may be available for your operating system, produced by the Postgres community for:

RHEL, RockyLinux, AlmaLinux;

Debian and Ubuntu;

SUSE Enterprise Linux.

You can also find packages for direct dependencies of Patroni, like python modules that might not be available in the official operating system repositories.

For more information see the PGDG repository [https://www.postgresql.org/download/linux/] documentation.

If you are on a RedHat Enterprise Linux derivative operating system you may also require packages from EPEL, see EPEL repository [https://docs.fedoraproject.org/en-US/epel/] documentation.

Once you have installed the PGDG repository for your OS you can install patroni.

Note

Patroni packages are not maintained by the Patroni developers, but rather by the Postgres community. If you require support please first try connecting on Postgres slack [http://pgtreats.info/slack-invite].

Installing on Debian derivatives

With PGDG repo installed, see above, install Patroni via apt run:

apt-get install patroni

Installing on RedHat derivatives

With PGDG repo installed, see above, install patroni with an etcd DCS via dnf on RHEL 9 (and derivatives) run:

dnf install patroni patroni-etcd

You can install etcd from PGDG if your RedHat derivative distribution does not provide packages. On the nodes that will host the DCS run:

dnf install 'dnf-command(config-manager)'
dnf config-manager --enable pgdg-rhel9-extras
dnf install etcd

You can replace the version of RHEL with

8

in the repo to make

pgdg-rhel8-extras

if needed. The repo name is still

pgdg-rhelN-extras

on RockyLinux, AlmaLinux, Oracle Linux, etc…

Installing on SUSE Enterprise Linux

You might need to enable the SUSE PackageHub repositories for some dependencies. see SUSE PackageHub [https://packagehub.suse.com/how-to-use/] documentation.

For SLES 15 with PGDG repo installed, see above, you can install patroni using:

zypper install patroni patroni-etcd

With the SUSE PackageHub repo enabled you can also install etcd:

SUSEConnect -p PackageHub/15.5/x86_64
zypper install etcd

Upgrading

Upgrading patroni is a very simple process, just update the software installation and restart the Patroni daemon on each node in the cluster.

However, restarting the Patroni daemon will result in a Postgres database restart. In some situations this may cause a failover of the primary node in your cluster, therefore it is recommended to put the cluster into maintenance mode until the Patroni daemon restart has been completed.

To put the cluster in maintenance mode, run the following command on one of the patroni nodes:

patronictl pause --wait

Then on each node in the cluster, perform the package upgrade required for your OS:

apt-get update && apt-get install patroni patroni-etcd

Restart the patroni daemon process on each node:

systemctl restart patroni

Then finally resume monitoring of Postgres with patroni to take it out of maintenance mode:

patronictl resume --wait

The cluster will now be full operational with the new version of Patroni.

Patroni configuration

There are 3 types of Patroni configuration:

Global dynamic configuration.

These options are stored in the DCS (Distributed Configuration Store) and applied on all cluster nodes. Dynamic configuration can be set at any time using patronictl edit-config tool or Patroni REST API. If the options changed are not part of the startup configuration, they are applied asynchronously (upon the next wake up cycle) to every node, which gets subsequently reloaded. If the node requires a restart to apply the configuration (for PostgreSQL parameters [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/view-pg-settings.html] with context postmaster, if their values have changed), a special flag pending_restart indicating this is set in the members.data JSON. Additionally, the node status indicates this by showing "restart_pending": true.

Local configuration file (patroni.yml).

These options are defined in the configuration file and take precedence over dynamic configuration. patroni.yml can be changed and reloaded at runtime (without restart of Patroni) by sending SIGHUP to the Patroni process, performing POST /reload REST-API request or executing patronictl reload. Local configuration can be either a single YAML file or a directory. When it is a directory, all YAML files in that directory are loaded one by one in sorted order. In case a key is defined in multiple files, the occurrence in the last file takes precedence.

Environment configuration.

It is possible to set/override some of the “Local” configuration parameters with environment variables. Environment configuration is very useful when you are running in a dynamic environment and you don’t know some of the parameters in advance (for example it’s not possible to know your external IP address when you are running inside docker).

Important rules

PostgreSQL parameters controlled by Patroni

Some of the PostgreSQL parameters must hold the same values on the primary and the replicas. For those, values set either in the local patroni configuration files or via the environment variables take no effect. To alter or set their values one must change the shared configuration in the DCS. Below is the actual list of such parameters together with the default and minimal values:

max_connections: default value 100, minimal value 25

max_locks_per_transaction: default value 64, minimal value 32

max_worker_processes: default value 8, minimal value 2

max_prepared_transactions: default value 0, minimal value 0

wal_level: default value hot_standby, accepted values: hot_standby, replica, logical

track_commit_timestamp: default value off

For the parameters below, PostgreSQL does not require equal values among the primary and all the replicas. However, considering the possibility of a replica to become the primary at any time, it doesn’t really make sense to set them differently; therefore, Patroni restricts setting their values to the dynamic configuration.

max_wal_senders: default value 10, minimal value 3

max_replication_slots: default value 10, minimal value 4

wal_keep_segments: default value 8, minimal value 1

wal_keep_size: default value 128MB, minimal value 16MB

wal_log_hints: on

These parameters are validated to ensure they are sane, or meet a minimum value.

There are some other Postgres parameters controlled by Patroni:

listen_addresses - is set either from postgresql.listen or from PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_LISTEN environment variable

port - is set either from postgresql.listen or from PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_LISTEN environment variable

cluster_name - is set either from scope or from PATRONI_SCOPE environment variable

hot_standby: on

To be on the safe side parameters from the above lists are written into postgresql.conf, and passed as a list of arguments to the postgres which gives them the highest precedence (except wal_keep_segments and wal_keep_size), even above ALTER SYSTEM [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/static/sql-altersystem.html]

There also are some parameters like postgresql.listen, postgresql.data_dir that can be set only locally, i.e. in the Patroni config file or via configuration variable. In most cases the local configuration will override the dynamic configuration.

When applying the local or dynamic configuration options, the following actions are taken:

The node first checks if there is a

postgresql.base.conf

file or if the custom_conf parameter is set.

If the custom_conf parameter is set, the file it specifies is used as the base configuration, ignoring

postgresql.base.conf

and

postgresql.conf

.

If the custom_conf parameter is not set and

postgresql.base.conf

exists, it contains the renamed “original” configuration and is used as the base configuration.

If there is no custom_conf nor

postgresql.base.conf

, the original

postgresql.conf

is renamed to

postgresql.base.conf

and used as the base configuration.

The dynamic options (with the exceptions above) are dumped into the

postgresql.conf

and an include is set in

postgresql.conf

to the base configuration (either

postgresql.base.conf

or the file at custom_conf). Therefore, we would be able to apply new options without re-reading the configuration file to check if the include is present or not.

Some parameters that are essential for Patroni to manage the cluster are overridden using the command line.

If an option that requires restart is changed (we should look at the context in pg_settings and at the actual values of those options), a pending_restart flag is set on that node. This flag is reset on any restart.

The parameters would be applied in the following order (run-time are given the highest priority):

load parameters from file

postgresql.base.conf

(or from a custom_conf file, if set)

load parameters from file

postgresql.conf

load parameters from file

postgresql.auto.conf

run-time parameter using

-o –name=value

This allows configuration for all the nodes (2), configuration for a specific node using ALTER SYSTEM (3) and ensures that parameters essential to the running of Patroni are enforced (4), as well as leaves room for configuration tools that manage

postgresql.conf

directly without involving Patroni (1).

PostgreSQL parameters that touch shared memory

PostgreSQL has some parameters that determine the size of the shared memory used by them:

max_connections

max_prepared_transactions

max_locks_per_transaction

max_wal_senders

max_worker_processes

Changing these parameters require a PostgreSQL restart to take effect, and their shared memory structures cannot be smaller on the standby nodes than on the primary node.

As explained before, Patroni restrict changing their values through dynamic configuration, which usually consists of:

Applying changes through patronictl edit-config (or via REST API /config endpoint)

Restarting nodes through patronictl restart (or via REST API /restart endpoint)

Note: please keep in mind that you should perform a restart of the PostgreSQL nodes through patronictl restart command, or via REST API /restart endpoint. An attempt to restart PostgreSQL by restarting the Patroni daemon, e.g. by executing systemctl restart patroni, can cause a failover to occur in the cluster, if you are restarting the primary node.

However, as those settings manage shared memory, some extra care should be taken when restarting the nodes:

If you want to increase the value of any of those settings:

Restart all standbys first

Restart the primary after that

If you want to decrease the value of any of those settings:

Restart the primary first

Restart all standbys after that

Note: if you attempt to restart all nodes in one go after decreasing the value of any of those settings, Patroni will ignore the change and restart the standby with the original setting value, thus requiring that you restart the standbys again later. Patroni does that to prevent the standby to enter in an infinite crash loop, because PostgreSQL quits with a

FATAL

message if you attempt to set any of those parameters to a value lower than what is visible in pg_controldata on the Standby node. In other words, we can only decrease the setting on the standby once its pg_controldata is up-to-date with the primary in regards to these changes on the primary.

More information about that can be found at PostgreSQL Administrator’s Overview [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/hot-standby.html#HOT-STANDBY-ADMIN].

Patroni configuration parameters

Also the following Patroni configuration options can be changed only dynamically:

ttl: 30

loop_wait: 10

retry_timeouts: 10

maximum_lag_on_failover: 1048576

max_timelines_history: 0

check_timeline: false

postgresql.use_slots: true

Upon changing these options, Patroni will read the relevant section of the configuration stored in DCS and change its run-time values.

Patroni nodes are dumping the state of the DCS options to disk upon for every change of the configuration into the file patroni.dynamic.json located in the Postgres data directory. Only the leader is allowed to restore these options from the on-disk dump if these are completely absent from the DCS or if they are invalid.

Configuration generation and validation

Patroni provides command-line interfaces for a Patroni local configuration generation and validation. Using the patroni executable you can:

Create a sample local Patroni configuration;

Create a Patroni configuration file for the locally running PostgreSQL instance (e.g. as a preparation step for the Patroni integration);

Validate a given Patroni configuration file.

Sample Patroni configuration

patroni --generate-sample-config [configfile]

Description

Generate a sample Patroni configuration file in yaml format. Parameter values are defined using the Environment configuration, otherwise, if not set, the defaults used in Patroni or the #FIXME string for the values that should be later defined by the user.

Some default values are defined based on the local setup:

postgresql.listen: the IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the standard 5432 port.

postgresql.connect_address: the IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the standard 5432 port.

postgresql.authentication.rewind: is only defined if the PostgreSQL version can be defined from the binary and the version is 11 or later.

restapi.listen: IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the standard 8008 port.

restapi.connect_address: IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the standard 8008 port.

Parameters

configfile - full path to the configuration file used to store the result. If not provided, the result is sent to stdout.

Patroni configuration for a running instance

patroni --generate-config [--dsn DSN] [configfile]

Description

Generate a Patroni configuration in yaml format for the locally running PostgreSQL instance. Either the provided DSN (takes precedence) or PostgreSQL environment variables [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-envars.html] will be used for the PostgreSQL connection. If the password is not provided, it should be entered via prompt.

All the non-internal GUCs defined in the source Postgres instance, independently if they were set through a configuration file, through the postmaster command-line, or through environment variables, will be used as the source for the following Patroni configuration parameters:

scope: cluster_name GUC value;

postgresql.listen: listen_addresses and port GUC values;

postgresql.datadir: data_directory GUC value;

postgresql.parameters: archive_command, restore_command, archive_cleanup_command, recovery_end_command, ssl_passphrase_command, hba_file, ident_file, config_file GUC values;

bootstrap.dcs: all other gathered PostgreSQL GUCs.

If scope, postgresql.listen or postgresql.datadir is not set from the Postgres GUCs, the respective Environment configuration value is used.

Other rules applied for the values definition:

name: PATRONI_NAME environment variable value if set, otherwise the current machine’s hostname.

postgresql.bin_dir: path to the Postgres binaries gathered from the running instance.

postgresql.connect_address: the IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the port used for the instance connection or the port GUC value.

postgresql.authentication.superuser: the configuration used for the instance connection;

postgresql.pg_hba: the lines gathered from the source instance’s hba_file.

postgresql.pg_ident: the lines gathered from the source instance’s ident_file.

restapi.listen: IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the standard 8008 port.

restapi.connect_address: IP address returned by gethostname call for the current machine’s hostname and the standard 8008 port.

Other parameters defined using Environment configuration are also included into the configuration.

Parameters

configfile

Full path to the configuration file used to store the result. If not provided, result is sent to stdout.

dsn

Optional DSN string for the local PostgreSQL instance to get GUC values from.

Validate Patroni configuration

patroni --validate-config [configfile] [--ignore-listen-port | -i]

Description

Validate the given Patroni configuration and print the information about the failed checks.

Parameters

configfile

Full path to the configuration file to check. If not given or file does not exist, will try to read from the PATRONI_CONFIG_VARIABLE environment variable or, if not set, from the Patroni environment variables.

--ignore-listen-port | -i

Optional flag to ignore bind failures for listen ports that are already in use when validating the configfile.

--print | -p

Optional flag to print out local configuration (including environment configuration overrides) after it has been successfully validated.

Pause/Resume mode for the cluster

The goal

Under certain circumstances Patroni needs to temporarily step down from managing the cluster, while still retaining the cluster state in DCS. Possible use cases are uncommon activities on the cluster, such as major version upgrades or corruption recovery. During those activities nodes are often started and stopped for reasons unknown to Patroni, some nodes can be even temporarily promoted, violating the assumption of running only one primary. Therefore, Patroni needs to be able to “detach” from the running cluster, implementing an equivalent of the maintenance mode in Pacemaker.

The implementation

When Patroni runs in a paused mode, it does not change the state of PostgreSQL, except for the following cases:

For each node, the member key in DCS is updated with the current information about the cluster. This causes Patroni to run read-only queries on a member node if the member is running.

For the Postgres primary with the leader lock Patroni updates the lock. If the node with the leader lock stops being the primary (i.e. is demoted manually), Patroni will release the lock instead of promoting the node back.

Manual unscheduled restart, manual unscheduled failover/switchover and reinitialize are allowed. No scheduled action is allowed. Manual switchover is only allowed if the node to switch over to is specified.

If ‘parallel’ primaries are detected by Patroni, it emits a warning, but does not demote the primary without the leader lock.

If there is no leader lock in the cluster, the running primary acquires the lock. If there is more than one primary node, then the first primary to acquire the lock wins. If there are no primary altogether, Patroni does not try to promote any replicas. There is an exception in this rule: if there is no leader lock because the old primary has demoted itself due to the manual promotion, then only the candidate node mentioned in the promotion request may take the leader lock. When the new leader lock is granted (i.e. after promoting a replica manually), Patroni makes sure the replicas that were streaming from the previous leader will switch to the new one.

When Postgres is stopped, Patroni does not try to start it. When Patroni is stopped, it does not try to stop the Postgres instance it is managing.

Patroni will not try to remove replication slots that don’t represent the other cluster member or are not listed in the configuration of the permanent slots.

User guide

patronictl supports pause and resume commands.

One can also issue a PATCH request to the {namespace}/{cluster}/config key with {"pause": true/false/null}

Introduction

Metatroni is a self-developed enhancement of Patroni:

Fully includes all original Patroni capabilities.

Additionally supports MySQL HA (database.type: mysql).

Supports ZooKeeper, etcd, or Consul (and other DCS backends Patroni supports).

MySQL details: MySQL high-availability support, MySQL operations and FAQ. Upstream Patroni background:

PostgreSQL HA with Kubernetes and Patroni [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iruaCgeG7qs], talk by Josh Berkus at KubeCon 2016 (video)

Feb. 2016 Zalando Tech blog post [https://engineering.zalando.com/posts/2016/02/zalandos-patroni-a-template-for-high-availability-postgresql.html]

Development Status

Patroni is in active development and accepts contributions. See our Contributing section below for more details.

We report new releases information here.

Technical Requirements/Installation

Go here for guidance on installing and upgrading Patroni on various platforms.

Planning the Number of PostgreSQL Nodes

Patroni/PostgreSQL nodes are decoupled from DCS nodes (except when Patroni implements RAFT on its own) and therefore there is no requirement on the minimal number of nodes. Running a cluster consisting of one primary and one standby is perfectly fine. You can add more standby nodes later.

2-node clusters (primary + standby) are common and provide automatic failover with high availability. Note that during failover, you’ll temporarily have no redundancy until the failed node rejoins.

DCS requirements: Your DCS (etcd, ZooKeeper, Consul) has to run with 3 or 5 nodes for proper consensus and fault tolerance. A single DCS cluster can store information for hundreds or thousands of Patroni clusters using different namespace/scope combinations.

Running and Configuring

The following section assumes Patroni repository as being cloned from https://github.com/patroni/patroni. Namely, you will need example configuration files

postgres0.yml

and

postgres1.yml

. If you installed Patroni with pip, you can obtain those files from the git repository and replace

./patroni.py

below with

patroni

command.

To get started, do the following from different terminals:

> etcd --data-dir=data/etcd --enable-v2=true
> ./patroni.py postgres0.yml
> ./patroni.py postgres1.yml

You will then see a high-availability cluster start up. Test different settings in the YAML files to see how the cluster’s behavior changes. Kill some of the components to see how the system behaves.

Add more postgres*.yml files to create an even larger cluster.

Patroni provides an HAProxy [http://www.haproxy.org/] configuration, which will give your application a single endpoint for connecting to the cluster’s leader. To configure, run:

> haproxy -f haproxy.cfg

> psql --host 127.0.0.1 --port 5000 postgres

YAML Configuration

Go here for comprehensive information about settings for etcd, consul, and ZooKeeper. And for an example, see postgres0.yml [https://github.com/patroni/patroni/blob/master/postgres0.yml].

Environment Configuration

Go here for comprehensive information about configuring(overriding) settings via environment variables.

Replication Choices

Patroni uses Postgres’ streaming replication, which is asynchronous by default. Patroni’s asynchronous replication configuration allows for maximum_lag_on_failover settings. This setting ensures failover will not occur if a follower is more than a certain number of bytes behind the leader. This setting should be increased or decreased based on business requirements. It’s also possible to use synchronous replication for better durability guarantees. See replication modes documentation for details.

Applications Should Not Use Superusers

When connecting from an application, always use a non-superuser. Patroni requires access to the database to function properly. By using a superuser from an application, you can potentially use the entire connection pool, including the connections reserved for superusers, with the superuser_reserved_connections setting. If Patroni cannot access the Primary because the connection pool is full, behavior will be undesirable.

Testing Your HA Solution

Testing an HA solution is a time consuming process, with many variables. This is particularly true considering a cross-platform application. You need a trained system administrator or a consultant to do this work. It is not something we can cover in depth in the documentation.

That said, here are some pieces of your infrastructure you should be sure to test:

Network (the network in front of your system as well as the NICs [physical or virtual] themselves)

Disk IO

file limits (nofile in Linux)

RAM. Even if you have oomkiller turned off, the unavailability of RAM could cause issues.

CPU

Virtualization Contention (overcommitting the hypervisor)

Any cgroup limitation (likely to be related to the above)

kill -9 of any postgres process (except postmaster!). This is a decent simulation of a segfault.

One thing that you should not do is run kill -9 on a postmaster process. This is because doing so does not mimic any real life scenario. If you are concerned your infrastructure is insecure and an attacker could run kill -9, no amount of HA process is going to fix that. The attacker will simply kill the process again, or cause chaos in another way.

Release notes

Version 4.1.3

Released 2026-05-05

Stability improvements

Properly handle mislabeled Etcd error (Ants Aasma)

Current Etcd versions raise Unknown error when Etcd leader is lost while updating the lease. Patroni will now override the reported error code to Unavailable.

Bugfixes

Use binary version when PG_VERSION file does not exist (Polina Bungina)

In some cases, for example when using custom bootstrap, the PG_VERSION file may not be present in the data directory. In this case, Patroni was treating the version as 0.0, which was causing issues with some of the version-specific logic. With this fix, Patroni will try to get the version from the binary in such cases.

Refactor logger intialization to avoid missing early log messages (Alexander Kukushkin)

Create PatroniLogger before loading Config to capture early log messages.

Include MONOTONIC_USEC in RELOADING=1 systemd notification (Alexander Kukushkin)

systemd 257+ requires MONOTONIC_USEC alongside RELOADING=1 for Type=notify-reload services. Without it, systemctl reload hangs indefinitely.

Improvements

Skip single-user crash recovery when backup_label exists (Vadim Ponomarev)

Skip single-user crash recovery and let PostgreSQL handle it during normal startup when starting a replica restored from an external backup (not using a custom bootstrap method).

Warn when running under systemd without python-systemd package (Alexander Kukushkin)

Instead of logging “systemd integration is not supported” at startup, check for NOTIFY_SOCKET and warn only when actually running under systemd without the python-systemd package installed.

Version 4.1.2

Released 2026-04-21

Systemd support improvements

Add support for notify-reload systemd unit type (Ronan Dunklau)

Allows systemctl reload to wait until Patroni has actually processed the configuration reload by sending RELOADING=1 and READY=1 notifications to systemd.

Send STOPPING=1 notification to systemd on shutdown (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni now properly notifies systemd that it is shutting down, following the systemd notify protocol.

Do not let PostgreSQL to notify systemd (Alexander Kukushkin)

Remove NotifyAccess=all from the example systemd unit file. Filter NOTIFY_SOCKET from the environment when starting PostgreSQL so it doesn’t send READY=1 or STOPPING=1 to systemd. When taking over a PostgreSQL that was started before Patroni and already has NOTIFY_SOCKET, re-assert READY=1 during PostgreSQL shutdown to counteract its STOPPING=1.

Version 4.1.1

Released 2026-04-08

Stability improvements

Compatibility with threading changes in python 3.11+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid starting/stopping threads at runtime. Introduce thread pools for REST API and for executing async tasks. Allow configuring global thread_pool_size and restapi.thread_pool_size.

Compatibility with python 3.14 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Run tests against python 3.14 and fix compatibility issues.

Compatibility with Etcd security fixes in v3.6.9, v3.5.28, and v3.4.42 (Alexander Kukushkin)

These Etcd releases addressed CVEs and changed behavior so cluster topology reads and lease keepalive are no longer allowed without authentication. Patroni now handles this by authenticating in member-discovery and lease-keepalive paths, re-authenticating on auth failures, and retrying requests accordingly.

Improvements for Etcd3 error handling (Alexander Kukushkin)

Handle broken JSON responses, be flexible in how JSON error is parsed, and improve reporting for etcd internal errors.

Bugfixes

Retry leader update on temporary Kubernetes 403 error (Sophia Ruan, Alexander Kukushkin)

When the Kubernetes API temporarily returns 403 Permission Denied (for example during transient RBAC issues), Patroni now verifies whether the current node still holds leadership and retries the leader update within retry_timeout instead of immediately demoting.

Fix issue with renaming leader node in sync mode and pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

/sync key wasn’t updated after renaming the leader node with Patroni restart in pause (without Postgres restart). It prevented Patroni from promoting after the next restart without pause.

Trigger pg_rewind check when the same primary increased timeline (Alexander Kukushkin)

Such timeline increase may happen as a result of crash recovery in a single user mode + promote after taking a leader key while other replica nodes are isolated from DCS. In this case replica nodes didn’t trigger pg_rewind state machine because the leader and therefore primary_conninfo didn’t change.

Only write superuser password during initdb bootstrap if it is non-empty (Michael Banck)

Writing an empty password during initdb bootstrap was causing issues.

Fix bug with failover_priority with synchronous_mode=on (Alexander Kukushkin)

tag.failover_priority values were ignored when synchronous_node_count > 1.

Fix bug with primary_conninfo password comparison (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from PostgreSQL 10, Patroni uses passfile in primary_conninfo and failed to update the passfile after the replication password was updated in yaml-file configuration with reload.

Don’t restart replica with nofailover tag in pause mode (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni used to start a manually shut down PostgreSQL replica in pause mode when it had nofailover tag set to true.

Fix check_recovery_conf() when PostgreSQL is in the starting state (Alexander Kukushkin)

For PostgreSQL v12 and newer, pg_settings cannot be queried while the server is still starting and not yet accepting connections. Missing recovery parameters are now added to the internal state when writing postgresql.conf. Additionally, restore the Postgresql.is_starting() check in Ha.is_healthiest_node().

Validate user options in dictionary format for initdb/basebackup (m4rrypro)

When initdb or basebackup options were provided as a dictionary (instead of a list), the option_is_allowed() validation was bypassed, allowing blocked options to be used.

Allow server-side compression for basebackup option (m4rrypro)

The compress option was completely blocked for basebackup, but since PostgreSQL 15, server-side compression is useful and works transparently with plain format. Client-side compression is still rejected.

Don’t reload PostgreSQL config while running custom bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

Custom bootstrap could be complex and involve PosgreSQL starting and stopping multiple times. Reloads of PostgreSQL config during this process could lead to unexpected behavior.

Check that postgresql.parameters is a dictionary (Alexander Kukushkin)

Discard new config if postgresql.parameters is not a dictionary.

Version 4.1.0

Released 2025-09-23

New features

Add support for systemd “notify” unit type (Ronan Dunklau)

Without a notify unit type, it is possible to start Patroni and immediately send it a SIGHUP signal using systemd, effectively killing it before it had time to set up its signal handlers.

Provide receive and replay LSN/lag information in API and ctl (Polina Bungina)

Patroni REST API /cluster endpoint and patronictl list command now provide receive LSN, replay LSN, receive lag, and replay lag information for each replica member.

Ensure clean demotion to standby cluster (Polina Bungina)

Make sure the introduction of the standby_cluster section in the dynamic configuration leads to a clean cluster demotion.

Implement patronictl demote-cluster and promote-cluster commands (Polina Bungina)

New commands for cluster demotion and promotion handle both the dynamic configuration editing and checking the result status.

Implement sync_priority tag (Polina Bungina)

This parameter controls the priority a member should have during synchronous replica selection when synchronous_mode is set to on.

Implement --print option for --validate-config (Polina Bungina)

Print out local configuration (including environment configuration overrides) after it has been successfully validated.

Implement kubernetes.bootstrap_labels (Polina Bungina)

This feature allows you to define labels that will be assigned to a member pod when in initializing new cluster, running custom bootstrap script, starting after custom bootstrap, or creating replica state.

Add configuration option to suppress duplicate heartbeat logs (Michael Morris)

If set to true, successive heartbeat logs that are identical shall not be output.

Add optional cluster_type attribute to permanent replication slots (Michael Banck)

This allows you to set whether a particular permanent replication slot should always be created, or just on a primary or standby cluster.

Make HTTP Server header configurable (David Grierson)

Introduce the restapi.server_tokens configuration parameter that allows you to restrict information disclosed in the HTTP Server header.

Implement readiness API checks for replication on replica members (Ants Aasma)

The previous implementation considered replicas ready as soon as PostgreSQL was started. With this change, a replica pod is only considered ready when PostgreSQL is replicating and is not too far behind the leader.

Improvements

Reduce log level of watchdog configuration failure (Ants Aasma)

Show the

Could not activate Linux watchdog device

log line on debug logging level, unless the watchdog is configured with required mode. It was previously shown on info level.

Take advantage of written_lsn and latest_end_lsn from pg_stat_wal_receiver (Alexander Kukushkin)

written_lsn, the actual write LSN, is now preferred over the one returned by pg_last_wal_receive_lsn(), which is in fact the flush LSN. latest_end_lsn points to WAL flush on the source host. In case of a primary, it allows better calculation of the replay lag, because values stored in DCS are updated only every loop_wait seconds.

Avoid interactions with slots created with the failover=true option (Alexander Kukushkin)

This change is required to make the logical failover slots feature fully functional.

Add PostgreSQL state to /metrics REST API endpoint (Ivan Filianin)

PostgreSQL instance state information is now available in the Prometheus format output of the /metrics REST API endpoint.

Version 4.0.7

Released 2025-09-22

New features

Add support for PostgreSQL 18 RC1 (Alexander Kukushkin)

GUC’s validator rules were extended. Patroni now properly handles the new background I/O worker.

Bugfixes

Fix potential issue around resolving localhost to IPv6 on Windows (András Váczi)

When configuring listen_addresses in PostgreSQL, using 0.0.0.0 or 127.0.0.1 will restrict listening to IPv4 only, excluding IPv6. On typical Windows systems, however, localhost often resolves to the IPv6 address ::1 by default. To ensure compatibility, Patroni now configures PostgreSQL to listen on 127.0.0.1, instead of localhost, on Windows systems.

Return global config only when /config key exists in DCS (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni REST API was returning an empty configuration instead of raising an error if the /config key was missing in DCS.

Fix the issue of failsafe mode not being triggered in case of Etcd unavailability (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was not always properly handling etcd3 exceptions, which resulted in failsafe mode not being triggered.

Fix signal handler reentrancy deadlock (Waynerv)

Patroni running in a Docker container with PID=1 in some special cases was experiencing deadlock after receiving SIGCHLD.

Recreate (permanent) physical slot when it doesn’t reserve WAL (Israel Barth Rubio)

Permanent physical replication slots created outside of Patroni scope without reserving WALs were causing a replication slot cannot be advanced error. To avoid this, Patroni now recreates such slots.

Handle watch cancelation messages in etcd3 properly (Alexander Kukushkin)

When etcd3 sends a cancelation message to the watch channel, it doesn’t close the connection. This results in Patroni using stale data. Patroni now solves it by breaking a loop of reading chunked response and closing the connection on the Patroni side.

Handle case when HTTPConnection socket is wrapped with pyopenssl (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was not correctly using pyopenssl interfaces, enforced in python-etcd.

Documentation improvements

Improve 2-node cluster guidance (Nikolay Samokhvalov)

Clarify behaviour during failover and DCS requirements.

Version 4.0.6

Released 2025-06-06

Bugfixes

Fix bug in failover from a leader with a higher priority (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make sure Patroni ignores the former leader with higher priority when it reports the same LSN as the current node.

Fix permissions for the postgresql.conf file created outside of PGDATA (Michael Banck)

Respect the system-wide umask value when creating the postgresql.conf file outside of the PGDATA directory.

Fix bug with switchover in synchronous_mode=quorum (Alexander Kukushkin)

Do not check quorum requirements when a candidate is specified.

Ignore stale Etcd nodes by comparing cluster term (Alexander Kukushkin)

Memorize the last known “raft_term” of the Etcd cluster, and when executing client requests, compare it with the “raft_term” reported by an Etcd node.

Update PostgreSQL configuration files on SIGHUP (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, Patroni was only replacing PostgreSQL configuration files if a change in global or local configuration was detected.

Properly handle Unavailable exception raised by etcd3 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni used to retry such requests on the same etcd3 node, while switching to another node is a better strategy.

Improve etcd3 lease handling (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make sure Patroni refreshes the etcd3 lease at least once per HA loop.

Recheck annotations on 409 status code when attempting to acquire leader lock (Alexander Kukushkin)

Implement the same behavior as was done for the leader object read in Patroni version 4.0.3.

Consider replay_lsn when advancing slots (Polina Bungina)

Do not try to advance slots on replicas past the replay_lsn. Additionally, advance the slot to the replay_lsn position if it is already past the confirmed_flush_lsn of this slot on the replica but the replica has still not replayed the actual LSN at which this slot is on the primary.

Make sure CHECKPOINT is executed after promote (Alexander Kukushkin)

It was possible that checkpoint task wasn’t reset on demote because CHECKPOINT wasn’t yet finished. This resulted in using a stale result when the next promote is triggered.

Avoid running “offline” demotion concurrently (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case of a slow shutdown, it might happen that the next heartbeat loop hits the DCS error handling method again, resulting in AsyncExecutor is busy, demoting from the main thread warning and starting offline demotion again.

Normalize the data_dir value before renaming the data directory on initialization failure (Waynerv)

Prevent a trailing slash in the data_dir parameter value from breaking the renaming process after an initialization failure.

Check that synchronous_standby_names contains the expected value (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, the mechanism implementing the state machine for non-quorum synchronous replication didn’t check the actual value of synchronous_standby_names, what resulted in a stale value of synchronous_standby_names being used when pg_stat_replication is a subset of synchronous_standby_names.

Version 4.0.5

Released 2025-02-20

Stability improvements

Compatibility with python-json-logger>=3.1 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Get rid of the warnings produced by the old API usage.

Compatibility with Python 3.13 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Run tests against Python 3.13.

Compatibility with pyinstaller>=4.4 (Joe Jensen)

Fall back to the default iter_modules if pyinstaller toc attribute is not present.

Fix issues with PostgreSQL 9.5 support (Alexander Kukushkin)

Properly handle pg_rewind output format.

Consider synchronous_standby_names format not supporting “num” specification.

Compatibility with the latest changes in urlparse (Alexander Kukushkin)

urlparse doesn’t accept multiple hosts with [] character in URL anymore. To mitigate the problem, switch to the native wrappers of PQconninfoParse() from libpq, when it is possible, and use our implementation only for older psycopg2 versions that are linked with an outdated version of libpq.

Bugfixes

Show only the members to be restarted upon restart confirmation (András Váczi)

Previously, when doing patronictl restart <clustername> --pending, the confirmation listed all members, regardless of whether their restart is pending.

Cancel long-running jobs on Patroni stop and remove data directory on replica bootstrap failure (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, Patroni could be doing replica bootstrap, while pg_basebackup / wal-g / pgBackRest / barman or similar keep running.

Properly handle cluster names with a slash in patronictl edit-config (Antoni Mur)

Replace a forward slash in cluster_name with an underscore.

Avoid dropping physical slots too early (Alexander Kukushkin)

Postpone removal of physical replication slots containing xmin after a failover: on the new primary – until this member is promoted, on replicas – until there is a leader in the cluster.

Handle all exceptions raised by subprocess in controldata() (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was not properly handling all exceptions possibly raised when calling pg_controldata utility.

Fix bug with a slot for a former leader not retained on failover (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid falsely relying on members being present in DCS, while on failover /member key for the former leader is expiring exactly at the same time.

Fix a couple of bugs in the quorum state machine (Alexander Kukushkin)

When evaluating whether there are healthy nodes for a leader race, before demoting we need to take into account quorum requirements. Without it, the former leader may end up in recovery surrounded by asynchronous nodes.

QuorumStateResolver wasn’t correctly handling the case when a replica node quickly joined and disconnected.

Improvements

Improve error on am empty or non-dictionary configuration file (Julian)

Throw a more explicit exception when validating if Patroni configuration file contains a valid Mapping object.

Version 4.0.4

Released 2024-11-22

Stability improvements

Add compatibility with the py-consul module (Alexander Kukushkin)

python-consul module is unmaintained for a long time, while py-consul is the official replacement. Backward compatibility with python-consul is retained.

Add compatibility with the prettytable>=3.12.0 module (Alexander Kukushkin)

Address deprecation warnings.

Compatibility with the ydiff==1.4.2 module (Alexander Kukushkin)

Fix compatibility issues for the latest version, constrain version in requirements.txt, and introduce latest version compatibility test.

Bugfixes

Run on_role_change callback after a failed primary recovery (Polina Bungina, Alexander Kukushkin)

Additionally run on_role_change callback for a primary that failed to start after a crash to increase chances the callback is executed, even if the further start as a replica fails.

Fix a thread leak in patronictl list -W (Alexander Kukushkin)

Cache DCS instance object to avoid thread leak.

Ensure only supported parameters are written to the connection string (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni used to pass parameters introduced in newer versions to the connection string, which had been leading to connection errors.

Version 4.0.3

Released 2024-10-18

Bugfixes

Disable pgaudit when creating users not to expose password (kviset)

Patroni was logging superuser, replication, and rewind passwords on their creation when pgaudit extension was enabled.

Fix issue with mixed setups: primary on pre-Patroni v4 and replicas on v4+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

Use xlog_location extracted from /members key instead of trying to get a member’s slot position from /status key if Patroni version running on the leader is pre-4.0.0. Not doing so has been causing WALs accumulation on replicas.

Do not ignore valid PostgreSQL GUCs that don’t have Patroni validator (Polina Bungina)

Still check against postgres --describe-config if a GUC does not have a Patroni validator but is, in fact, a valid GUC.

Improvements

Recheck annotations on 409 status code when reading leader object in K8s (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid an additional update if PATCH request was canceled by Patroni, while the request successfully updated the target.

Add support of sslnegotiation client-side connection option (Alexander Kukushkin)

sslnegotiation was added to the final PostgreSQL 17 release.

Version 4.0.2

Released 2024-09-17

Bugfixes

Handle exceptions while discovering configuration validation files (Alexander Kukushkin)

Skip directories for which Patroni does not have sufficient permissions to perform list operations.

Make sure inactive hot physical replication slots don’t hold xmin (Alexander Kukushkin, Polina Bungina)

Since version 3.2.0 Patroni creates physical replication slots for all members on replicas and periodically moves them forward using pg_replication_slot_advance() function. However if for any reason hot_standby_feedback is enabled and the primary is demoted to replica, the now inactive slots have NOT NULL xmin value propagated back to the new primary. This results in xmin horizon not being moved forward and vacuum not being able to clean up dead tuples. With this fix, Patroni recreates the physical replication slots that are supposed to be inactive but have NOT NULL xmin value.

Fix unhandled DCSError during the startup phase (Waynerv)

Ensure DCS connectivity before trying to check the uniqueness of the node name.

Explicitly include CMDLINE_OPTIONS GUCs when querying pg_settings (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make sure all GUCs that are passed to postmaster as command line parameters are restored when Patroni is joining a running standby. This is a follow-up for the bug fixed in Patroni 3.2.2.

Fix bug in synchronous_standby_names quotting logic (Alexander Kukushkin)

According to PostgreSQL documentation, ANY and FIRST keywords are supposed to be double-quoted, which Patroni did not do before.

Fix keepalive connection out-of-range issue (hadizamani021)

Ensure that keepalive option value calculated based on the ttl set does not exceed the maximum allowed value for the current platform.

Version 4.0.1

Released 2024-08-30

Bugfix

Patroni was creating unnecessary replication slots for itself (Alexander Kukushkin)

It was happening if name contains upper-case or special characters.

Version 4.0.0

Released 2024-08-29

Warning

This version completes work on getting rid of the “master” term, in favor of “primary”. This means a couple of breaking changes, please read the release notes carefully. Upgrading to the Patroni 4+ will work reliably only if you run Patroni 3.1.0 or newer. Upgrading from an older version directly to 4+ is possible but may lead to unexpected behavior if the primary fails while the rest of the nodes are running on other Patroni versions.

Breaking changes

The following breaking changes were introduced when getting rid of the non-inclusive “master” term in the Patroni code:

On Kubernetes, Patroni by default will set role label to primary. In case if you want to keep the old behavior and avoid downtime or lengthy complex migrations, you can configure parameters kubernetes.leader_label_value and kubernetes.standby_leader_label_value to master. Read more here.

Patroni role is written to DCS as primary instead of master.

Patroni role returned by Patroni REST API has been changed from master to primary.

Patroni REST API no longer accepts role=master in requests to /switchover, /failover, /restart endpoints.

/metrics REST API endpoint will no longer report patroni_master metric.

patronictl no longer accepts --master option for any command. --leader or --primary options should be used instead.

no_master option in the declarative configuration of custom replica creation methods is no longer treated as a special option, please use no_leader instead.

patroni_wale_restore script doesn’t accept --no_master option anymore.

patroni_barman script doesn’t accept --role=master option anymore.

All callback scripts are executed with role=primary option passed instead of role=master.

patronictl failover does not accept --leader option that was deprecated since Patroni 3.2.0.

User creation functionality (bootstrap.users configuration section) deprecated since Patroni 3.2.0 has been removed.

New features

Quorum-based failover (Ants Aasma, Alexander Kukushkin)

The feature implements quorum-based synchronous replication (available from PostgreSQL v10) which helps to reduce worst-case latencies, even during normal operation, as a higher latency of replicating to one standby can be compensated by other standbys. Patroni implements additional safeguards to prevent any user-visible data loss by choosing a failover candidate based on the latest transaction received.

Register Citus secondaries in pg_dist_node (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni now maintains the list of nodes with role==replica, state==running and without noloadbalance tag in pg_dist_node.

Configurable retention of members’ replication slots (Alexander Kukushkin)

Implements support of member_slots_ttl global configuration parameter that controls for how long member replication slots should be kept around when the member key is absent.

Make permissions of log files created by Patroni configurable (Alexander Kukushkin)

Allows to set specific permissions for log files created by Patroni. If not specified, permissions are set based on the current umask value.

Compatibility with PostgreSQL 17 beta3 (Alexander Kukushkin)

GUC’s validator rules were extended. Patroni handles all the new auxiliary backends during shutdown and sets dbname in primary_conninfo, as it is required for logical replication slots synchronization.

Implement --ignore-listen-port option for Patroni config validation (Sahil Naphade)

Make it possible to ignore already bound ports when running patroni --validate-config.

Improvements

Make wal_log_hints configurable (Paul_Kim)

Allows to avoid the overhead of wal_log_hints configuration being enabled in case use_pg_rewind is set to off.

Log pg_basebackup command in DEBUG level (Waynerv)

Facilitates failed initialization debugging.

Bugfixes

Advance permanent slots for cascading nodes while in failsafe (Alexander Kukushkin)

Ensure that slots for cascading replicas are properly advanced on the primary when failsafe mode is activated. It is done by extending replicas response on POST /failsafe REST API request with their xlog_location.

Don’t let the current node be chosen as synchronous (Alexander Kukushkin)

There may be “something” streaming from the current primary node with application_name that matches the name of the current primary. Patroni was not properly handling this situation, which could end up in the primary being declared as a synchronous node and consequently was blocking switchovers.

Ignore restapi.allowlist_include_members for POST /failsafe (Alexander Kukushkin)

Improve GUCs validation (Polina Bungina)

Due to additional validation through running postgres --describe-config command, it was previously not possible to set GUCs not listed there through Patroni configuration. This limitation is now removed.

Add line with localhost to .pgpass file when unix sockets are detected (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni will add an additional line to .pgpass file if host parameter specified starts with / character. This allows to cover a corner case when host matches the default socket directory path.

Fix logging issues (Waynerv)

Defined proper request URL in failsafe handling logs and fixed the order of timestamps in postmaster check log.

Version 3.3.2

Released 2024-07-11

Bugfixes

Fix plain Postgres synchronous replication mode (Israel Barth Rubio)

Since synchronous_mode was introduced to Patroni, the plain Postgres synchronous replication was not working. With this bugfix, Patroni sets the value of synchronous_standby_names as configured by the user, if that is the case, when synchronous_mode is disabled.

Handle logical slots invalidation on a standby (Polina Bungina)

Since PG16 logical replication slots on a standby can be invalidated due to horizon: from now on, Patroni forces copy (i.e., recreation) of invalidated slots.

Fix race condition with logical slot advance and copy (Alexander Kukushkin)

Due to this bug, it was a possible situation when an invalidated logical replication slot was copied with PostgreSQL restart more than once.

Version 3.3.1

Released 2024-06-17

Stability improvements

Compatibility with Python 3.12 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Handle a new attribute added to logging.LogRecord.

Bugfixes

Fix infinite recursion in replicatefrom tags handling (Alexander Kukushkin)

As a part of this fix, also improve is_physical_slot() check and adjust documentation.

Fix wrong role reporting in standby clusters (Alexander Kukushkin)

synchronous_standby_names and synchronous replication only work on a real primary node and in the case of cascading replication are simply ignored by Postgres. Before this fix, patronictl list and GET /cluster were falsely reporting some nodes as synchronous.

Fix availability of the allow_in_place_tablespaces GUC (Polina Bungina)

allow_in_place_tablespaces was not only added to PostgreSQL 15 but also backpatched to PostgreSQL 10-14.

Version 3.3.0

Released 2024-04-04

Warning

All older Partoni versions are not compatible with ydiff>=1.3.

There are the following options available to “fix” the problem:

upgrade Patroni to the latest version

install ydiff<1.3 after installing Patroni

install cdiff module

New features

Add ability to pass auth_data to Zookeeper client (Aras Mumcuyan)

It allows to specify the authentication credentials to use for the connection.

Add a contrib script for Barman integration (Israel Barth Rubio)

Provide an application patroni_barman that allows to perform Barman operations remotely and can be used as a custom bootstrap/custom replica method or as an on_role_change callback. Please check here for more information.

Support JSON log format (alisalemmi)

Apart from plain (default), Patroni now also supports json log format. Requires python-json-logger>=2.0.2 library to be installed.

Show pending_restart_reason information (Polina Bungina)

Provide extended information about the PostgreSQL parameters that caused pending_restart flag to be set. Both patronictl list and /patroni REST API endpoint now show the parameters names and their “diff” as pending_restart_reason.

Implement nostream tag (Grigory Smolkin)

If nostream tag is set to true, the node will not use replication protocol to stream WAL but instead rely on archive recovery (if restore_command is configured). It also disables copying and synchronization of permanent logical replication slots on the node itself and all its cascading replicas.

Improvements

Implement validation of the log section (Alexander Kukushkin)

Until now validator was not checking the correctness of the logging configuration provided.

Improve logging for PostgreSQL parameters change (Polina Bungina)

Convert old values to a human-readable format and log information about the pg_controldata vs Patroni global configuration mismatch.

Bugfixes

Properly filter out not allowed pg_basebackup options (Israel Barth Rubio)

Due to a bug, Patroni was not properly filtering out the not allowed options configured for the basebackup replica bootstrap method, when provided in the - setting: value format.

Fix etcd3 authentication error handling (Alexander Kukushkin)

Always retry one time on etcd3 authentication error if authentication was not done right before executing the request. Also, do not restart watchers on reauthentication.

Improve logic of the validator files discovery (Waynerv)

Use importlib library to discover the files with available configuration parameters when possible (for Python 3.9+). This implementation is more stable and doesn’t break the Patroni distributions based on zip archives.

Use target_session_attrs only when multiple hosts are specified in the standby_cluster section (Alexander Kukushkin)

target_session_attrs=read-write is now added to the primary_conninfo on the standby leader node only when standby_cluster.host section contains multiple hosts separated by commas.

Add compatibility code for ydiff library version 1.3+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is relying on some API from ydiff that is not public because it is supposed to be just a terminal tool rather than a python module. Unfortunately, the API change in 1.3 broke old Patroni versions.

Version 3.2.2

Released 2024-01-17

Bugfixes

Don’t let replica restore initialize key when DCS was wiped (Alexander Kukushkin)

It was happening in the method where Patroni was supposed to take over a standalone PG cluster.

Use consistent read when fetching just updated sync key from Consul (Alexander Kukushkin)

Consul doesn’t provide any interface to immediately get ModifyIndex for the key that we just updated, therefore we have to perform an explicit read operation. Since stale reads are allowed by default, we sometimes used to get an outdated version of the key.

Reload Postgres config if a parameter that requires restart was reset to the original value (Polina Bungina)

Previously Patroni wasn’t updating the config, but only resetting the pending_restart.

Fix erroneous inverted logic of the confirmation prompt message when doing a failover to an async candidate in synchronous mode (Polina Bungina)

The problem existed only in patronictl.

Exclude leader from failover candidates in patronictl (Polina Bungina)

If the cluster is healthy, failing over to an existing leader is no-op.

Create Citus database and extension idempotently (Alexander Kukushkin, Zhao Junwang)

It will allow to create them in the post_bootstrap script in case if there is a need to add some more dependencies to the Citus database.

Don’t filter our contradictory nofailover tag (Polina Bungina)

The configuration {nofailover: false, failover_priority: 0} set on a node didn’t allow it to participate in the race, while it should, because nofailover tag should take precedence.

Fixed PyInstaller frozen issue (Sophia Ruan)

The freeze_support() was called after argparse and as a result, Patroni wasn’t able to start Postgres.

Fixed bug in the config generator for patronictl and Citus configuration (Israel Barth Rubio)

It prevented patronictl and Citus configuration parameters set via environment variables from being written into the generated config.

Restore recovery GUCs and some Patroni-managed parameters when joining a running standby (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was failing to restart Postgres v12 onwards with an error about missing port in one of the internal structures.

Fixes around pending_restart flag (Polina Bungina)

Don’t expose pending_restart when in custom bootstrap with recovery_target_action = promote or when someone changed hot_standby or wal_log_hints using for example ALTER SYSTEM.

Version 3.2.1

Released 2023-11-30

Bugfixes

Limit accepted values for --format argument in patronictl (Alexander Kukushkin)

It used to accept any arbitrary string and produce no output if the value wasn’t recognized.

Verify that replica nodes received checkpoint LSN on shutdown before releasing the leader key (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously in some cases, we were using LSN of the SWITCH record that is followed by CHECKPOINT (if archiving mode is enabled). As a result the former primary sometimes had to do pg_rewind, but there would be no data loss involved.

Do a real HTTP request when performing node name uniqueness check (Alexander Kukushkin)

When running Patroni in containers it is possible that the traffic is routed using docker-proxy, which listens on the port and accepts incoming connections. It was causing false positives.

Fixed Citus support with Etcd v2 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was failing to deploy a new Citus cluster with Etcd v2.

Fixed pg_rewind behavior with Postgres v16+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

The error message format of pg_waldump changed in v16 which caused pg_rewind to be called by Patroni even when it was not necessary.

Fixed bug with custom bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was falsely applying --command argument, which is a bootstrap command itself.

Fixed the issue with REST API health check endpoints (Sophia Ruan)

There were chances that after Postgres restart it could return unknown state for Postgres because connections were not properly closed.

Cache postgres --describe-config output results (Waynerv)

They are used to figure out which GUCs are available to validate PostgreSQL configuration and we don’t expect this list to change while Patroni is running.

Version 3.2.0

Released 2023-10-25

Deprecation notice

The bootstrap.users support will be removed in version 4.0.0. If you need to create users after deploying a new cluster please use the bootstrap.post_bootstrap hook for that.

Breaking changes

Enforce loop_wait + 2*retry_timeout <= ttl rule and hard-code minimal possible values (Alexander Kukushkin)

Minimal values: loop_wait=2, retry_timeout=3, ttl=20. In case values are smaller or violate the rule they are adjusted and a warning is written to Patroni logs.

New features

Failover priority (Mark Pekala)

With the help of tags.failover_priority it’s now possible to make a node more preferred during the leader race. More details in the documentation (ref tags).

Implemented patroni --generate-config [--dsn DSN] and patroni --generate-sample-config (Polina Bungina)

It allows to generate a config file for the running PostgreSQL cluster or a sample config file for the new Patroni cluster.

Use a dedicated connection to Postgres for Patroni REST API (Alexander Kukushkin)

It helps to avoid blocking the main heartbeat loop if the system is under stress.

Enrich some endpoints with the name of the node (sskserk)

For the monitoring endpoint name is added next to the scope and for metrics endpoint the name is added to tags.

Ensure strict failover/switchover difference (Polina Bungina)

Be more precise in log messages and allow failing over to an asynchronous node in a healthy synchronous cluster.

Make permanent physical replication slots behave similarly to permanent logical slots (Alexander Kukushkin)

Create permanent physical replication slots on all nodes that are allowed to become the leader and use pg_replication_slot_advance() function to advance restart_lsn for slots on standby nodes.

Add capability of specifying namespace through --dcs argument in patronictl (Israel Barth Rubio)

It could be handy if patronictl is used without a configuration file.

Add support for additional parameters in custom bootstrap configuration (Israel Barth Rubio)

Previously it was only possible to add custom arguments to the command and now one could list them as a mapping.

Improvements

Set citus.local_hostname GUC to the same value which is used by Patroni to connect to the Postgres (Alexander Kukushkin)

There are cases when Citus wants to have a connection to the local Postgres. By default it uses localhost, which is not always available.

Bugfixes

Ignore synchronous_mode setting in a standby cluster (Polina Bungina)

Postgres doesn’t support cascading synchronous replication and not ignoring synchronous_mode was breaking a switchover in a standby cluster.

Handle SIGCHLD for on_reload callback (Alexander Kukushkin)

Not doing so results in a zombie process, which is reaped only when the next on_reload is executed.

Handle AuthOldRevision error when working with Etcd v3 (Alexander Kukushkin, Kenny Do)

The error is raised if Etcd is configured to use JWT and when the user database in Etcd is updated.

Version 3.1.2

Released 2023-09-26

Bugfixes

Fixed bug with wal_keep_size checks (Alexander Kukushkin)

The wal_keep_size is a GUC that normally has a unit and Patroni was failing to cast its value to int. As a result the value of bootstrap.dcs was not written to the /config key afterwards.

Detect and resolve inconsistencies between /sync key and synchronous_standby_names (Alexander Kukushkin)

Normally, Patroni updates /sync and synchronous_standby_names in a very specific order, but in case of a bug or when someone manually reset synchronous_standby_names, Patroni was getting into an inconsistent state. As a result it was possible that the failover happens to an asynchronous node.

Read GUC’s values when joining running Postgres (Alexander Kukushkin)

When restarted in pause, Patroni was discarding the synchronous_standby_names GUC from the postgresql.conf. To solve it and avoid similar issues, Patroni will read GUC’s value if it is joining an already running Postgres.

Silenced annoying warnings when checking for node uniqueness (Alexander Kukushkin)

WARNING messages are produced by urllib3 if Patroni is quickly restarted.

Version 3.1.1

Released 2023-09-20

Bugfixes

Reset failsafe state on promote (ChenChangAo)

If switchover/failover happened shortly after failsafe mode had been activated, the newly promoted primary was demoting itself after failsafe becomes inactive.

Silence useless warnings in patronictl (Alexander Kukushkin)

If patronictl uses the same patroni.yaml file as Patroni and can access PGDATA directory it might have been showing annoying warnings about incorrect values in the global configuration.

Explicitly enable synchronous mode for a corner case (Alexander Kukushkin)

Synchronous mode effectively was never activated if there are no replicas streaming from the primary.

Fixed bug with 0 integer values validation (Israel Barth Rubio)

In most cases, it didn’t cause any issues, just warnings.

Don’t return logical slots for standby cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni can’t create logical replication slots in the standby cluster, thus they should be ignored if they are defined in the global configuration.

Avoid showing docstring in patronictl --help output (Israel Barth Rubio)

The click module needs to get a special hint for that.

Fixed bug with kubernetes.standby_leader_label_value (Alexander Kukushkin)

This feature effectively never worked.

Returned cluster system identifier to the patronictl list output (Polina Bungina)

The problem was introduced while implementing the support for Citus, where we need to hide the identifier because it is different for coordinator and all workers.

Override write_leader_optime method in Kubernetes implementation (Alexander Kukushkin)

The method is supposed to write shutdown LSN to the leader Endpoint/ConfigMap when there are no healthy replicas available to become the new primary.

Don’t start stopped postgres in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

Due to a race condition, Patroni was falsely assuming that the standby should be restarted because some recovery parameters (primary_conninfo or similar) were changed.

Fixed bug in patronictl query command (Israel Barth Rubio)

It didn’t work when only -m argument was provided or when none of -r or -m were provided.

Properly treat integer parameters that are used in the command line to start postgres (Polina Bungina)

If values are supplied as strings and not casted to integer it was resulting in an incorrect calculation of max_prepared_transactions based on max_connections for Citus clusters.

Don’t rely on pg_stat_wal_receiver when deciding on pg_rewind (Alexander Kukushkin)

It could happen that received_tli reported by pg_stat_wal_receiver is ahead of the actual replayed timeline, while the timeline reported by DENTIFY_SYSTEM via replication connection is always correct.

Version 3.1.0

Released 2023-08-03

Breaking changes

Changed semantic of restapi.keyfile and restapi.certfile (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously Patroni was using restapi.keyfile and restapi.certfile as client certificates as a fallback if there were no respective configuration parameters in the ctl section.

Warning

If you enabled client certificates validation (restapi.verify_client is set to required), you also must provide valid client certificates in the ctl.certfile, ctl.keyfile, ctl.keyfile_password. If not provided, Patroni will not work correctly.

New features

Make Pod role label configurable (Waynerv)

Values could be customized using kubernetes.leader_label_value, kubernetes.follower_label_value and kubernetes.standby_leader_label_value parameters. This feature will be very useful when we change the master role to the primary. You can read more about the feature and migration steps here.

Improvements

Various improvements of patroni --validate-config (Alexander Kukushkin)

Improved parameter validation for different DCS, bootstrap.dcs , ctl, restapi, and watchdog sections.

Start Postgres not in recovery if it crashed during recovery while Patroni is running (Alexander Kukushkin)

It may reduce recovery time and will help to prevent unnecessary timeline increments.

Avoid unnecessary updates of /status key (Alexander Kukushkin)

When there are no permanent logical slots Patroni was updating the /status on every heartbeat loop even when LSN on the primary didn’t move forward.

Don’t allow stale primary to win the leader race (Alexander Kukushkin)

If Patroni was hanging during a significant time due to lack of resources it will additionally check that no other nodes promoted Postgres before acquiring the leader lock.

Implemented visibility of certain PostgreSQL parameters validation (Alexander Kukushkin, Feike Steenbergen)

If validation of max_connections, max_wal_senders, max_prepared_transactions, max_locks_per_transaction, max_replication_slots, or max_worker_processes failed Patroni was using some sane default value. Now in addition to that it will also show a warning.

Set permissions for files and directories created in PGDATA (Alexander Kukushkin)

All files created by Patroni had only owner read/write permissions. This behaviour was breaking backup tools that run under a different user and relying on group read permissions. Now Patroni honors permissions on PGDATA and correctly sets permissions on all directories and files it creates inside PGDATA.

Bugfixes

Run archive_command through shell (Waynerv)

Patroni might archive some WAL segments before doing crash recovery in a single-user mode or before pg_rewind. If the archive_command contains some shell operators, like && it didn’t work with Patroni.

Fixed “on switchover” shutdown checks (Polina Bungina)

It was possible that specified candidate is still streaming and didn’t received shut down checking but the leader key was removed because some other nodes were healthy.

Fixed “is primary” check (Alexander Kukushkin)

During the leader race replicas were not able to recognize that Postgres on the old leader is still running as a primary.

Fixed patronictl list (Alexander Kukushkin)

The Cluster name field was missing in tsv, json, and yaml output formats.

Fixed pg_rewind behaviour after pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

Under certain conditions, Patroni wasn’t able to join the false primary back to the cluster with pg_rewind after coming out of maintenance mode.

Fixed bug in Etcd v3 implementation (Alexander Kukushkin)

Invalidate internal KV cache if key update performed using create_revision/mod_revision field due to revision mismatch.

Fixed behaviour of replicas in standby cluster in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

When the leader key expires replicas in standby cluster will not follow the remote node but keep primary_conninfo as it is.

Version 3.0.4

Released 2023-07-13

New features

Make the replication status of standby nodes visible (Alexander Kukushkin)

For PostgreSQL 9.6+ Patroni will report the replication state as streaming when the standby is streaming from the other node or in archive recovery when there is no replication connection and restore_command is set. The state is visible in member keys in DCS, in the REST API, and in patronictl list output.

Improvements

Improved error messages with Etcd v3 (Alexander Kukushkin)

When Etcd v3 cluster isn’t accessible Patroni was reporting that it can’t access /v2 endpoints.

Use quorum read in patronictl if it is possible (Alexander Kukushkin)

Etcd or Consul clusters could be degraded to read-only, but from the patronictl view everything was fine. Now it will fail with the error.

Prevent splitbrain from duplicate names in configuration (Mark Pekala)

When starting Patroni will check if node with the same name is registered in DCS, and try to query its REST API. If REST API is accessible Patroni exits with an error. It will help to protect from the human error.

Start Postgres not in recovery if it crashed while Patroni is running (Alexander Kukushkin)

It may reduce recovery time and will help from unnecessary timeline increments.

Bugfixes

REST API SSL certificate were not reloaded upon receiving a SIGHUP (Israel Barth Rubio)

Regression was introduced in 3.0.3.

Fixed integer GUCs validation for parameters like max_connections (Feike Steenbergen)

Patroni didn’t like quoted numeric values. Regression was introduced in 3.0.3.

Fix issue with synchronous_mode (Alexander Kukushkin)

Execute txid_current() with synchronous_commit=off so it doesn’t accidentally wait for absent synchronous standbys when synchronous_mode_strict is enabled.

Version 3.0.3

Released 2023-06-22

New features

Compatibility with PostgreSQL 16 beta1 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Extended GUC’s validator rules.

Make PostgreSQL GUC’s validator extensible (Israel Barth Rubio)

Validator rules are loaded from YAML files located in patroni/postgresql/available_parameters/ directory. Files are ordered in alphabetical order and applied one after another. It makes possible to have custom validators for non-standard Postgres distributions.

Added restapi.request_queue_size option (Andrey Zhidenkov, Aleksei Sukhov)

Sets request queue size for TCP socket used by Patroni REST API. Once the queue is full, further requests get a “Connection denied” error. The default value is 5.

Call initdb directly when initializing a new cluster (Matt Baker)

Previously it was called via pg_ctl, what required a special quoting of parameters passed to initdb.

Added before stop hook (Le Duane)

The hook could be configured via postgresql.before_stop and is executed right before pg_ctl stop. The exit code doesn’t impact shutdown process.

Added support for custom Postgres binary names (Israel Barth Rubio, Polina Bungina)

When using a custom Postgres distribution it may be the case that the Postgres binaries are compiled with different names other than the ones used by the community Postgres distribution. Custom binary names could be configured using postgresql.bin_name.* and PATRONI_POSTGRESQL_BIN_* environment variables.

Improvements

Various improvements of patroni --validate-config (Polina Bungina)

Make bootstrap.initdb optional. It is only required for new clusters, but patroni --validate-config was complaining if it was missing in the config.

Don’t error out when postgresql.bin_dir is empty or not set. Try to first find Postgres binaries in the default PATH instead.

Make postgresql.authentication.rewind section optional. If it is missing, Patroni is using the superuser.

Improved error reporting in patronictl (Israel Barth Rubio)

The \n symbol was rendered as it is, instead of the actual newline symbol.

Bugfixes

Fixed issue in Citus support (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the REST API call from the promoted worker to the coordinator failed during switchover it was leaving the given Citus group blocked during indefinite time.

Allow

etcd3

URL in

–dcs-url

option of

patronictl

(Israel Barth Rubio)

If users attempted to pass a

etcd3

URL through

–dcs-url

option of

patronictl

they would face an exception.

Version 3.0.2

Released 2023-03-24

Warning

Version 3.0.2 dropped support of Python older than 3.6.

New features

Added sync standby replica status to /metrics endpoint (Thomas von Dein, Alexander Kukushkin)

Before were only reporting primary/standby_leader/replica.

User-friendly handling of PAGER in patronictl (Israel Barth Rubio)

It makes pager configurable via PAGER environment variable, which overrides default less and more.

Make K8s retriable HTTP status code configurable (Alexander Kukushkin)

On some managed platforms it is possible to get status code 401 Unauthorized, which sometimes gets resolved after a few retries.

Improvements

Set hot_standby to off during custom bootstrap only if recovery_target_action is set to promote (Alexander Kukushkin)

It was necessary to make recovery_target_action=pause work correctly.

Don’t allow on_reload callback to kill other callbacks (Alexander Kukushkin)

on_start/on_stop/on_role_change are usually used to add/remove Virtual IP and on_reload should not interfere with them.

Switched to IMDSFetcher in aws callback example script (Polina Bungina)

The IMDSv2 requires a token to work with and the IMDSFetcher handles it transparently.

Bugfixes

Fixed patronictl switchover on Citus cluster running on Kubernetes (Lukáš Lalinský)

It didn’t work for namespaces different from default.

Don’t write to PGDATA if major version is not known (Alexander Kukushkin)

If right after the start PGDATA was empty (maybe wasn’t yet mounted), Patroni was making a false assumption about PostgreSQL version and falsely creating recovery.conf file even if the actual major version is v10+.

Fixed bug with Citus metadata after coordinator failover (Alexander Kukushkin)

The citus_set_coordinator_host() call doesn’t cause metadata sync and the change was invisible on worker nodes. The issue is solved by switching to citus_update_node().

Use etcd hosts listed in the config file as a fallback when all etcd nodes “failed” (Alexander Kukushkin)

The etcd cluster may change topology over time and Patroni tries to follow it. If at some point all nodes became unreachable Patroni will use a combination of nodes from the config plus the last known topology when trying to reconnect.

Version 3.0.1

Released 2023-02-16

Bugfixes

Pass proper role name to an on_role_change callback script’. (Alexander Kukushkin, Polina Bungina)

Patroni used to erroneously pass promoted role to an on_role_change callback script on promotion. The passed role name changed back to master. This regression was introduced in 3.0.0.

Version 3.0.0

Released 2023-01-30

This version adds integration with Citus [https://www.citusdata.com] and makes it possible to survive temporary DCS outages without demoting primary.

Warning

Version 3.0.0 is the last release supporting Python 2.7. Upcoming release will drop support of Python versions older than 3.7.

The RAFT support is deprecated. We will do our best to maintain it, but take neither guarantee nor responsibility for possible issues.

This version is the first step in getting rid of the “master”, in favor of “primary”. Upgrading to the next major release will work reliably only if you run at least 3.0.0.

New features

DCS failsafe mode (Alexander Kukushkin, Polina Bungina)

If the feature is enabled it will allow Patroni cluster to survive temporary DCS outages. You can find more details in the documentation.

Citus support (Alexander Kukushkin, Polina Bungina, Jelte Fennema)

Patroni enables easy deployment and management of Citus [https://www.citusdata.com] clusters with HA. Please check here page for more information.

Improvements

Suppress recurring errors when dropping unknown but active replication slots (Michael Banck)

Patroni will still write these logs, but only in DEBUG.

Run only one monitoring query per HA loop (Alexander Kukushkin)

It wasn’t the case if synchronous replication is enabled.

Keep only latest failed data directory (William Albertus Dembo)

If bootstrap failed Patroni used to rename $PGDATA folder with timestamp suffix. From now on the suffix will be .failed and if such folder exists it is removed before renaming.

Improved check of synchronous replication connections (Alexander Kukushkin)

When the new host is added to the synchronous_standby_names it will be set as synchronous in DCS only when it managed to catch up with the primary in addition to pg_stat_replication.sync_state = 'sync'.

Removed functionality

Remove patronictl scaffold (Alexander Kukushkin)

The only reason for having it was a hacky way of running standby clusters.

Version 2.1.7

Released 2023-01-04

Bugfixes

Fixed little incompatibilities with legacy python modules (Alexander Kukushkin)

They prevented from building/running Patroni on Debian buster/Ubuntu bionic.

Version 2.1.6

Released 2022-12-30

Improvements

Fix annoying exceptions on ssl socket shutdown (Alexander Kukushkin)

The HAProxy is closing connections as soon as it got the HTTP Status code leaving no time for Patroni to properly shutdown SSL connection.

Adjust example Dockerfile for arm64 (Polina Bungina)

Remove explicit amd64 and x86_64, don’t remove libnss_files.so.*.

Security improvements

Enforce search_path=pg_catalog for non-replication connections (Alexander Kukushkin)

Since Patroni is heavily relying on superuser connections, we want to protect it from the possible attacks carried out using user-defined functions and/or operators in public schema with the same name and signature as the corresponding objects in pg_catalog. For that, search_path=pg_catalog is enforced for all connections created by Patroni (except replication connections).

Prevent passwords from being recorded in pg_stat_statements (Feike Steenbergen)

It is achieved by setting pg_stat_statements.track_utility=off when creating users.

Bugfixes

Declare proxy_address as optional (Denis Laxalde)

As it is effectively a non-required option.

Improve behaviour of the insecure option (Alexander Kukushkin)

Ctl’s insecure option didn’t work properly when client certificates were used for REST API requests.

Take watchdog configuration from bootstrap.dcs when the new cluster is bootstrapped (Matt Baker)

Patroni used to initially configure watchdog with defaults when bootstrapping a new cluster rather than taking configuration used to bootstrap the DCS.

Fix the way file extensions are treated while finding executables in WIN32 (Martín Marqués)

Only add .exe to a file name if it has no extension yet.

Fix Consul TTL setup (Alexander Kukushkin)

We used ttl/2.0 when setting the value on the HTTPClient, but forgot to multiply the current value by 2 in the class’ property. It was resulting in Consul TTL off by twice.

Removed functionality

Remove patronictl configure (Polina Bungina)

There is no more need for a separate patronictl config creation.

Version 2.1.5

Released 2022-11-28

This version enhances compatibility with PostgreSQL 15 and declares Etcd v3 support as production ready. The Patroni on Raft remains in Beta.

New features

Improve patroni --validate-config (Denis Laxalde)

Exit with code 1 if config is invalid and print errors to stderr.

Don’t drop replication slots in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is automatically creating/removing physical replication slots when members are joining/leaving the cluster. In pause slots will no longer be removed.

Support the HEAD request method for monitoring endpoints (Robert Cutajar)

If used instead of GET Patroni will return only the HTTP Status Code.

Support behave tests on Windows (Alexander Kukushkin)

Emulate graceful Patroni shutdown (SIGTERM) on Windows by introduce the new REST API endpoint POST /sigterm.

Introduce postgresql.proxy_address (Alexander Kukushkin)

It will be written to the member key in DCS as the proxy_url and could be used/useful for service discovery.

Stability improvements

Call pg_replication_slot_advance() from a thread (Alexander Kukushkin)

On busy clusters with many logical replication slots the pg_replication_slot_advance() call was affecting the main HA loop and could result in the member key expiration.

Archive possibly missing WALs before calling pg_rewind on the old primary (Polina Bungina)

If the primary crashed and was down during considerable time, some WAL files could be missing from archive and from the new primary. There is a chance that pg_rewind could remove these WAL files from the old primary making it impossible to start it as a standby. By archiving ready WAL files we not only mitigate this problem but in general improving continues archiving experience.

Ignore 403 errors when trying to create Kubernetes Service (Nick Hudson, Polina Bungina)

Patroni was spamming logs by unsuccessful attempts to create the service, which in fact could already exist.

Improve liveness probe (Alexander Kukushkin)

The liveness problem will start failing if the heartbeat loop is running longer than

ttl

on the primary or

2*ttl

on the replica. That will allow us to use it as an alternative for watchdog on Kubernetes.

Make sure only sync node tries to grab the lock when switchover (Alexander Kukushkin, Polina Bungina)

Previously there was a slim chance that up-to-date async member could become the leader if the manual switchover was performed without specifying the target.

Avoid cloning while bootstrap is running (Ants Aasma)

Do not allow a create replica method that does not require a leader to be triggered while the cluster bootstrap is running.

Compatibility with kazoo-2.9.0 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Depending on python version the SequentialThreadingHandler.select() method may raise TypeError and IOError exceptions if select() is called on the closed socket.

Explicitly shut down SSL connection before socket shutdown (Alexander Kukushkin)

Not doing it resulted in unexpected eof while reading errors with OpenSSL 3.0.

Compatibility with

prettytable>=2.2.0

(Alexander Kukushkin)

Due to the internal API changes the cluster name header was shown on the incorrect line.

Bugfixes

Handle expired token for Etcd lease_grant (monsterxx03)

In case of error get the new token and retry request.

Fix bug in the GET /read-only-sync endpoint (Alexander Kukushkin)

It was introduced in previous release and effectively never worked.

Handle the case when data dir storage disappeared (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is periodically checking that the PGDATA is there and not empty, but in case of issues with storage the os.listdir() is raising the OSError exception, breaking the heart-beat loop.

Apply master_stop_timeout when waiting for user backends to close (Alexander Kukushkin)

Something that looks like user backend could be in fact a background worker (e.g., Citus Maintenance Daemon) that is failing to stop.

Accept *:<port> for postgresql.listen (Denis Laxalde)

The patroni --validate-config was complaining about it being invalid.

Timeouts fixes in Raft (Alexander Kukushkin)

When Patroni or patronictl are starting they try to get Raft cluster topology from known members. These calls were made without proper timeouts.

Forcefully update consul service if token was changed (John A. Lotoski)

Not doing so results in errors “rpc error making call: rpc error making call: ACL not found”.

Version 2.1.4

Released 2022-06-01

New features

Improve pg_rewind behavior on typical Debian/Ubuntu systems (Gunnar “Nick” Bluth)

On Postgres setups that keep

postgresql.conf

outside of the data directory (e.g. Ubuntu/Debian packages), pg_rewind --restore-target-wal fails to figure out the value of the restore_command.

Allow setting TLSServerName on Consul service checks (Michael Gmelin)

Useful when checks are performed by IP and the Consul node_name is not a FQDN.

Added ppc64le support in watchdog (Jean-Michel Scheiwiler)

And fixed watchdog support on some non-x86 platforms.

Switched aws.py callback from boto to boto3 (Alexander Kukushkin)

boto 2.x is abandoned since 2018 and fails with python 3.9.

Periodically refresh service account token on K8s (Haitao Li)

Since Kubernetes v1.21 service account tokens expire in 1 hour.

Added /read-only-sync monitoring endpoint (Dennis4b)

It is similar to the /read-only but includes only synchronous replicas.

Stability improvements

Don’t copy the logical replication slot to a replica if there is a configuration mismatch in the logical decoding setup with the primary (Alexander Kukushkin)

A replica won’t copy a logical replication slot from the primary anymore if the slot doesn’t match the plugin or database configuration options. Previously, the check for whether the slot matches those configuration options was not performed until after the replica copied the slot and started with it, resulting in unnecessary and repeated restarts.

Special handling of recovery configuration parameters for PostgreSQL v12+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

While starting as replica Patroni should be able to update postgresql.conf and restart/reload if the leader address has changed by caching current parameters values instead of querying them from pg_settings.

Better handling of IPv6 addresses in the postgresql.listen parameters (Alexander Kukushkin)

Since the listen parameter has a port, people try to put IPv6 addresses into square brackets, which were not correctly stripped when there is more than one IP in the list.

Use replication credentials when performing divergence check only on PostgreSQL v10 and older (Alexander Kukushkin)

If rewind is enabled, Patroni will again use either superuser or rewind credentials on newer Postgres versions.

Bugfixes

Fixed missing import of dateutil.parser (Wesley Mendes)

Tests weren’t failing only because it was also imported from other modules.

Ensure that optime annotation is a string (Sebastian Hasler)

In certain cases Patroni was trying to pass it as numeric.

Better handling of failed pg_rewind attempt (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the primary becomes unavailable during pg_rewind, $PGDATA will be left in a broken state. Following that, Patroni will remove the data directory even if this is not allowed by the configuration.

Don’t remove slots annotations from the leader ConfigMap/Endpoint when PostgreSQL isn’t ready (Alexander Kukushkin)

If slots value isn’t passed the annotation will keep the current value.

Handle concurrency problem with K8s API watchers (Alexander Kukushkin)

Under certain (unknown) conditions watchers might become stale; as a result, attempt_to_acquire_leader() method could fail due to the HTTP status code 409. In that case we reset watchers connections and restart from scratch.

Version 2.1.3

Released 2022-02-18

New features

Added support for encrypted TLS keys for patronictl (Alexander Kukushkin)

It could be configured via ctl.keyfile_password or the PATRONI_CTL_KEYFILE_PASSWORD environment variable.

Added more metrics to the /metrics endpoint (Alexandre Pereira)

Specifically, patroni_pending_restart and patroni_is_paused.

Make it possible to specify multiple hosts in the standby cluster configuration (Michael Banck)

If the standby cluster is replicating from the Patroni cluster it might be nice to rely on client-side failover which is available in libpq since PostgreSQL v10. That is, the primary_conninfo on the standby leader and pg_rewind setting target_session_attrs=read-write in the connection string. The pgpass file will be generated with multiple lines (one line per host), and instead of calling CHECKPOINT on the primary cluster nodes the standby cluster will wait for pg_control to be updated.

Stability improvements

Compatibility with legacy psycopg2 (Alexander Kukushkin)

For example, the psycopg2 installed from Ubuntu 18.04 packages doesn’t have the UndefinedFile exception yet.

Restart etcd3 watcher if all Etcd nodes don’t respond (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the watcher is alive the get_cluster() method continues returning stale information even if all Etcd nodes are failing.

Don’t remove the leader lock in the standby cluster while paused (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously the lock was maintained only by the node that was running as a primary and not a standby leader.

Bugfixes

Fixed bug in the standby-leader bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was considering bootstrap as failed if Postgres didn’t start accepting connections after 60 seconds. The bug was introduced in the 2.1.2 release.

Fixed bug with failover to a cascading standby (Alexander Kukushkin)

When figuring out which slots should be created on cascading standby we forgot to take into account that the leader might be absent.

Fixed small issues in Postgres config validator (Alexander Kukushkin)

Integer parameters introduced in PostgreSQL v14 were failing to validate because min and max values were quoted in the validator.py

Use replication credentials when checking leader status (Alexander Kukushkin)

It could be that the remove_data_directory_on_diverged_timelines is set, but there is no rewind_credentials defined and superuser access between nodes is not allowed.

Fixed “port in use” error on REST API certificate replacement (Ants Aasma)

When switching certificates there was a race condition with a concurrent API request. If there is one active during the replacement period then the replacement will error out with a port in use error and Patroni gets stuck in a state without an active API server.

Fixed a bug in cluster bootstrap if passwords contain % characters (Bastien Wirtz)

The bootstrap method executes the DO block, with all parameters properly quoted, but the cursor.execute() method didn’t like an empty list with parameters passed.

Fixed the “AttributeError: no attribute ‘leader’” exception (Hrvoje Milković)

It could happen if the synchronous mode is enabled and the DCS content was wiped out.

Fix bug in divergence timeline check (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was falsely assuming that timelines have diverged. For pg_rewind it didn’t create any problem, but if pg_rewind is not allowed and the remove_data_directory_on_diverged_timelines is set, it resulted in reinitializing the former leader.

Version 2.1.2

Released 2021-12-03

New features

Compatibility with psycopg>=3.0 (Alexander Kukushkin)

By default psycopg2 is preferred.

psycopg>=3.0

will be used only if psycopg2 is not available or its version is too old.

Add dcs_last_seen field to the REST API (Michael Banck)

This field notes the last time (as unix epoch) a cluster member has successfully communicated with the DCS. This is useful to identify and/or analyze network partitions.

Release the leader lock when pg_controldata reports “shut down” (Alexander Kukushkin)

To solve the problem of slow switchover/shutdown in case archive_command is slow/failing, Patroni will remove the leader key immediately after pg_controldata started reporting PGDATA as shut down cleanly and it verified that there is at least one replica that received all changes. If there are no replicas that fulfill this condition the leader key is not removed and the old behavior is retained, i.e. Patroni will keep updating the lock.

Add sslcrldir connection parameter support (Kostiantyn Nemchenko)

The new connection parameter was introduced in the PostgreSQL v14.

Allow setting ACLs for ZNodes in Zookeeper (Alwyn Davis)

Introduce a new configuration option zookeeper.set_acls so that Kazoo will apply a default ACL for each ZNode that it creates.

Stability improvements

Delay the next attempt of recovery till next HA loop (Alexander Kukushkin)

If Postgres crashed due to out of disk space (for example) and fails to start because of that Patroni is too eagerly trying to recover it flooding logs.

Add log before demoting, which can take some time (Michael Banck)

It can take some time for the demote to finish and it might not be obvious from looking at the logs what exactly is going on.

Improve “I am” status messages (Michael Banck)

no action. I am a secondary ({0}) vs no action. I am ({0}), a secondary

Cast to int wal_keep_segments when converting to wal_keep_size (Jorge Solórzano)

It is possible to specify wal_keep_segments as a string in the global dynamic configuration and due to Python being a dynamically typed language the string was simply multiplied. Example: wal_keep_segments: "100" was converted to 100100100100100100100100100100100100100100100100MB.

Allow switchover only to sync nodes when synchronous replication is enabled (Alexander Kukushkin)

In addition to that do the leader race only against known synchronous nodes.

Use cached role as a fallback when Postgres is slow (Alexander Kukushkin)

In some extreme cases Postgres could be so slow that the normal monitoring query does not finish in a few seconds. The statement_timeout exception not being properly handled could lead to the situation where Postgres was not demoted on time when the leader key expired or the update failed. In case of such exception Patroni will use the cached role to determine whether Postgres is running as a primary.

Avoid unnecessary updates of the member ZNode (Alexander Kukushkin)

If no values have changed in the members data, the update should not happen.

Optimize checkpoint after promote (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid doing CHECKPOINT if the latest timeline is already stored in pg_control. It helps to avoid unnecessary CHECKPOINT right after initializing the new cluster with initdb.

Prefer members without nofailover when picking sync nodes (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously sync nodes were selected only based on the replication lag, hence the node with nofailover tag had the same chances to become synchronous as any other node. That behavior was confusing and dangerous at the same time because in case of a failed primary the failover could not happen automatically.

Remove duplicate hosts from the etcd machine cache (Michael Banck)

Advertised client URLs in the etcd cluster could be misconfigured. Removing duplicates in Patroni in this case is a low-hanging fruit.

Bugfixes

Skip temporary replication slots while doing slot management (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from v10 pg_basebackup creates a temporary replication slot for WAL streaming and Patroni was trying to drop it because the slot name looks unknown. In order to fix it, we skip all temporary slots when querying pg_stat_replication_slots view.

Ensure pg_replication_slot_advance() doesn’t timeout (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was using the default statement_timeout in this case and once the call failed there are very high chances that it will never recover, resulting in increased size of pg_wal and pg_catalog bloat.

The /status wasn’t updated on demote (Alexander Kukushkin)

After demoting PostgreSQL the old leader updates the last LSN in DCS. Starting from 2.1.0 the new /status key was introduced, but the optime was still written to the /optime/leader.

Handle DCS exceptions when demoting (Alexander Kukushkin)

While demoting the master due to failure to update the leader lock it could happen that DCS goes completely down and the get_cluster() call raises an exception. Not being handled properly it results in Postgres remaining stopped until DCS recovers.

The use_unix_socket_repl didn’t work is some cases (Alexander Kukushkin)

Specifically, if postgresql.unix_socket_directories is not set. In this case Patroni is supposed to use the default value from libpq.

Fix a few issues with Patroni REST API (Alexander Kukushkin)

The clusters_unlocked sometimes could be not defined, what resulted in exceptions in the GET /metrics endpoint. In addition to that the error handling method was assuming that the connect_address tuple always has two elements, while in fact there could be more in case of IPv6.

Wait for newly promoted node to finish recovery before deciding to rewind (Alexander Kukushkin)

It could take some time before the actual promote happens and the new timeline is created. Without waiting replicas could come to the conclusion that rewind isn’t required.

Handle missing timelines in a history file when deciding to rewind (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the current replica timeline is missing in the history file on the primary the replica was falsely assuming that rewind isn’t required.

Version 2.1.1

Released 2021-08-19

New features

Support for ETCD SRV name suffix (David Pavlicek)

Etcd allows to differentiate between multiple Etcd clusters under the same domain and from now on Patroni also supports it.

Enrich history with the new leader (huiyalin525)

It adds the new column to the patronictl history output.

Make the CA bundle configurable for in-cluster Kubernetes config (Aron Parsons)

By default Patroni is using /var/run/secrets/kubernetes.io/serviceaccount/ca.crt and this new feature allows specifying the custom kubernetes.cacert.

Support dynamically registering/deregistering as a Consul service and changing tags (Tommy Li)

Previously it required Patroni restart.

Bugfixes

Avoid unnecessary reload of REST API (Alexander Kukushkin)

The previous release added a feature of reloading REST API certificates if changed on disk. Unfortunately, the reload was happening unconditionally right after the start.

Don’t resolve cluster members when etcd.use_proxies is set (Alexander Kukushkin)

When starting up Patroni checks the healthiness of Etcd cluster by querying the list of members. In addition to that, it also tried to resolve their hostnames, which is not necessary when working with Etcd via proxy and was causing unnecessary warnings.

Skip rows with NULL values in the pg_stat_replication (Alexander Kukushkin)

It seems that the pg_stat_replication view could contain NULL values in the replay_lsn, flush_lsn, or write_lsn fields even when state = 'streaming'.

Version 2.1.0

Released 2021-07-06

This version adds compatibility with PostgreSQL v14, makes logical replication slots to survive failover/switchover, implements support of allowlist for REST API, and also reducing the number of logs to one line per heart-beat.

New features

Compatibility with PostgreSQL v14 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Unpause WAL replay if Patroni is not in a “pause” mode itself. It could be “paused” due to the change of certain parameters like for example max_connections on the primary.

Failover logical slots (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make logical replication slots survive failover/switchover on PostgreSQL v11+. The replication slot if copied from the primary to the replica with restart and later the pg_replication_slot_advance() [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/11/functions-admin.html#id-1.5.8.31.8.5.2.2.8.1.1] function is used to move it forward. As a result, the slot will already exist before the failover and no events should be lost, but, there is a chance that some events could be delivered more than once.

Implemented allowlist for Patroni REST API (Alexander Kukushkin)

If configured, only IP’s that matching rules would be allowed to call unsafe endpoints. In addition to that, it is possible to automatically include IP’s of members of the cluster to the list.

Added support of replication connections via unix socket (Mohamad El-Rifai)

Previously Patroni was always using TCP for replication connection what could cause some issues with SSL verification. Using unix sockets allows exempt replication user from SSL verification.

Health check on user-defined tags (Arman Jafari Tehrani)

Along with predefined tags: it is possible to specify any number of custom tags that become visible in the patronictl list output and in the REST API. From now on it is possible to use custom tags in health checks.

Added Prometheus /metrics endpoint (Mark Mercado, Michael Banck)

The endpoint exposing the same metrics as /patroni.

Reduced chattiness of Patroni logs (Alexander Kukushkin)

When everything goes normal, only one line will be written for every run of HA loop.

Breaking changes

The old permanent logical replication slots feature will no longer work with PostgreSQL v10 and older (Alexander Kukushkin)

The strategy of creating the logical slots after performing a promotion can’t guaranty that no logical events are lost and therefore disabled.

The /leader endpoint always returns 200 if the node holds the lock (Alexander Kukushkin)

Promoting the standby cluster requires updating load-balancer health checks, which is not very convenient and easy to forget. To solve it, we change the behavior of the /leader health check endpoint. It will return 200 without taking into account whether the cluster is normal or the standby_cluster.

Improvements in Raft support

Reliable support of Raft traffic encryption (Alexander Kukushkin)

Due to the different issues in the PySyncObj the encryption support was very unstable

Handle DNS issues in Raft implementation (Alexander Kukushkin)

If self_addr and/or partner_addrs are configured using the DNS name instead of IP’s the PySyncObj was effectively doing resolve only once when the object is created. It was causing problems when the same node was coming back online with a different IP.

Stability improvements

Compatibility with psycopg2-2.9+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

In psycopg2 the autocommit = True is ignored in the with connection block, which breaks replication protocol connections.

Fix excessive HA loop runs with Zookeeper (Alexander Kukushkin)

Update of member ZNodes was causing a chain reaction and resulted in running the HA loops multiple times in a row.

Reload if REST API certificate is changed on disk (Michael Todorovic)

If the REST API certificate file was updated in place Patroni didn’t perform a reload.

Don’t create pgpass dir if kerberos auth is used (Kostiantyn Nemchenko)

Kerberos and password authentication are mutually exclusive.

Fixed little issues with custom bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

Start Postgres with hot_standby=off only when we do a PITR and restart it after PITR is done.

Bugfixes

Compatibility with kazoo-2.7+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

Since Patroni is handling retries on its own, it is relying on the old behavior of kazoo that requests to a Zookeeper cluster are immediately discarded when there are no connections available.

Explicitly request the version of Etcd v3 cluster when it is known that we are connecting via proxy (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is working with Etcd v3 cluster via gPRC-gateway and it depending on the cluster version different endpoints (/v3, /v3beta, or /v3alpha) must be used. The version was resolved only together with the cluster topology, but since the latter was never done when connecting via proxy.

Version 2.0.2

Released 2021-02-22

New features

Ability to ignore externally managed replication slots (James Coleman)

Patroni is trying to remove any replication slot which is unknown to it, but there are certainly cases when replication slots should be managed externally. From now on it is possible to configure slots that should not be removed.

Added support for cipher suite limitation for REST API (Gunnar “Nick” Bluth)

It could be configured via restapi.ciphers or the PATRONI_RESTAPI_CIPHERS environment variable.

Added support for encrypted TLS keys for REST API (Jonathan S. Katz)

It could be configured via restapi.keyfile_password or the PATRONI_RESTAPI_KEYFILE_PASSWORD environment variable.

Constant time comparison of REST API authentication credentials (Alex Brasetvik)

Use hmac.compare_digest() instead of ==, which is vulnerable to timing attack.

Choose synchronous nodes based on replication lag (Krishna Sarabu)

If the replication lag on the synchronous node starts exceeding the configured threshold it could be demoted to asynchronous and/or replaced by the other node. Behaviour is controlled with maximum_lag_on_syncnode.

Stability improvements

Start postgres with hot_standby = off when doing custom bootstrap (Igor Yanchenko)

During custom bootstrap Patroni is restoring the basebackup, starting Postgres up, and waiting until recovery finishes. Some PostgreSQL parameters on the standby can’t be smaller than on the primary and if the new value (restored from WAL) is higher than the configured one, Postgres panics and stops. In order to avoid such behavior we will do custom bootstrap without hot_standby mode.

Warn the user if the required watchdog is not healthy (Nicolas Thauvin)

When the watchdog device is not writable or missing in required mode, the member cannot be promoted. Added a warning to show the user where to search for this misconfiguration.

Better verbosity for single-user mode recovery (Alexander Kukushkin)

If Patroni notices that PostgreSQL wasn’t shutdown clearly, in certain cases the crash-recovery is executed by starting Postgres in single-user mode. It could happen that the recovery failed (for example due to the lack of space on disk) but errors were swallowed.

Added compatibility with python-consul2 module (Alexander Kukushkin, Wilfried Roset)

The good old python-consul is not maintained since a few years, therefore someone created a fork with new features and bug-fixes.

Don’t use bypass_api_service when running patronictl (Alexander Kukushkin)

When a K8s pod is running in a non-default namespace it does not necessarily have enough permissions to query the kubernetes endpoint. In this case Patroni shows the warning and ignores the bypass_api_service setting. In case of patronictl the warning was a bit annoying.

Create raft.data_dir if it doesn’t exists or make sure that it is writable (Mark Mercado)

Improves user-friendliness and usability.

Bugfixes

Don’t interrupt restart or promote if lost leader lock in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

In pause it is allowed to run postgres as primary without lock.

Fixed issue with shutdown_request() in the REST API (Nicolas Limage)

In order to improve handling of SSL connections and delay the handshake until thread is started Patroni overrides a few methods in the HTTPServer. The shutdown_request() method was forgotten.

Fixed issue with sleep time when using Zookeeper (Alexander Kukushkin)

There were chances that Patroni was sleeping up to twice longer between running HA code.

Fixed invalid os.symlink() calls when moving data directory after failed bootstrap (Andrew L’Ecuyer)

If the bootstrap failed Patroni is renaming data directory, pg_wal, and all tablespaces. After that it updates symlinks so filesystem remains consistent. The symlink creation was failing due to the src and dst arguments being swapped.

Fixed bug in the post_bootstrap() method (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the superuser password wasn’t configured Patroni was failing to call the post_init script and therefore the whole bootstrap was failing.

Fixed an issues with pg_rewind in the standby cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the superuser name is different from Postgres, the pg_rewind in the standby cluster was failing because the connection string didn’t contain the database name.

Exit only if authentication with Etcd v3 explicitly failed (Alexander Kukushkin)

On start Patroni performs discovery of Etcd cluster topology and authenticates if it is necessarily. It could happen that one of etcd servers is not accessible, Patroni was trying to perform authentication on this server and failing instead of retrying with the next node.

Handle case with psutil cmdline() returning empty list (Alexander Kukushkin)

Zombie processes are still postmasters children, but they don’t have cmdline()

Treat PATRONI_KUBERNETES_USE_ENDPOINTS environment variable as boolean (Alexander Kukushkin)

Not doing so was making impossible disabling kubernetes.use_endpoints via environment.

Improve handling of concurrent endpoint update errors (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni will explicitly query the current endpoint object, verify that the current pod still holds the leader lock and repeat the update.

Version 2.0.1

Released 2020-10-01

New features

Use more as pager in patronictl edit-config if less is not available (Pavel Golub)

On Windows it would be the more.com. In addition to that, cdiff was changed to ydiff in requirements.txt, but patronictl still supports both for compatibility.

Added support of raft bind_addr and password (Alexander Kukushkin)

raft.bind_addr might be useful when running behind NAT. raft.password enables traffic encryption (requires the cryptography module).

Added sslpassword connection parameter support (Kostiantyn Nemchenko)

The connection parameter was introduced in PostgreSQL 13.

Stability improvements

Changed the behavior in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni will not call the bootstrap method if the PGDATA directory is missing/empty.

Patroni will not exit on sysid mismatch in pause, only log a warning.

The node will not try to grab the leader key in pause mode if Postgres is running not in recovery (accepting writes) but the sysid doesn’t match with the initialize key.

Apply master_start_timeout when executing crash recovery (Alexander Kukushkin)

If Postgres crashed on the leader node, Patroni does a crash-recovery by starting Postgres in single-user mode. During the crash-recovery the leader lock is being updated. If the crash-recovery didn’t finish in master_start_timeout seconds, Patroni will stop it forcefully and release the leader lock.

Removed the secure extra from the urllib3 requirements (Alexander Kukushkin)

The only reason for adding it there was the ipaddress dependency for python 2.7.

Bugfixes

Fixed a bug in the Kubernetes.update_leader() (Alexander Kukushkin)

An unhandled exception was preventing demoting the primary when the update of the leader object failed.

Fixed hanging patronictl when RAFT is being used (Alexander Kukushkin)

When using patronictl with Patroni config, self_addr should be added to the partner_addrs.

Fixed bug in get_guc_value() (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was failing to get the value of restore_command on PostgreSQL 12, therefore fetching missing WALs for pg_rewind didn’t work.

Version 2.0.0

Released 2020-09-02

This version enhances compatibility with PostgreSQL 13, adds support of multiple synchronous standbys, has significant improvements in handling of pg_rewind, adds support of Etcd v3 and Patroni on pure RAFT (without Etcd, Consul, or Zookeeper), and makes it possible to optionally call the pre_promote (fencing) script.

PostgreSQL 13 support

Don’t fire on_reload when promoting to standby_leader on PostgreSQL 13+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

When promoting to standby_leader we change primary_conninfo, update the role and reload Postgres. Since on_role_change and on_reload effectively duplicate each other, Patroni will call only on_role_change.

Added support for gssencmode and channel_binding connection parameters (Alexander Kukushkin)

PostgreSQL 12 introduced gssencmode and 13 channel_binding connection parameters and now they can be used if defined in the postgresql.authentication section.

Handle renaming of wal_keep_segments to wal_keep_size (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case of misconfiguration (wal_keep_segments on 13 and wal_keep_size on older versions) Patroni will automatically adjust the configuration.

Use pg_rewind with --restore-target-wal on 13 if possible (Alexander Kukushkin)

On PostgreSQL 13 Patroni checks if restore_command is configured and tells pg_rewind to use it.

New features

[BETA] Implemented support of Patroni on pure RAFT (Alexander Kukushkin)

This makes it possible to run Patroni without 3rd party dependencies, like Etcd, Consul, or Zookeeper. For HA you will have to run either three Patroni nodes or two nodes with Patroni and one node with patroni_raft_controller. For more information please check the documentation.

[BETA] Implemented support for Etcd v3 protocol via gPRC-gateway (Alexander Kukushkin)

Etcd 3.0 was released more than four years ago and Etcd 3.4 has v2 disabled by default. There are also chances that v2 will be completely removed from Etcd, therefore we implemented support of Etcd v3 in Patroni. In order to start using it you have to explicitly create the etcd3 section is the Patroni configuration file.

Supporting multiple synchronous standbys (Krishna Sarabu)

It allows running a cluster with more than one synchronous replicas. The maximum number of synchronous replicas is controlled by the new parameter synchronous_node_count. It is set to 1 by default and has no effect when the synchronous_mode is set to off.

Added possibility to call the pre_promote script (Sergey Dudoladov)

Unlike callbacks, the pre_promote script is called synchronously after acquiring the leader lock, but before promoting Postgres. If the script fails or exits with a non-zero exitcode, the current node will release the leader lock.

Added support for configuration directories (Floris van Nee)

YAML files in the directory loaded and applied in alphabetical order.

Advanced validation of PostgreSQL parameters (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case the specific parameter is not supported by the current PostgreSQL version or when its value is incorrect, Patroni will remove the parameter completely or try to fix the value.

Wake up the main thread when the forced checkpoint after promote completed (Alexander Kukushkin)

Replicas are waiting for checkpoint indication via member key of the leader in DCS. The key is normally updated only once per HA loop. Without waking the main thread up, replicas will have to wait up to loop_wait seconds longer than necessary.

Use of pg_stat_wal_receiver view on 9.6+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

The view contains up-to-date values of primary_conninfo and primary_slot_name, while the contents of recovery.conf could be stale.

Improved handing of IPv6 addresses in the Patroni config file (Mateusz Kowalski)

The IPv6 address is supposed to be enclosed into square brackets, but Patroni was expecting to get it plain. Now both formats are supported.

Added Consul service_tags configuration parameter (Robert Edström)

They are useful for dynamic service discovery, for example by load balancers.

Implemented SSL support for Zookeeper (Kostiantyn Nemchenko)

It requires kazoo>=2.6.0.

Implemented no_params option for custom bootstrap method (Kostiantyn Nemchenko)

It allows calling wal-g, pgBackRest and other backup tools without wrapping them into shell scripts.

Move WAL and tablespaces after a failed init (Feike Steenbergen)

When doing reinit, Patroni was already removing not only PGDATA but also the symlinked WAL directory and tablespaces. Now the move_data_directory() method will do a similar job, i.e. rename WAL directory and tablespaces and update symlinks in PGDATA.

Improved in pg_rewind support

Improved timeline divergence check (Alexander Kukushkin)

We don’t need to rewind when the replayed location on the replica is not ahead of the switchpoint or the end of the checkpoint record on the former primary is the same as the switchpoint. In order to get the end of the checkpoint record we use pg_waldump and parse its output.

Try to fetch missing WAL if pg_rewind complains about it (Alexander Kukushkin)

It could happen that the WAL segment required for pg_rewind doesn’t exist in the pg_wal directory anymore and therefore pg_rewind can’t find the checkpoint location before the divergence point. Starting from PostgreSQL 13 pg_rewind could use restore_command for fetching missing WALs. For older PostgreSQL versions Patroni parses the errors of a failed rewind attempt and tries to fetch the missing WAL by calling the restore_command on its own.

Detect a new timeline in the standby cluster and trigger rewind/reinitialize if necessary (Alexander Kukushkin)

The standby_cluster is decoupled from the primary cluster and therefore doesn’t immediately know about leader elections and timeline switches. In order to detect the fact, the standby_leader periodically checks for new history files in pg_wal.

Shorten and beautify history log output (Alexander Kukushkin)

When Patroni is trying to figure out the necessity of pg_rewind, it could write the content of the history file from the primary into the log. The history file is growing with every failover/switchover and eventually starts taking up too many lines, most of which are not so useful. Instead of showing the raw data, Patroni will show only 3 lines before the current replica timeline and 2 lines after.

Improvements on K8s

Get rid of kubernetes python module (Alexander Kukushkin)

The official python kubernetes client contains a lot of auto-generated code and therefore very heavy. Patroni uses only a small fraction of K8s API endpoints and implementing support for them wasn’t hard.

Make it possible to bypass the kubernetes service (Alexander Kukushkin)

When running on K8s, Patroni is usually communicating with the K8s API via the kubernetes service, the address of which is exposed in the KUBERNETES_SERVICE_HOST environment variable. Like any other service, the kubernetes service is handled by kube-proxy, which in turn, depending on the configuration, is either relying on a userspace program or iptables for traffic routing. Skipping the intermediate component and connecting directly to the K8s master nodes allows us to implement a better retry strategy and mitigate risks of demoting Postgres when K8s master nodes are upgraded.

Sync HA loops of all pods of a Patroni cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

Not doing so was increasing failure detection time from ttl to ttl + loop_wait.

Populate references and nodename in the subsets addresses on K8s (Alexander Kukushkin)

Some load-balancers are relying on this information.

Fix possible race conditions in the update_leader() (Alexander Kukushkin)

The concurrent update of the leader configmap or endpoint happening outside of Patroni might cause the update_leader() call to fail. In this case Patroni rechecks that the current node is still owning the leader lock and repeats the update.

Explicitly disallow patching non-existent config (Alexander Kukushkin)

For DCS other than kubernetes the PATCH call is failing with an exception due to cluster.config being None, but on Kubernetes it was happily creating the config annotation and preventing writing bootstrap configuration after the bootstrap finished.

Fix bug in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

Replicas were removing primary_conninfo and restarting Postgres when the leader key was absent, but they should do nothing.

Improvements in REST API

Defer TLS handshake until worker thread has started (Alexander Kukushkin, Ben Harris)

If the TLS handshake was done in the API thread and the client-side didn’t send any data, the API thread was blocked (risking DoS).

Check basic-auth independently from client certificate in REST API (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously only the client certificate was validated. Doing two checks independently is an absolutely valid use-case.

Write double CRLF after HTTP headers of the OPTIONS request (Sergey Burladyan)

HAProxy was happy with a single CRLF, while Consul health-check complained about broken connection and unexpected EOF.

GET /cluster was showing stale members info for Zookeeper (Alexander Kukushkin)

The endpoint was using the Patroni internal cluster view. For Patroni itself it didn’t cause any issues, but when exposed to the outside world we need to show up-to-date information, especially replication lag.

Fixed health-checks for standby cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

The GET /standby-leader for a master and GET /master for a standby_leader were incorrectly responding with 200.

Implemented DELETE /switchover (Alexander Kukushkin)

The REST API call deletes the scheduled switchover.

Created /readiness and /liveness endpoints (Alexander Kukushkin)

They could be useful to eliminate “unhealthy” pods from subsets addresses when the K8s service is used with label selectors.

Enhanced GET /replica and GET /async REST API health-checks (Krishna Sarabu, Alexander Kukushkin)

Checks now support optional keyword ?lag=<max-lag> and will respond with 200 only if the lag is smaller than the supplied value. If relying on this feature please keep in mind that information about WAL position on the leader is updated only every loop_wait seconds!

Added support for user defined HTTP headers in the REST API response (Yogesh Sharma)

This feature might be useful if requests are made from a browser.

Improvements in patronictl

Don’t try to call non-existing leader in patronictl pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

While pausing a cluster without a leader on K8s, patronictl was showing warnings that member “None” could not be accessed.

Handle the case when member conn_url is missing (Alexander Kukushkin)

On K8s it is possible that the pod doesn’t have the necessary annotations because Patroni is not yet running. It was making patronictl to fail.

Added ability to print ASCII cluster topology (Maxim Fedotov, Alexander Kukushkin)

It is very useful to get overview of the cluster with cascading replication.

Implement patronictl flush switchover (Alexander Kukushkin)

Before that patronictl flush only supported cancelling scheduled restarts.

Bugfixes

Attribute error during bootstrap of the cluster with existing PGDATA (Krishna Sarabu)

When trying to create/update the /history key, Patroni was accessing the ClusterConfig object which wasn’t created in DCS yet.

Improved exception handling in Consul (Alexander Kukushkin)

Unhandled exception in the touch_member() method caused the whole Patroni process to crash.

Enforce synchronous_commit=local for the post_init script (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni was already doing that when creating users (replication, rewind), but missing it in the case of post_init was an oversight. As a result, if the script wasn’t doing it internally on it’s own the bootstrap in synchronous_mode wasn’t able to finish.

Increased maxsize in the Consul pool manager (ponvenkates)

With the default size=1 some warnings were generated.

Patroni was wrongly reporting Postgres as running (Alexander Kukushkin)

The state wasn’t updated when for example Postgres crashed due to an out-of-disk error.

Put * into pgpass instead of missing or empty values (Alexander Kukushkin)

If for example the standby_cluster.port is not specified, the pgpass file was incorrectly generated.

Skip physical replication slot creation on the leader node with special characters (Krishna Sarabu)

Patroni appeared to be creating a dormant slot (when slots defined) for the leader node when the name contained special chars such as ‘-’ (for e.g. “abc-us-1”).

Avoid removing non-existent pg_hba.conf in the custom bootstrap (Krishna Sarabu)

Patroni was failing if pg_hba.conf happened to be located outside of the pgdata dir after custom bootstrap.

Version 1.6.5

Released 2020-08-23

New features

Master stop timeout (Krishna Sarabu)

The number of seconds Patroni is allowed to wait when stopping Postgres. Effective only when synchronous_mode is enabled. When set to value greater than 0 and the synchronous_mode is enabled, Patroni sends SIGKILL to the postmaster if the stop operation is running for more than the value set by master_stop_timeout. Set the value according to your durability/availability tradeoff. If the parameter is not set or set to non-positive value, master_stop_timeout does not have an effect.

Don’t create permanent physical slot with name of the primary (Alexander Kukushkin)

It is a common problem that the primary recycles WAL segments while the replica is down. Now we have a good solution for static clusters, with a fixed number of nodes and names that never change. You just need to list the names of all nodes in the slots so the primary will not remove the slot when the node is down (not registered in DCS).

First draft of Config Validator (Igor Yanchenko)

Use patroni --validate-config patroni.yaml in order to validate Patroni configuration.

Possibility to configure max length of timelines history (Krishna Sarabu)

Patroni writes the history of failovers/switchovers into the /history key in DCS. Over time the size of this key becomes big, but in most cases only the last few lines are interesting. The max_timelines_history parameter allows to specify the maximum number of timeline history items to be kept in DCS.

Kazoo 2.7.0 compatibility (Danyal Prout)

Some non-public methods in Kazoo changed their signatures, but Patroni was relying on them.

Improvements in patronictl

Show member tags (Kostiantyn Nemchenko, Alexander Kukushkin)

Tags are configured individually for every node and there was no easy way to get an overview of them

Improve members output (Alexander Kukushkin)

The redundant cluster name won’t be shown anymore on every line, only in the table header.

$ patronictl list
+ Cluster: batman (6813309862653668387) +---------+----+-----------+---------------------+
|    Member   |      Host      |  Role  |  State  | TL | Lag in MB | Tags                |
+-------------+----------------+--------+---------+----+-----------+---------------------+
| postgresql0 | 127.0.0.1:5432 | Leader | running |  3 |           | clonefrom: true     |
|             |                |        |         |    |           | noloadbalance: true |
|             |                |        |         |    |           | nosync: true        |
+-------------+----------------+--------+---------+----+-----------+---------------------+
| postgresql1 | 127.0.0.1:5433 |        | running |  3 |       0.0 |                     |
+-------------+----------------+--------+---------+----+-----------+---------------------+

Fail if a config file is specified explicitly but not found (Kaarel Moppel)

Previously patronictl was only reporting a DEBUG message.

Solved the problem of not initialized K8s pod breaking patronictl (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is relying on certain pod annotations on K8s. When one of the Patroni pods is stopping or starting there is no valid annotation yet and patronictl was failing with an exception.

Stability improvements

Apply 1 second backoff if LIST call to K8s API server failed (Alexander Kukushkin)

It is mostly necessary to avoid flooding logs, but also helps to prevent starvation of the main thread.

Retry if the retry-after HTTP header is returned by K8s API (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the K8s API server is overwhelmed with requests it might ask to retry.

Scrub KUBERNETES_ environment from the postmaster (Feike Steenbergen)

The KUBERNETES_ environment variables are not required for PostgreSQL, yet having them exposed to the postmaster will also expose them to backends and to regular database users (using pl/perl for example).

Clean up tablespaces on reinitialize (Krishna Sarabu)

During reinit, Patroni was removing only PGDATA and leaving user-defined tablespace directories. This is causing Patroni to loop in reinit. The previous workarond for the problem was implementing the custom bootstrap script.

Explicitly execute CHECKPOINT after promote happened (Alexander Kukushkin)

It helps to reduce the time before the new primary is usable for pg_rewind.

Smart refresh of Etcd members (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case Patroni failed to execute a request on all members of the Etcd cluster, Patroni will re-check A or SRV records for changes of IPs/hosts before retrying the next time.

Skip missing values from pg_controldata (Feike Steenbergen)

Values are missing when trying to use binaries of a version that doesn’t match PGDATA. Patroni will try to start Postgres anyway, and Postgres will complain that the major version doesn’t match and abort with an error.

Bugfixes

Disable SSL verification for Consul when required (Julien Riou)

Starting from a certain version of urllib3, the cert_reqs must be explicitly set to ssl.CERT_NONE in order to effectively disable SSL verification.

Avoid opening replication connection on every cycle of HA loop (Alexander Kukushkin)

Regression was introduced in 1.6.4.

Call on_role_change callback on failed primary (Alexander Kukushkin)

In certain cases it could lead to the virtual IP remaining attached to the old primary. Regression was introduced in 1.4.5.

Reset rewind state if postgres started after successful pg_rewind (Alexander Kukushkin)

As a result of this bug Patroni was starting up manually shut down postgres in the pause mode.

Convert recovery_min_apply_delay to ms when checking recovery.conf

Patroni was indefinitely restarting replica if recovery_min_apply_delay was configured on PostgreSQL older than 12.

PyInstaller compatibility (Alexander Kukushkin)

PyInstaller freezes (packages) Python applications into stand-alone executables. The compatibility was broken when we switched to the spawn method instead of fork for multiprocessing.

Version 1.6.4

Released 2020-01-27

New features

Implemented --wait option for patronictl reinit (Igor Yanchenko)

Patronictl will wait for reinit to finish is the --wait option is used.

Further improvements of Windows support (Igor Yanchenko, Alexander Kukushkin)

All shell scripts which are used for integration testing are rewritten in python

The pg_ctl kill will be used to stop postgres on non posix systems

Don’t try to use unix-domain sockets

Stability improvements

Make sure unix_socket_directories and stats_temp_directory exist (Igor Yanchenko)

Upon the start of Patroni and Postgres make sure that unix_socket_directories and stats_temp_directory exist or try to create them. Patroni will exit if failed to create them.

Make sure postgresql.pgpass is located in the place where Patroni has write access (Igor Yanchenko)

In case if it doesn’t have a write access Patroni will exit with exception.

Disable Consul serfHealth check by default (Kostiantyn Nemchenko)

Even in case of little network problems the failing serfHealth leads to invalidation of all sessions associated with the node. Therefore, the leader key is lost much earlier than ttl which causes unwanted restarts of replicas and maybe demotion of the primary.

Configure tcp keepalives for connections to K8s API (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case if we get nothing from the socket after TTL seconds it can be considered dead.

Avoid logging of passwords on user creation (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the password is rejected or logging is configured to verbose or not configured at all it might happen that the password is written into postgres logs. In order to avoid it Patroni will change log_statement, log_min_duration_statement, and log_min_error_statement to some safe values before doing the attempt to create/update user.

Bugfixes

Use restore_command from the standby_cluster config on cascading replicas (Alexander Kukushkin)

The standby_leader was already doing it from the beginning the feature existed. Not doing the same on replicas might prevent them from catching up with standby leader.

Update timeline reported by the standby cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case of timeline switch the standby cluster was correctly replicating from the primary but patronictl was reporting the old timeline.

Allow certain recovery parameters be defined in the custom_conf (Alexander Kukushkin)

When doing validation of recovery parameters on replica Patroni will skip archive_cleanup_command, promote_trigger_file, recovery_end_command, recovery_min_apply_delay, and restore_command if they are not defined in the patroni config but in files other than postgresql.auto.conf or postgresql.conf.

Improve handling of postgresql parameters with period in its name (Alexander Kukushkin)

Such parameters could be defined by extensions where the unit is not necessarily a string. Changing the value might require a restart (for example pg_stat_statements.max).

Improve exception handling during shutdown (Alexander Kukushkin)

During shutdown Patroni is trying to update its status in the DCS. If the DCS is inaccessible an exception might be raised. Lack of exception handling was preventing logger thread from stopping.

Version 1.6.3

Released 2019-12-05

Bugfixes

Don’t expose password when running pg_rewind (Alexander Kukushkin)

Bug was introduced in the #1301 [https://github.com/patroni/patroni/pull/1301]

Apply connection parameters specified in the postgresql.authentication to pg_basebackup and custom replica creation methods (Alexander Kukushkin)

They were relying on url-like connection string and therefore parameters never applied.

Version 1.6.2

Released 2019-12-05

New features

Implemented patroni --version (Igor Yanchenko)

It prints the current version of Patroni and exits.

Set the user-agent http header for all http requests (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is communicating with Consul, Etcd, and Kubernetes API via the http protocol. Having a specifically crafted user-agent (example: Patroni/1.6.2 Python/3.6.8 Linux) might be useful for debugging and monitoring.

Make it possible to configure log level for exception tracebacks (Igor Yanchenko)

If you set log.traceback_level=DEBUG the tracebacks will be visible only when log.level=DEBUG. The default behavior remains the same.

Stability improvements

Avoid importing all DCS modules when searching for the module required by the config file (Alexander Kukushkin)

There is no need to import modules for Etcd, Consul, and Kubernetes if we need only e.g. Zookeeper. It helps to reduce memory usage and solves the problem of having INFO messages Failed to import smth.

Removed python requests module from explicit requirements (Alexander Kukushkin)

It wasn’t used for anything critical, but causing a lot of problems when the new version of urllib3 is released.

Improve handling of etcd.hosts written as a comma-separated string instead of YAML array (Igor Yanchenko)

Previously it was failing when written in format host1:port1, host2:port2 (the space character after the comma).

Usability improvements

Don’t force users to choose members from an empty list in patronictl (Igor Yanchenko)

If the user provides a wrong cluster name, we will raise an exception rather than ask to choose a member from an empty list.

Make the error message more helpful if the REST API cannot bind (Igor Yanchenko)

For an inexperienced user it might be hard to figure out what is wrong from the Python stacktrace.

Bugfixes

Fix calculation of wal_buffers (Alexander Kukushkin)

The base unit has been changed from 8 kB blocks to bytes in PostgreSQL 11.

Use passfile in primary_conninfo only on PostgreSQL 10+ (Alexander Kukushkin)

On older versions there is no guarantee that passfile will work, unless the latest version of libpq is installed.

Version 1.6.1

Released 2019-11-15

New features

Added PATRONICTL_CONFIG_FILE environment variable (msvechla)

It allows configuring the --config-file argument for patronictl from the environment.

Implement patronictl history (Alexander Kukushkin)

It shows the history of failovers/switchovers.

Pass -c statement_timeout=0 in PGOPTIONS when doing pg_rewind (Alexander Kukushkin)

It protects from the case when statement_timeout on the server is set to some small value and one of the statements executed by pg_rewind is canceled.

Allow lower values for PostgreSQL configuration (Soulou)

Patroni didn’t allow some of the PostgreSQL configuration parameters be set smaller than some hardcoded values. Now the minimal allowed values are smaller, default values have not been changed.

Allow for certificate-based authentication (Jonathan S. Katz)

This feature enables certificate-based authentication for superuser, replication, rewind accounts and allows the user to specify the sslmode they wish to connect with.

Use the passfile in the primary_conninfo instead of password (Alexander Kukushkin)

It allows to avoid setting 600 permissions on postgresql.conf

Perform pg_ctl reload regardless of config changes (Alexander Kukushkin)

It is possible that some config files are not controlled by Patroni. When somebody is doing a reload via the REST API or by sending SIGHUP to the Patroni process, the usual expectation is that Postgres will also be reloaded. Previously it didn’t happen when there were no changes in the postgresql section of Patroni config.

Compare all recovery parameters, not only primary_conninfo (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously the check_recovery_conf() method was only checking whether primary_conninfo has changed, never taking into account all other recovery parameters.

Make it possible to apply some recovery parameters without restart (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from PostgreSQL 12 the following recovery parameters could be changed without restart: archive_cleanup_command, promote_trigger_file, recovery_end_command, and recovery_min_apply_delay. In future Postgres releases this list will be extended and Patroni will support it automatically.

Make it possible to change use_slots online (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously it required restarting Patroni and removing slots manually.

Remove only PATRONI_ prefixed environment variables when starting up Postgres (Cody Coons)

It will solve a lot of problems with running different Foreign Data Wrappers.

Stability improvements

Use LIST + WATCH when working with K8s API (Alexander Kukushkin)

It allows to efficiently receive object changes (pods, endpoints/configmaps) and makes less stress on K8s master nodes.

Improve the workflow when PGDATA is not empty during bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

According to the initdb source code it might consider a PGDATA empty when there are only lost+found and .dotfiles in it. Now Patroni does the same. If PGDATA happens to be non-empty, and at the same time not valid from the pg_controldata point of view, Patroni will complain and exit.

Avoid calling expensive os.listdir() on every HA loop (Alexander Kukushkin)

When the system is under IO stress, os.listdir() could take a few seconds (or even minutes) to execute, badly affecting the HA loop of Patroni. This could even cause the leader key to disappear from DCS due to the lack of updates. There is a better and less expensive way to check that the PGDATA is not empty. Now we check the presence of the global/pg_control file in the PGDATA.

Some improvements in logging infrastructure (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously there was a possibility to loose the last few log lines on shutdown because the logging thread was a daemon thread.

Use spawn multiprocessing start method on python 3.4+ (Maciej Kowalczyk)

It is a known issue [https://bugs.python.org/issue6721] in Python that threading and multiprocessing do not mix well. Switching from the default method fork to the spawn is a recommended workaround. Not doing so might result in the Postmaster starting process hanging and Patroni indefinitely reporting INFO: restarting after failure in progress, while Postgres is actually up and running.

Improvements in REST API

Make it possible to check client certificates in the REST API (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the verify_client is set to required, Patroni will check client certificates for all REST API calls. When it is set to optional, client certificates are checked for all unsafe REST API endpoints.

Return the response code 503 for the GET /replica health check request if Postgres is not running (Alexander Anikin)

Postgres might spend significant time in recovery before it starts accepting client connections.

Implement /history and /cluster endpoints (Alexander Kukushkin)

The /history endpoint shows the content of the history key in DCS. The /cluster endpoint shows all cluster members and some service info like pending and scheduled restarts or switchovers.

Improvements in Etcd support

Retry on Etcd RAFT internal error (Alexander Kukushkin)

When the Etcd node is being shut down, it sends response code=300, data='etcdserver: server stopped', which was causing Patroni to demote the primary.

Don’t give up on Etcd request retry too early (Alexander Kukushkin)

When there were some network problems, Patroni was quickly exhausting the list of Etcd nodes and giving up without using the whole retry_timeout, potentially resulting in demoting the primary.

Bugfixes

Disable synchronous_commit when granting execute permissions to the pg_rewind user (kremius)

If the bootstrap is done with synchronous_mode_strict: true the

GRANT EXECUTE

statement was waiting indefinitely due to the non-synchronous nodes being available.

Fix memory leak on python 3.7 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni is using ThreadingMixIn to process REST API requests and python 3.7 made threads spawn for every request non-daemon by default.

Fix race conditions in asynchronous actions (Alexander Kukushkin)

There was a chance that patronictl reinit --force could be overwritten by the attempt to recover stopped Postgres. This ended up in a situation when Patroni was trying to start Postgres while basebackup was running.

Fix race condition in postmaster_start_time() method (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the method is executed from the REST API thread, it requires a separate cursor object to be created.

Fix the problem of not promoting the sync standby that had a name containing upper case letters (Alexander Kukushkin)

We converted the name to the lower case because Postgres was doing the same while comparing the application_name with the value in synchronous_standby_names.

Kill all children along with the callback process before starting the new one (Alexander Kukushkin)

Not doing so makes it hard to implement callbacks in bash and eventually can lead to the situation when two callbacks are running at the same time.

Fix ‘start failed’ issue (Alexander Kukushkin)

Under certain conditions the Postgres state might be set to ‘start failed’ despite Postgres being up and running.

Version 1.6.0

Released 2019-08-05

This version adds compatibility with PostgreSQL 12, makes is possible to run pg_rewind without superuser on PostgreSQL 11 and newer, and enables IPv6 support.

New features

Psycopg2 was removed from requirements and must be installed independently (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from 2.8.0 psycopg2 was split into two different packages, psycopg2, and psycopg2-binary, which could be installed at the same time into the same place on the filesystem. In order to decrease dependency hell problem, we let a user choose how to install it. There are a few options available, please consult the documentation.

Compatibility with PostgreSQL 12 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from PostgreSQL 12 there is no recovery.conf anymore and all former recovery parameters are converted into GUC [https://www.enterprisedb.com/blog/what-is-a-guc-variable]. In order to protect from ALTER SYSTEM SET primary_conninfo or similar, Patroni will parse postgresql.auto.conf and remove all standby and recovery parameters from there. Patroni config remains backward compatible. For example despite restore_command being a GUC, one can still specify it in the postgresql.recovery_conf.restore_command section and Patroni will write it into postgresql.conf for PostgreSQL 12.

Make it possible to use pg_rewind without superuser on PostgreSQL 11 and newer (Alexander Kukushkin)

If you want to use this feature please define username and password in the postgresql.authentication.rewind section of Patroni configuration file. For an already existing cluster you will have to create the user manually and GRANT EXECUTE permission on a few functions. You can find more details in the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/11/app-pgrewind.html#id-1.9.5.8.8].

Do a smart comparison of actual and desired primary_conninfo values on replicas (Alexander Kukushkin)

It might help to avoid replica restart when you are converting an already existing primary-standby cluster to one managed by Patroni

IPv6 support (Alexander Kukushkin)

There were two major issues. Patroni REST API service was listening only on 0.0.0.0 and IPv6 IP addresses used in the api_url and conn_url were not properly quoted.

Kerberos support (Ajith Vilas, Alexander Kukushkin)

It makes possible using Kerberos authentication between Postgres nodes instead of defining passwords in Patroni configuration file

Manage pg_ident.conf (Alexander Kukushkin)

This functionality works similarly to pg_hba.conf: if the postgresql.pg_ident is defined in the config file or DCS, Patroni will write its value to pg_ident.conf, however, if postgresql.parameters.ident_file is defined, Patroni will assume that pg_ident is managed from outside and not update the file.

Improvements in REST API

Added /health endpoint (Wilfried Roset)

It will return an HTTP status code only if PostgreSQL is running

Added /read-only and /read-write endpoints (Julien Riou)

The /read-only endpoint enables reads balanced across replicas and the primary. The /read-write endpoint is an alias for /primary, /leader and /master.

Use SSLContext to wrap the REST API socket (Julien Riou)

Usage of ssl.wrap_socket() is deprecated and was still allowing soon-to-be-deprecated protocols like TLS 1.1.

Logging improvements

Two-step logging (Alexander Kukushkin)

All log messages are first written into the in-memory queue and later they are asynchronously flushed into the stderr or file from a separate thread. The maximum queue size is limited (configurable). If the limit is reached, Patroni will start losing logs, which is still better than blocking the HA loop.

Enable debug logging for GET/OPTIONS API calls together with latency (Jan Tomsa)

It will help with debugging of health-checks performed by HAProxy, Consul or other tooling that decides which node is the primary/replica.

Log exceptions caught in Retry (Daniel Kucera)

Log the final exception when either the number of attempts or the timeout were reached. It will hopefully help to debug some issues when communication to DCS fails.

Improvements in patronictl

Enhance dialogues for scheduled switchover and restart (Rafia Sabih)

Previously dialogues did not take into account scheduled actions and therefore were misleading.

Check if config file exists (Wilfried Roset)

Be verbose about configuration file when the given filename does not exists, instead of ignoring silently (which can lead to misunderstanding).

Add fallback value for EDITOR (Wilfried Roset)

When the EDITOR environment variable was not defined, patronictl edit-config was failing with

PatroniCtlException

. The new strategy is to try editor and than vi, which should be available on most systems.

Improvements in Consul support

Allow to specify Consul consistency mode (Jan Tomsa)

You can read more about consistency mode here [https://www.consul.io/api/features/consistency.html].

Reload Consul config on SIGHUP (Cameron Daniel Kucera, Alexander Kukushkin)

It is especially useful when somebody is changing the value of token.

Bugfixes

Fix corner case in switchover/failover (Sharoon Thomas)

The variable scheduled_at may be undefined if REST API is not accessible and we are using DCS as a fallback.

Open trust to localhost in pg_hba.conf during custom bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously it was open only to unix_socket, which was causing a lot of errors: FATAL:  no pg_hba.conf entry for replication connection from host "127.0.0.1", user "replicator"

Consider synchronous node as healthy even when the former leader is ahead (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the primary loses access to the DCS, it restarts Postgres in read-only, but it might happen that other nodes can still access the old primary via the REST API. Such a situation was causing the synchronous standby not to promote because the old primary was reporting WAL position ahead of the synchronous standby.

Standby cluster bugfixes (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make it possible to bootstrap a replica in a standby cluster when the standby_leader is not accessible and a few other minor fixes.

Version 1.5.6

Released 2019-08-03

New features

Support work with etcd cluster via set of proxies (Alexander Kukushkin)

It might happen that etcd cluster is not accessible directly but via set of proxies. In this case Patroni will not perform etcd topology discovery but just round-robin via proxy hosts. Behavior is controlled by

etcd.use_proxies

.

Changed callbacks behavior when role on the node is changed (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the role was changed from

master

or

standby_leader

to

replica

or from

replica

to

standby_leader

,

on_restart

callback will not be called anymore in favor of

on_role_change

callback.

Change the way how we start postgres (Alexander Kukushkin)

Use

multiprocessing.Process

instead of executing itself and

multiprocessing.Pipe

to transmit the postmaster pid to the Patroni process. Before that we were using pipes, what was leaving postmaster process with stdin closed.

Bug fixes

Fix role returned by REST API for the standby leader (Alexander Kukushkin)

It was incorrectly returning

replica

instead of

standby_leader

Wait for callback end if it could not be killed (Julien Tachoires)

Patroni doesn’t have enough privileges to terminate the callback script running under

sudo

what was cancelling the new callback. If the running script could not be killed, Patroni will wait until it finishes and then run the next callback.

Reduce lock time taken by dcs.get_cluster method (Alexander Kukushkin)

Due to the lock being held DCS slowness was affecting the REST API health checks causing false positives.

Improve cleaning of PGDATA when

pg_wal

/

pg_xlog

is a symlink (Julien Tachoires)

In this case Patroni will explicitly remove files from the target directory.

Remove unnecessary usage of os.path.relpath (Ants Aasma)

It depends on being able to resolve the working directory, what will fail if Patroni is started in a directory that is later unlinked from the filesystem.

Do not enforce ssl version when communicating with Etcd (Alexander Kukushkin)

For some unknown reason python3-etcd on debian and ubuntu are not based on the latest version of the package and therefore it enforces TLSv1 which is not supported by Etcd v3. We solved this problem on Patroni side.

Version 1.5.5

Released 2019-02-15

This version introduces the possibility of automatic reinit of the former master, improves patronictl list output and fixes a number of bugs.

New features

Add support of

PATRONI_ETCD_PROTOCOL

,

PATRONI_ETCD_USERNAME

and

PATRONI_ETCD_PASSWORD

environment variables (Étienne M)

Before it was possible to configure them only in the config file or as a part of

PATRONI_ETCD_URL

, which is not always convenient.

Make it possible to automatically reinit the former master (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the pg_rewind is disabled or can’t be used, the former master could fail to start as a new replica due to diverged timelines. In this case, the only way to fix it is wiping the data directory and reinitializing. This behavior could be changed by setting

postgresql.remove_data_directory_on_diverged_timelines

. When it is set, Patroni will wipe the data directory and reinitialize the former master automatically.

Show information about timelines in patronictl list (Alexander Kukushkin)

It helps to detect stale replicas. In addition to that,

Host

will include ‘:{port}’ if the port value isn’t default or there is more than one member running on the same host.

Create a headless service associated with the $SCOPE-config endpoint (Alexander Kukushkin)

The “config” endpoint keeps information about the cluster-wide Patroni and Postgres configuration, history file, and last but the most important, it holds the

initialize

key. When the Kubernetes master node is restarted or upgraded, it removes endpoints without services. The headless service will prevent it from being removed.

Bug fixes

Adjust the read timeout for the leader watch blocking query (Alexander Kukushkin)

According to the Consul documentation, the actual response timeout is increased by a small random amount of additional wait time added to the supplied maximum wait time to spread out the wake up time of any concurrent requests. It adds up to

wait / 16

additional time to the maximum duration. In our case we are adding

wait / 15

or 1 second depending on what is bigger.

Always use replication=1 when connecting via replication protocol to the postgres (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from Postgres 10 the line in the pg_hba.conf with database=replication doesn’t accept connections with the parameter replication=database.

Don’t write primary_conninfo into recovery.conf for wal-only standby cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

Despite not having neither

host

nor

port

defined in the

standby_cluster

config, Patroni was putting the

primary_conninfo

into the

recovery.conf

, which is useless and generating a lot of errors.

Version 1.5.4

Released 2019-01-15

This version implements flexible logging and fixes a number of bugs.

New features

Improvements in logging infrastructure (Alexander Kukushkin, Lucas Capistrant, Alexander Anikin)

Logging configuration could be configured not only from environment variables but also from Patroni config file. It makes it possible to change logging configuration in runtime by updating config and doing reload or sending SIGHUP to the Patroni process. By default Patroni writes logs to stderr, but now it becomes possible to write logs directly into the file and rotate when it reaches a certain size. In addition to that added support of custom dateformat and the possibility to fine-tune log level for each python module.

Make it possible to take into account the current timeline during leader elections (Alexander Kukushkin)

It could happen that the node is considering itself as a healthiest one although it is currently not on the latest known timeline. In some cases we want to avoid promoting of such node, which could be achieved by setting

check_timeline

parameter to

true

(default behavior remains unchanged).

Relaxed requirements on superuser credentials

Libpq allows opening connections without explicitly specifying neither username nor password. Depending on situation it relies either on pgpass file or trust authentication method in pg_hba.conf. Since pg_rewind is also using libpq, it will work the same way.

Implemented possibility to configure Consul Service registration and check interval via environment variables (Alexander Kukushkin)

Registration of service in Consul was added in the 1.5.0, but so far it was only possible to turn it on via patroni.yaml.

Stability Improvements

Set archive_mode to off during the custom bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

We want to avoid archiving wals and history files until the cluster is fully functional. It really helps if the custom bootstrap involves pg_upgrade.

Apply five seconds backoff when loading global config on start (Alexander Kukushkin)

It helps to avoid hammering DCS when Patroni just starting up.

Reduce amount of error messages generated on shutdown (Alexander Kukushkin)

They were harmless but rather annoying and sometimes scary.

Explicitly secure rw perms for recovery.conf at creation time (Lucas Capistrant)

We don’t want anybody except patroni/postgres user reading this file, because it contains replication user and password.

Redirect HTTPServer exceptions to logger (Julien Riou)

By default, such exceptions were logged on standard output messing with regular logs.

Bug fixes

Removed stderr pipe to stdout on pg_ctl process (Cody Coons)

Inheriting stderr from the main Patroni process allows all Postgres logs to be seen along with all patroni logs. This is very useful in a container environment as Patroni and Postgres logs may be consumed using standard tools (docker logs, kubectl, etc). In addition to that, this change fixes a bug with Patroni not being able to catch postmaster pid when postgres writing some warnings into stderr.

Set Consul service check deregister timeout in Go time format (Pavel Kirillov)

Without explicitly mentioned time unit registration was failing.

Relax checks of standby_cluster cluster configuration (Dmitry Dolgov, Alexander Kukushkin)

It was accepting only strings as valid values and therefore it was not possible to specify the port as integer and create_replica_methods as a list.

Version 1.5.3

Released 2018-12-03

Compatibility and bugfix release.

Improve stability when running with python3 against zookeeper (Alexander Kukushkin)

Change of

loop_wait

was causing Patroni to disconnect from zookeeper and never reconnect back.

Fix broken compatibility with postgres 9.3 (Alexander Kukushkin)

When opening a replication connection we should specify replication=1, because 9.3 does not understand replication=’database’

Make sure we refresh Consul session at least once per HA loop and improve handling of consul sessions exceptions (Alexander Kukushkin)

Restart of local consul agent invalidates all sessions related to the node. Not calling session refresh on time and not doing proper handling of session errors was causing demote of the primary.

Version 1.5.2

Released 2018-11-26

Compatibility and bugfix release.

Compatibility with kazoo-2.6.0 (Alexander Kukushkin)

In order to make sure that requests are performed with an appropriate timeout, Patroni redefines create_connection method from python-kazoo module. The last release of kazoo slightly changed the way how create_connection method is called.

Fix Patroni crash when Consul cluster loses the leader (Alexander Kukushkin)

The crash was happening due to incorrect implementation of touch_member method, it should return boolean and not raise any exceptions.

Version 1.5.1

Released 2018-11-01

This version implements support of permanent replication slots, adds support of pgBackRest and fixes number of bugs.

New features

Permanent replication slots (Alexander Kukushkin)

Permanent replication slots are preserved on failover/switchover, that is, Patroni on the new primary will create configured replication slots right after doing promote. Slots could be configured with the help of

patronictl edit-config

. The initial configuration could be also done in the bootstrap.dcs.

Add pgbackrest support (Yogesh Sharma)

pgBackrest can restore in existing $PGDATA folder, this allows speedy restore as files which have not changed since last backup are skipped, to support this feature new parameter

keep_data

has been introduced. See replica creation method section for additional examples.

Bug fixes

A few bugfixes in the “standby cluster” workflow (Alexander Kukushkin)

Please see https://github.com/patroni/patroni/pull/823 for more details.

Fix REST API health check when cluster management is paused and DCS is not accessible (Alexander Kukushkin)

Regression was introduced in https://github.com/patroni/patroni/commit/90cf930036a9d5249265af15d2b787ec7517cf57

Version 1.5.0

Released 2018-09-20

This version enables Patroni HA cluster to operate in a standby mode, introduces experimental support for running on Windows, and provides a new configuration parameter to register PostgreSQL service in Consul.

New features

Standby cluster (Dmitry Dolgov)

One or more Patroni nodes can form a standby cluster that runs alongside the primary one (i.e. in another datacenter) and consists of standby nodes that replicate from the master in the primary cluster. All PostgreSQL nodes in the standby cluster are replicas; one of those replicas elects itself to replicate directly from the remote master, while the others replicate from it in a cascading manner. More detailed description of this feature and some configuration examples can be found at here.

Register Services in Consul (Pavel Kirillov, Alexander Kukushkin)

If

register_service

parameter in the consul configuration is enabled, the node will register a service with the name

scope

and the tag

master

,

replica

or

standby-leader

.

Experimental Windows support (Pavel Golub)

From now on it is possible to run Patroni on Windows, although Windows support is brand-new and hasn’t received as much real-world testing as its Linux counterpart. We welcome your feedback!

Improvements in patronictl

Add patronictl -k/–insecure flag and support for restapi cert (Wilfried Roset)

In the past if the REST API was protected by the self-signed certificates

patronictl

would fail to verify them. There was no way to disable that verification. It is now possible to configure

patronictl

to skip the certificate verification altogether or provide CA and client certificates in the ctl: section of configuration.

Exclude members with nofailover tag from patronictl switchover/failover output (Alexander Anikin)

Previously, those members were incorrectly proposed as candidates when performing interactive switchover or failover via patronictl.

Stability improvements

Avoid parsing non-key-value output lines of pg_controldata (Alexander Anikin)

Under certain circuimstances pg_controldata outputs lines without a colon character. That would trigger an error in Patroni code that parsed pg_controldata output, hiding the actual problem; often such lines are emitted in a warning shown by pg_controldata before the regular output, i.e. when the binary major version does not match the one of the PostgreSQL data directory.

Add member name to the error message during the leader election (Jan Mussler)

During the leader election, Patroni connects to all known members of the cluster and requests their status. Such status is written to the Patroni log and includes the name of the member. Previously, if the member was not accessible, the error message did not indicate its name, containing only the URL.

Immediately reserve the WAL position upon creation of the replication slot (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from 9.6,

pg_create_physical_replication_slot

function provides an additional boolean parameter

immediately_reserve

. When it is set to

false

, which is also the default, the slot doesn’t reserve the WAL position until it receives the first client connection, potentially losing some segments required by the client in a time window between the slot creation and the initial client connection.

Fix bug in strict synchronous replication (Alexander Kukushkin)

When running with

synchronous_mode_strict: true

, in some cases Patroni puts

*

into the

synchronous_standby_names

, changing the sync state for most of the replication connections to

potential

. Previously, Patroni couldn’t pick a synchronous candidate under such curcuimstances, as it only considered those with the state

async

.

Version 1.4.6

Released 2018-08-14

Bug fixes and stability improvements

This release fixes a critical issue with Patroni API /master endpoint returning 200 for the non-master node. This is a reporting issue, no actual split-brain, but under certain circumstances clients might be directed to the read-only node.

Reset is_leader status on demote (Alexander Kukushkin, Oleksii Kliukin)

Make sure demoted cluster member stops responding with code 200 on the /master API call.

Add new “cluster_unlocked” field to the API output (Dmitry Dolgov)

This field indicates whether the cluster has the master running. It can be used when it is not possible to query any other node but one of the replicas.

Version 1.4.5

Released 2018-08-03

New features

Improve logging when applying new postgres configuration (Don Seiler)

Patroni logs changed parameter names and values.

Python 3.7 compatibility (Christoph Berg)

async is a reserved keyword in python3.7

Set state to “stopped” in the DCS when a member is shut down (Tony Sorrentino)

This shows the member state as “stopped” in “patronictl list” command.

Improve the message logged when stale postmaster.pid matches a running process (Ants Aasma)

The previous one was beyond confusing.

Implement patronictl reload functionality (Don Seiler)

Before that it was only possible to reload configuration by either calling REST API or by sending SIGHUP signal to the Patroni process.

Take and apply some parameters from controldata when starting as a replica (Alexander Kukushkin)

The value of

max_connections

and some other parameters set in the global configuration may be lower than the one actually used by the primary; when this happens, the replica cannot start and should be fixed manually. Patroni takes care of that now by reading and applying the value from

pg_controldata

, starting postgres and setting

pending_restart

flag.

If set, use LD_LIBRARY_PATH when starting postgres (Chris Fraser)

When starting up Postgres, Patroni was passing along PATH, LC_ALL and LANG env vars if they are set. Now it is doing the same with LD_LIBRARY_PATH. It should help if somebody installed PostgreSQL to non-standard place.

Rename create_replica_method to create_replica_methods (Dmitry Dolgov)

To make it clear that it’s actually an array. The old name is still supported for backward compatibility.

Bug fixes and stability improvements

Fix condition for the replica start due to pg_rewind in paused state (Oleksii Kliukin)

Avoid starting the replica that had already executed pg_rewind before.

Respond 200 to the master health-check only if update_lock has been successful (Alexander Kukushkin)

Prevent Patroni from reporting itself a master on the former (demoted) master if DCS is partitioned.

Fix compatibility with the new consul module (Alexander Kukushkin)

Starting from v1.1.0 python-consul changed internal API and started using

list

instead of

dict

to pass query parameters.

Catch exceptions from Patroni REST API thread during shutdown (Alexander Kukushkin)

Those uncaught exceptions kept PostgreSQL running at shutdown.

Do crash recovery only when Postgres runs as the master (Alexander Kukushkin)

Require

pg_controldata

to report ‘in production’ or ‘shutting down’ or ‘in crash recovery’. In all other cases no crash recovery is necessary.

Improve handling of configuration errors (Henning Jacobs, Alexander Kukushkin)

It is possible to change a lot of parameters in runtime (including

restapi.listen

) by updating Patroni config file and sending SIGHUP to Patroni process. This fix eliminates obscure exceptions from the ‘restapi’ thread when some of the parameters receive invalid values.

Version 1.4.4

Released 2018-05-22

Stability improvements

Fix race condition in poll_failover_result (Alexander Kukushkin)

It didn’t affect directly neither failover nor switchover, but in some rare cases it was reporting success too early, when the former leader released the lock, producing a ‘Failed over to “None”’ instead of ‘Failed over to “desired-node”’ message.

Treat Postgres parameter names as case insensitive (Alexander Kukushkin)

Most of the Postgres parameters have snake_case names, but there are three exceptions from this rule: DateStyle, IntervalStyle and TimeZone. Postgres accepts those parameters when written in a different case (e.g. timezone = ‘some/tzn’); however, Patroni was unable to find case-insensitive matches of those parameter names in pg_settings and ignored such parameters as a result.

Abort start if attaching to running postgres and cluster not initialized (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni can attach itself to an already running Postgres instance. It is imperative to start running Patroni on the master node before getting to the replicas.

Fix behavior of patronictl scaffold (Alexander Kukushkin)

Pass dict object to touch_member instead of json encoded string, DCS implementation will take care of encoding it.

Don’t demote master if failed to update leader key in pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

During maintenance a DCS may start failing write requests while continuing to responds to read ones. In that case, Patroni used to put the Postgres master node to a read-only mode after failing to update the leader lock in DCS.

Sync replication slots when Patroni notices a new postmaster process (Alexander Kukushkin)

If Postgres has been restarted, Patroni has to make sure that list of replication slots matches its expectations.

Verify sysid and sync replication slots after coming out of pause (Alexander Kukushkin)

During the

maintenance

mode it may happen that data directory was completely rewritten and therefore we have to make sure that

Database system identifier

still belongs to our cluster and replication slots are in sync with Patroni expectations.

Fix a possible failure to start not running Postgres on a data directory with postmaster lock file present (Alexander Kukushkin)

Detect reuse of PID from the postmaster lock file. More likely to hit such problem if you run Patroni and Postgres in the docker container.

Improve protection of DCS being accidentally wiped (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni has a lot of logic in place to prevent failover in such case; it can also restore all keys back; however, until this change an accidental removal of /config key was switching off pause mode for 1 cycle of HA loop.

Do not exit when encountering invalid system ID (Oleksii Kliukin)

Do not exit when the cluster system ID is empty or the one that doesn’t pass the validation check. In that case, the cluster most likely needs a reinit; mention it in the result message. Avoid terminating Patroni, as otherwise reinit cannot happen.

Compatibility with Kubernetes 1.10+

Added check for empty subsets (Cody Coons)

Kubernetes 1.10.0+ started returning

Endpoints.subsets

set to

None

instead of

[]

.

Bootstrap improvements

Make deleting recovery.conf optional (Brad Nicholson)

If

bootstrap.<custom_bootstrap_method_name>.keep_existing_recovery_conf

is defined and set to True, Patroni will not remove the existing recovery.conf file. This is useful when bootstrapping from a backup with tools like pgBackRest that generate the appropriate

recovery.conf

for you.

Allow options to the basebackup built-in method (Oleksii Kliukin)

It is now possible to supply options to the built-in basebackup method by defining the

basebackup

section in the configuration, similar to how those are defined for custom replica creation methods. The difference is in the format accepted by the

basebackup

section: since pg_basebackup accepts both

–key=value

and

–key

options, the contents of the section could be either a dictionary of key-value pairs, or a list of either one-element dictionaries or just keys (for the options that don’t accept values). See replica creation method section for additional examples.

Version 1.4.3

Released 2018-03-05

Improvements in logging

Make log level configurable from environment variables (Andy Newton, Keyvan Hedayati)

PATRONI_LOGLEVEL

- sets the general logging level

PATRONI_REQUESTS_LOGLEVEL

- sets the logging level for all HTTP requests e.g. Kubernetes API calls See

the docs for Python logging <https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#levels>

to get the names of possible log levels

Stability improvements and bug fixes

Don’t rediscover etcd cluster topology when watch timed out (Alexander Kukushkin)

If we have only one host in etcd configuration and exactly this host is not accessible, Patroni was starting discovery of cluster topology and never succeeding. Instead it should just switch to the next available node.

Write content of bootstrap.pg_hba into a pg_hba.conf after custom bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

Now it behaves similarly to the usual bootstrap with

initdb

Single user mode was waiting for user input and never finish (Alexander Kukushkin)

Regression was introduced in https://github.com/patroni/patroni/pull/576

Version 1.4.2

Released 2018-01-30

Improvements in patronictl

Rename scheduled failover to scheduled switchover (Alexander Kukushkin)

Failover and switchover functions were separated in version 1.4, but

patronictl list

was still reporting

Scheduled failover

instead of

Scheduled switchover

.

Show information about pending restarts (Alexander Kukushkin)

In order to apply some configuration changes sometimes it is necessary to restart postgres. Patroni was already giving a hint about that in the REST API and when writing node status into DCS, but there were no easy way to display it.

Make show-config to work with cluster_name from config file (Alexander Kukushkin)

It works similar to the

patronictl edit-config

Stability improvements

Avoid calling pg_controldata during bootstrap (Alexander Kukushkin)

During initdb or custom bootstrap there is a time window when pgdata is not empty but pg_controldata has not been written yet. In such case pg_controldata call was failing with error messages.

Handle exceptions raised from psutil (Alexander Kukushkin)

cmdline is read and parsed every time when

cmdline()

method is called. It could happen that the process being examined has already disappeared, in that case

NoSuchProcess

is raised.

Kubernetes support improvements

Don’t swallow errors from k8s API (Alexander Kukushkin)

A call to Kubernetes API could fail for a different number of reasons. In some cases such call should be retried, in some other cases we should log the error message and the exception stack trace. The change here will help debug Kubernetes permission issues.

Update Kubernetes example Dockerfile to install Patroni from the master branch (Maciej Szulik)

Before that it was using

feature/k8s

, which became outdated.

Add proper RBAC to run patroni on k8s (Maciej Szulik)

Add the Service account that is assigned to the pods of the cluster, the role that holds only the necessary permissions, and the rolebinding that connects the Service account and the Role.

Version 1.4.1

Released 2018-01-17

Fixes in patronictl

Don’t show current leader in suggested list of members to failover to. (Alexander Kukushkin)

patronictl failover could still work when there is leader in the cluster and it should be excluded from the list of member where it is possible to failover to.

Make patronictl switchover compatible with the old Patroni api (Alexander Kukushkin)

In case if POST /switchover REST API call has failed with status code 501 it will do it once again, but to /failover endpoint.

Version 1.4

Released 2018-01-10

This version adds support for using Kubernetes as a DCS, allowing to run Patroni as a cloud-native agent in Kubernetes without any additional deployments of Etcd, Zookeeper or Consul.

Upgrade notice

Installing Patroni via pip will no longer bring in dependencies for (such as libraries for Etcd, Zookeper, Consul or Kubernetes, or support for AWS). In order to enable them one need to list them in pip install command explicitly, for instance

pip install patroni[etcd,kubernetes]

.

Kubernetes support

Implement Kubernetes-based DCS. The endpoints meta-data is used in order to store the configuration and the leader key. The meta-data field inside the pods definition is used to store the member-related data. In addition to using Endpoints, Patroni supports ConfigMaps. You can find more information about this feature in the Kubernetes chapter of the documentation

Stability improvements

Factor out postmaster process into a separate object (Ants Aasma)

This object identifies a running postmaster process via pid and start time and simplifies detection (and resolution) of situations when the postmaster was restarted behind our back or when postgres directory disappeared from the file system.

Minimize the amount of SELECT’s issued by Patroni on every loop of HA cycle (Alexander Kukushkin)

On every iteration of HA loop Patroni needs to know recovery status and absolute wal position. From now on Patroni will run only single SELECT to get this information instead of two on the replica and three on the master.

Remove leader key on shutdown only when we have the lock (Ants Aasma)

Unconditional removal was generating unnecessary and misleading exceptions.

Improvements in patronictl

Add version command to patronictl (Ants Aasma)

It will show the version of installed Patroni and versions of running Patroni instances (if the cluster name is specified).

Make optional specifying cluster_name argument for some of patronictl commands (Alexander Kukushkin, Ants Aasma)

It will work if patronictl is using usual Patroni configuration file with the scope defined.

Show information about scheduled switchover and maintenance mode (Alexander Kukushkin)

Before that it was possible to get this information only from Patroni logs or directly from DCS.

Improve patronictl reinit (Alexander Kukushkin)

Sometimes patronictl reinit refused to proceed when Patroni was busy with other actions, namely trying to start postgres.

patronictl

didn’t provide any commands to cancel such long running actions and the only (dangerous) workarond was removing a data directory manually. The new implementation of

reinit

forcefully cancels other long-running actions before proceeding with reinit.

Implement --wait flag in patronictl pause and patronictl resume (Alexander Kukushkin)

It will make patronictl wait until the requested action is acknowledged by all nodes in the cluster. Such behaviour is achieved by exposing the pause flag for every node in DCS and via the REST API.

Rename patronictl failover into patronictl switchover (Alexander Kukushkin)

The previous failover was actually only capable of doing a switchover; it refused to proceed in a cluster without the leader.

Alter the behavior of patronictl failover (Alexander Kukushkin)

It will work even if there is no leader, but in that case you will have to explicitly specify a node which should become the new leader.

Expose information about timeline and history

Expose current timeline in DCS and via API (Alexander Kukushkin)

Store information about the current timeline for each member of the cluster. This information is accessible via the API and is stored in the DCS

Store promotion history in the /history key in DCS (Alexander Kukushkin)

In addition, store the timeline history enriched with the timestamp of the corresponding promotion in the /history key in DCS and update it with each promote.

Add endpoints for getting synchronous and asynchronous replicas

Add new /sync and /async endpoints (Alexander Kukushkin, Oleksii Kliukin)

Those endpoints (also accessible as /synchronous and /asynchronous) return 200 only for synchronous and asynchronous replicas correspondingly (excluding those marked as

noloadbalance

).

Allow multiple hosts for Etcd

Add a new

hosts

parameter to Etcd configuration (Alexander Kukushkin)

This parameter should contain the initial list of hosts that will be used to discover and populate the list of the running etcd cluster members. If for some reason during work this list of discovered hosts is exhausted (no available hosts from that list), Patroni will return to the initial list from the

hosts

parameter.

Version 1.3.6

Released 2017-11-10

Stability improvements

Verify process start time when checking if postgres is running. (Ants Aasma)

After a crash that doesn’t clean up postmaster.pid there could be a new process with the same pid, resulting in a false positive for is_running(), which will lead to all kinds of bad behavior.

Shutdown postgresql before bootstrap when we lost data directory (ainlolcat)

When data directory on the master is forcefully removed, postgres process can still stay alive for some time and prevent the replica created in place of that former master from starting or replicating. The fix makes Patroni cache the postmaster pid and its start time and let it terminate the old postmaster in case it is still running after the corresponding data directory has been removed.

Perform crash recovery in a single user mode if postgres master dies (Alexander Kukushkin)

It is unsafe to start immediately as a standby and not possible to run pg_rewind if postgres hasn’t been shut down cleanly. The single user crash recovery only kicks in if pg_rewind is enabled or there is no master at the moment.

Consul improvements

Make it possible to provide datacenter configuration for Consul (Vilius Okockis, Alexander Kukushkin)

Before that Patroni was always communicating with datacenter of the host it runs on.

Always send a token in X-Consul-Token http header (Alexander Kukushkin)

If consul.token is defined in Patroni configuration, we will always send it in the ‘X-Consul-Token’ http header. python-consul module tries to be “consistent” with Consul REST API, which doesn’t accept token as a query parameter for session API [https://www.consul.io/api/session.html], but it still works with ‘X-Consul-Token’ header.

Adjust session TTL if supplied value is smaller than the minimum possible (Stas Fomin, Alexander Kukushkin)

It could happen that the TTL provided in the Patroni configuration is smaller than the minimum one supported by Consul. In that case, Consul agent fails to create a new session. Without a session Patroni cannot create member and leader keys in the Consul KV store, resulting in an unhealthy cluster.

Other improvements

Define custom log format via environment variable PATRONI_LOGFORMAT (Stas Fomin)

Allow disabling timestamps and other similar fields in Patroni logs if they are already added by the system logger (usually when Patroni runs as a service).

Version 1.3.5

Released 2017-10-12

Bugfix

Set role to ‘uninitialized’ if data directory was removed (Alexander Kukushkin)

If the node was running as a master it was preventing from failover.

Stability improvement

Try to run postmaster in a single-user mode if we tried and failed to start postgres (Alexander Kukushkin)

Usually such problem happens when node running as a master was terminated and timelines were diverged. If recovery.conf has restore_command defined, there are really high chances that postgres will abort startup and leave controldata unchanged. It makes impossible to use pg_rewind, which requires a clean shutdown.

Consul improvements

Make it possible to specify health checks when creating session (Alexander Kukushkin)

If not specified, Consul will use “serfHealth”. From one side it allows fast detection of isolated master, but from another side it makes it impossible for Patroni to tolerate short network lags.

Bugfix

Fix watchdog on Python 3 (Ants Aasma)

A misunderstanding of the ioctl() call interface. If mutable=False then fcntl.ioctl() actually returns the arg buffer back. This accidentally worked on Python2 because int and str comparison did not return an error. Error reporting is actually done by raising IOError on Python2 and OSError on Python3.

Version 1.3.4

Released 2017-09-08

Different Consul improvements

Pass the consul token as a header (Andrew Colin Kissa)

Headers are now the preferred way to pass the token to the consul API [https://www.consul.io/api/index.html#authentication].

Advanced configuration for Consul (Alexander Kukushkin)

possibility to specify scheme, token, client and ca certificates details.

compatibility with python-consul-0.7.1 and above (Alexander Kukushkin)

new python-consul module has changed signature of some methods

“Could not take out TTL lock” message was never logged (Alexander Kukushkin)

Not a critical bug, but lack of proper logging complicates investigation in case of problems.

Quote synchronous_standby_names using quote_ident

When writing synchronous_standby_names into the postgresql.conf its value must be quoted (Alexander Kukushkin)

If it is not quoted properly, PostgreSQL will effectively disable synchronous replication and continue to work.

Different bugfixes around pause state, mostly related to watchdog (Alexander Kukushkin)

Do not send keepalives if watchdog is not active

Avoid activating watchdog in a pause mode

Set correct postgres state in pause mode

Do not try to run queries from API if postgres is stopped

Version 1.3.3

Released 2017-08-04

Bugfixes

synchronous replication was disabled shortly after promotion even when synchronous_mode_strict was turned on (Alexander Kukushkin)

create empty pg_ident.conf file if it is missing after restoring from the backup (Alexander Kukushkin)

open access in pg_hba.conf to all databases, not only postgres (Franco Bellagamba)

Version 1.3.2

Released 2017-07-31

Bugfix

patronictl edit-config didn’t work with ZooKeeper (Alexander Kukushkin)

Version 1.3.1

Released 2017-07-28

Bugfix

failover via API was broken due to change in _MemberStatus (Alexander Kukushkin)

Version 1.3

Released 2017-07-27

Version 1.3 adds custom bootstrap possibility, significantly improves support for pg_rewind, enhances the synchronous mode support, adds configuration editing to patronictl and implements watchdog support on Linux. In addition, this is the first version to work correctly with PostgreSQL 10.

Upgrade notice

There are no known compatibility issues with the new version of Patroni. Configuration from version 1.2 should work without any changes. It is possible to upgrade by installing new packages and either restarting Patroni (will cause PostgreSQL restart), or by putting Patroni into a pause mode first and then restarting Patroni on all nodes in the cluster (Patroni in a pause mode will not attempt to stop/start PostgreSQL), resuming from the pause mode at the end.

Custom bootstrap

Make the process of bootstrapping the cluster configurable (Alexander Kukushkin)

Allow custom bootstrap scripts instead of initdb when initializing the very first node in the cluster. The bootstrap command receives the name of the cluster and the path to the data directory. The resulting cluster can be configured to perform recovery, making it possible to bootstrap from a backup and do point in time recovery. Refer to the documentation page for more detailed description of this feature.

Smarter pg_rewind support

Decide on whether to run pg_rewind by looking at the timeline differences from the current master (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, Patroni had a fixed set of conditions to trigger pg_rewind, namely when starting a former master, when doing a switchover to the designated node for every other node in the cluster or when there is a replica with the nofailover tag. All those cases have in common a chance that some replica may be ahead of the new master. In some cases, pg_rewind did nothing, in some other ones it was not running when necessary. Instead of relying on this limited list of rules make Patroni compare the master and the replica WAL positions (using the streaming replication protocol) in order to reliably decide if rewind is necessary for the replica.

Synchronous replication mode strict

Enhance synchronous replication support by adding the strict mode (James Sewell, Alexander Kukushkin)

Normally, when synchronous_mode is enabled and there are no replicas attached to the master, Patroni will disable synchronous replication in order to keep the master available for writes. The synchronous_mode_strict option changes that, when it is set Patroni will not disable the synchronous replication in a lack of replicas, effectively blocking all clients writing data to the master. In addition to the synchronous mode guarantee of preventing any data loss due to automatic failover, the strict mode ensures that each write is either durably stored on two nodes or not happening altogether if there is only one node in the cluster.

Configuration editing with patronictl

Add configuration editing to patronictl (Ants Aasma, Alexander Kukushkin)

Add the ability to patronictl of editing dynamic cluster configuration stored in DCS. Support either specifying the parameter/values from the command-line, invoking the $EDITOR, or applying configuration from the yaml file.

Linux watchdog support

Implement watchdog support for Linux (Ants Aasma)

Support Linux software watchdog in order to reboot the node where Patroni is not running or not responding (e.g because of the high load) The Linux software watchdog reboots the non-responsive node. It is possible to configure the watchdog device to use (

/dev/watchdog

by default) and the mode (on, automatic, off) from the watchdog section of the Patroni configuration. You can get more information from the watchdog documentation.

Add support for PostgreSQL 10

Patroni is compatible with all beta versions of PostgreSQL 10 released so far and we expect it to be compatible with the PostgreSQL 10 when it will be released.

PostgreSQL-related minor improvements

Define pg_hba.conf via the Patroni configuration file or the dynamic configuration in DCS (Alexander Kukushkin)

Allow to define the contents of pg_hba.conf in the pg_hba sub-section of the postgresql section of the configuration. This simplifies managing pg_hba.conf on multiple nodes, as one needs to define it only ones in DCS instead of logging to every node, changing it manually and reload the configuration.

When defined, the contents of this section will replace the current pg_hba.conf completely. Patroni ignores it if hba_file PostgreSQL parameter is set.

Support connecting via a UNIX socket to the local PostgreSQL cluster (Alexander Kukushkin)

Add the use_unix_socket option to the postgresql section of Patroni configuration. When set to true and the PostgreSQL unix_socket_directories option is not empty, enables Patroni to use the first value from it to connect to the local PostgreSQL cluster. If unix_socket_directories is not defined, Patroni will assume its default value and omit the host parameter in the PostgreSQL connection string altogether.

Support change of superuser and replication credentials on reload (Alexander Kukushkin)

Support storing of configuration files outside of PostgreSQL data directory (@jouir)

Add the new configuration postgresql configuration directive config_dir. It defaults to the data directory and must be writable by Patroni.

Bug fixes and stability improvements

Handle EtcdEventIndexCleared and EtcdWatcherCleared exceptions (Alexander Kukushkin)

Faster recovery when the watch operation is ended by Etcd by avoiding useless retries.

Remove error spinning on Etcd failure and reduce log spam (Ants Aasma)

Avoid immediate retrying and emitting stack traces in the log on the second and subsequent Etcd connection failures.

Export locale variables when forking PostgreSQL processes (Oleksii Kliukin)

Avoid the

postmaster became multithreaded during startup

fatal error on non-English locales for PostgreSQL built with NLS.

Extra checks when dropping the replication slot (Alexander Kukushkin)

In some cases Patroni is prevented from dropping the replication slot by the WAL sender.

Truncate the replication slot name to 63 (NAMEDATALEN - 1) characters to comply with PostgreSQL naming rules (Nick Scott)

Fix a race condition resulting in extra connections being opened to the PostgreSQL cluster from Patroni (Alexander Kukushkin)

Release the leader key when the node restarts with an empty data directory (Alex Kerney)

Set asynchronous executor busy when running bootstrap without a leader (Alexander Kukushkin)

Failure to do so could have resulted in errors stating the node belonged to a different cluster, as Patroni proceeded with the normal business while being bootstrapped by a bootstrap method that doesn’t require a leader to be present in the cluster.

Improve WAL-E replica creation method (Joar Wandborg, Alexander Kukushkin).

Use csv.DictReader when parsing WAL-E base backup, accepting ISO dates with space-delimited date and time.

Support fetching current WAL position from the replica to estimate the amount of WAL to restore. Previously, the code used to call system information functions that were available only on the master node.

Version 1.2

Released 2016-12-13

This version introduces significant improvements over the handling of synchronous replication, makes the startup process and failover more reliable, adds PostgreSQL 9.6 support and fixes plenty of bugs. In addition, the documentation, including these release notes, has been moved to https://patroni.readthedocs.io.

Synchronous replication

Add synchronous replication support. (Ants Aasma)

Adds a new configuration variable synchronous_mode. When enabled, Patroni will manage synchronous_standby_names to enable synchronous replication whenever there are healthy standbys available. When synchronous mode is enabled, Patroni will automatically fail over only to a standby that was synchronously replicating at the time of the master failure. This effectively means that no user visible transaction gets lost in such a case. See the feature documentation for the detailed description and implementation details.

Reliability improvements

Do not try to update the leader position stored in the leader optime key when PostgreSQL is not 100% healthy. Demote immediately when the update of the leader key failed. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Exclude unhealthy nodes from the list of targets to clone the new replica from. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Implement retry and timeout strategy for Consul similar to how it is done for Etcd. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make --dcs and --config-file apply to all options in patronictl. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Write all postgres parameters into postgresql.conf. (Alexander Kukushkin)

It allows starting PostgreSQL configured by Patroni with just pg_ctl.

Avoid exceptions when there are no users in the config. (Kirill Pushkin)

Allow pausing an unhealthy cluster. Before this fix, patronictl would bail out if the node it tries to execute pause on is unhealthy. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Improve the leader watch functionality. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously the replicas were always watching the leader key (sleeping until the timeout or the leader key changes). With this change, they only watch when the replica’s PostgreSQL is in the running state and not when it is stopped/starting or restarting PostgreSQL.

Avoid running into race conditions when handling SIGCHILD as a PID 1. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously a race condition could occur when running inside the Docker containers, since the same process inside Patroni both spawned new processes and handled SIGCHILD from them. This change uses fork/execs for Patroni and leaves the original PID 1 process responsible for handling signals from children.

Fix WAL-E restore. (Oleksii Kliukin)

Previously WAL-E restore used the no_master flag to avoid consulting with the master altogether, making Patroni always choose restoring from WAL over the pg_basebackup. This change reverts it to the original meaning of no_master, namely Patroni WAL-E restore may be selected as a replication method if the master is not running. The latter is checked by examining the connection string passed to the method. In addition, it makes the retry mechanism more robust and handles other minutia.

Implement asynchronous DNS resolver cache. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid failing when DNS is temporary unavailable (for instance, due to an excessive traffic received by the node).

Implement starting state and master start timeout. (Ants Aasma, Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously pg_ctl waited for a timeout and then happily trodded on considering PostgreSQL to be running. This caused PostgreSQL to show up in listings as running when it was actually not and caused a race condition that resulted in either a failover, or a crash recovery, or a crash recovery interrupted by failover and a missed rewind. This change adds a master_start_timeout parameter and introduces a new state for the main HA loop: starting. When master_start_timeout is 0 we will failover immediately when the master crashes as soon as there is a failover candidate. Otherwise, Patroni will wait after attempting to start PostgreSQL on the master for the duration of the timeout; when it expires, it will failover if possible. Manual failover requests will be honored during the crash of the master even before the timeout expiration.

Introduce the timeout parameter to the restart API endpoint and patronictl. When it is set and restart takes longer than the timeout, PostgreSQL is considered unhealthy and the other nodes becomes eligible to take the leader lock.

Fix pg_rewind behavior in a pause mode. (Ants Aasma)

Avoid unnecessary restart in a pause mode when Patroni thinks it needs to rewind but rewind is not possible (i.e. pg_rewind is not present). Fallback to default libpq values for the superuser (default OS user) if superuser authentication is missing from the pg_rewind related Patroni configuration section.

Serialize callback execution. Kill the previous callback of the same type when the new one is about to run. Fix the issue of spawning zombie processes when running callbacks. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid promoting a former master when the leader key is set in DCS but update to this leader key fails. (Alexander Kukushkin)

This avoids the issue of a current master continuing to keep its role when it is partitioned together with the minority of nodes in Etcd and other DCSs that allow “inconsistent reads”.

Miscellaneous

Add post_init configuration option on bootstrap. (Alejandro Martínez)

Patroni will call the script argument of this option right after running initdb and starting up PostgreSQL for a new cluster. The script receives a connection URL with superuser and sets PGPASSFILE to point to the .pgpass file containing the password. If the script fails, Patroni initialization fails as well. It is useful for adding new users or creating extensions in the new cluster.

Implement PostgreSQL 9.6 support. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Use wal_level = replica as a synonym for hot_standby, avoiding pending_restart flag when it changes from one to another. (Alexander Kukushkin)

Documentation improvements

Add a Patroni main loop workflow diagram [https://raw.githubusercontent.com/patroni/patroni/master/docs/ha_loop_diagram.png]. (Alejandro Martínez, Alexander Kukushkin)

Improve README, adding the Helm chart and links to release notes. (Lauri Apple)

Move Patroni documentation to Read the Docs. The up-to-date documentation is available at https://patroni.readthedocs.io. (Oleksii Kliukin)

Makes the documentation easily viewable from different devices (including smartphones) and searchable.

Move the package to the semantic versioning. (Oleksii Kliukin)

Patroni will follow the major.minor.patch version schema to avoid releasing the new minor version on small but critical bugfixes. We will only publish the release notes for the minor version, which will include all patches.

Version 1.1

Released 2016-09-07

This release improves management of Patroni cluster by bring in pause mode, improves maintenance with scheduled and conditional restarts, makes Patroni interaction with Etcd or Zookeeper more resilient and greatly enhances patronictl.

Upgrade notice

When upgrading from releases below 1.0 read about changing of credentials and configuration format at 1.0 release notes.

Pause mode

Introduce pause mode to temporary detach Patroni from managing PostgreSQL instance (Murat Kabilov, Alexander Kukushkin, Oleksii Kliukin).

Previously, one had to send SIGKILL signal to Patroni to stop it without terminating PostgreSQL. The new pause mode detaches Patroni from PostgreSQL cluster-wide without terminating Patroni. It is similar to the maintenance mode in Pacemaker. Patroni is still responsible for updating member and leader keys in DCS, but it will not start, stop or restart PostgreSQL server in the process. There are a few exceptions, for instance, manual failovers, reinitializes and restarts are still allowed. You can read a detailed description of this feature.

In addition, patronictl supports new pause and resume commands to toggle the pause mode.

Scheduled and conditional restarts

Add conditions to the restart API command (Oleksii Kliukin)

This change enhances Patroni restarts by adding a couple of conditions that can be verified in order to do the restart. Among the conditions are restarting when PostgreSQL role is either a master or a replica, checking the PostgreSQL version number or restarting only when restart is necessary in order to apply configuration changes.

Add scheduled restarts (Oleksii Kliukin)

It is now possible to schedule a restart in the future. Only one scheduled restart per node is supported. It is possible to clear the scheduled restart if it is not needed anymore. A combination of scheduled and conditional restarts is supported, making it possible, for instance, to scheduled minor PostgreSQL upgrades in the night, restarting only the instances that are running the outdated minor version without adding postgres-specific logic to administration scripts.

Add support for conditional and scheduled restarts to patronictl (Murat Kabilov).

patronictl restart supports several new options. There is also patronictl flush command to clean the scheduled actions.

Robust DCS interaction

Set Kazoo timeouts depending on the loop_wait (Alexander Kukushkin)

Originally, ping_timeout and connect_timeout values were calculated from the negotiated session timeout. Patroni loop_wait was not taken into account. As a result, a single retry could take more time than the session timeout, forcing Patroni to release the lock and demote.

This change set ping and connect timeout to half of the value of loop_wait, speeding up detection of connection issues and leaving enough time to retry the connection attempt before losing the lock.

Update Etcd topology only after original request succeed (Alexander Kukushkin)

Postpone updating the Etcd topology known to the client until after the original request. When retrieving the cluster topology, implement the retry timeouts depending on the known number of nodes in the Etcd cluster. This makes our client prefer to get the results of the request to having the up-to-date list of nodes.

Both changes make Patroni connections to DCS more robust in the face of network issues.

Patronictl, monitoring and configuration

Return information about streaming replicas via the API (Feike Steenbergen)

Previously, there was no reliable way to query Patroni about PostgreSQL instances that fail to stream changes (for instance, due to connection issues). This change exposes the contents of pg_stat_replication via the /patroni endpoint.

Add patronictl scaffold command (Oleksii Kliukin)

Add a command to create cluster structure in Etcd. The cluster is created with user-specified sysid and leader, and both leader and member keys are made persistent. This command is useful to create so-called master-less configurations, where Patroni cluster consisting of only replicas replicate from the external master node that is unaware of Patroni. Subsequently, one may remove the leader key, promoting one of the Patroni nodes and replacing the original master with the Patroni-based HA cluster.

Add configuration option bin_dir to locate PostgreSQL binaries (Ants Aasma)

It is useful to be able to specify the location of PostgreSQL binaries explicitly when Linux distros that support installing multiple PostgreSQL versions at the same time.

Allow configuration file path to be overridden using custom_conf of (Alejandro Martínez)

Allows for custom configuration file paths, which will be unmanaged by Patroni, details.

Bug fixes and code improvements

Make Patroni compatible with new version schema in PostgreSQL 10 and above (Feike Steenbergen)

Make sure that Patroni understand 2-digits version numbers when doing conditional restarts based on the PostgreSQL version.

Use pkgutil to find DCS modules (Alexander Kukushkin)

Use the dedicated python module instead of traversing directories manually in order to find DCS modules.

Always call on_start callback when starting Patroni (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, Patroni did not call any callbacks when attaching to the already running node with the correct role. Since callbacks are often used to route client connections that could result in the failure to register the running node in the connection routing scheme. With this fix, Patroni calls on_start callback even when attaching to the already running node.

Do not drop active replication slots (Murat Kabilov, Oleksii Kliukin)

Avoid dropping active physical replication slots on master. PostgreSQL cannot drop such slots anyway. This change makes possible to run non-Patroni managed replicas/consumers on the master.

Close Patroni connections during start of the PostgreSQL instance (Alexander Kukushkin)

Forces Patroni to close all former connections when PostgreSQL node is started. Avoids the trap of reusing former connections if postmaster was killed with SIGKILL.

Replace invalid characters when constructing slot names from member names (Ants Aasma)

Make sure that standby names that do not comply with the slot naming rules don’t cause the slot creation and standby startup to fail. Replace the dashes in the slot names with underscores and all other characters not allowed in slot names with their unicode codepoints.

Version 1.0

Released 2016-07-05

This release introduces the global dynamic configuration that allows dynamic changes of the PostgreSQL and Patroni configuration parameters for the entire HA cluster. It also delivers numerous bugfixes.

Upgrade notice

When upgrading from v0.90 or below, always upgrade all replicas before the master. Since we don’t store replication credentials in DCS anymore, an old replica won’t be able to connect to the new master.

Dynamic Configuration

Implement the dynamic global configuration (Alexander Kukushkin)

Introduce new REST API endpoint /config to provide PostgreSQL and Patroni configuration parameters that should be set globally for the entire HA cluster (master and all the replicas). Those parameters are set in DCS and in many cases can be applied without disrupting PostgreSQL or Patroni. Patroni sets a special flag called “pending restart” visible via the API when some of the values require the PostgreSQL restart. In that case, restart should be issued manually via the API.

Patroni SIGHUP or POST to /reload will make it re-read the configuration file.

See the Patroni configuration for the details on which parameters can be changed and the order of processing difference configuration sources.

The configuration file format has changed since the v0.90. Patroni is still compatible with the old configuration files, but in order to take advantage of the bootstrap parameters one needs to change it. Users are encourage to update them by referring to the dynamic configuration documentation page.

More flexible configuration*

Make postgresql configuration and database name Patroni connects to configurable (Misja Hoebe)

Introduce

database

and

config_base_name

configuration parameters. Among others, it makes possible to run Patroni with PipelineDB and other PostgreSQL forks.

Implement possibility to configure some Patroni configuration parameters via environment (Alexander Kukushkin)

Those include the scope, the node name and the namespace, as well as the secrets and makes it easier to run Patroni in a dynamic environment, i.e. Kubernetes Please, refer to the supported environment variables for further details.

Update the built-in Patroni docker container to take advantage of environment-based configuration (Feike Steenbergen).

Add Zookeeper support to Patroni docker image (Alexander Kukushkin)

Split the Zookeeper and Exhibitor configuration options (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make patronictl reuse the code from Patroni to read configuration (Alexander Kukushkin)

This allows patronictl to take advantage of environment-based configuration.

Set application name to node name in primary_conninfo (Alexander Kukushkin)

This simplifies identification and configuration of synchronous replication for a given node.

Stability, security and usability improvements

Reset sysid and do not call pg_controldata when restore of backup in progress (Alexander Kukushkin)

This change reduces the amount of noise generated by Patroni API health checks during the lengthy initialization of this node from the backup.

Fix a bunch of pg_rewind corner-cases (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoid running pg_rewind if the source cluster is not the master.

In addition, avoid removing the data directory on an unsuccessful rewind, unless the new parameter remove_data_directory_on_rewind_failure is set to true. By default it is false.

Remove passwords from the replication connection string in DCS (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, Patroni always used the replication credentials from the Postgres URL in DCS. That is now changed to take the credentials from the patroni configuration. The secrets (replication username and password) and no longer exposed in DCS.

Fix the asynchronous machinery around the demote call (Alexander Kukushkin)

Demote now runs totally asynchronously without blocking the DCS interactions.

Make patronictl always send the authorization header if it is configured (Alexander Kukushkin)

This allows patronictl to issue “protected” requests, i.e. restart or reinitialize, when Patroni is configured to require authorization on those.

Handle the SystemExit exception correctly (Alexander Kukushkin)

Avoids the issues of Patroni not stopping properly when receiving the SIGTERM

Sample haproxy templates for confd (Alexander Kukushkin)

Generates and dynamically changes haproxy configuration from the patroni state in the DCS using confide

Improve and restructure the documentation to make it more friendly to the new users (Lauri Apple)

API must report role=master during pg_ctl stop (Alexander Kukushkin)

Makes the callback calls more reliable, particularly in the cluster stop case. In addition, introduce the

pg_ctl_timeout

option to set the timeout for the start, stop and restart calls via the

pg_ctl

.

Fix the retry logic in etcd (Alexander Kukushkin)

Make retries more predictable and robust.

Make Zookeeper code more resilient against short network hiccups (Alexander Kukushkin)

Reduce the connection timeouts to make Zookeeper connection attempts more frequent.

Version 0.90

Released 2016-04-27

This releases adds support for Consul, includes a new noloadbalance tag, changes the behavior of the clonefrom tag, improves pg_rewind handling and improves patronictl control program.

Consul support

Implement Consul support (Alexander Kukushkin)

Patroni runs against Consul, in addition to Etcd and Zookeeper. the connection parameters can be configured in the YAML file.

New and improved tags

Implement noloadbalance tag (Alexander Kukushkin)

This tag makes Patroni always return that the replica is not available to the load balancer.

Change the implementation of the clonefrom tag (Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, a node name had to be supplied to the clonefrom, forcing a tagged replica to clone from the specific node. The new implementation makes clonefrom a boolean tag: if it is set to true, the replica becomes a candidate for other replicas to clone from it. When multiple candidates are present, the replicas picks one randomly.

Stability and security improvements

Numerous reliability improvements (Alexander Kukushkin)

Removes some spurious error messages, improves the stability of the failover, addresses some corner cases with reading data from DCS, shutdown, demote and reattaching of the former leader.

Improve systems script to avoid killing Patroni children on stop (Jan Keirse, Alexander Kukushkin)

Previously, when stopping Patroni, systemd also sent a signal to PostgreSQL. Since Patroni also tried to stop PostgreSQL by itself, it resulted in sending to different shutdown requests (the smart shutdown, followed by the fast shutdown). That resulted in replicas disconnecting too early and a former master not being able to rejoin after demote. Fix by Jan with prior research by Alexander.

Eliminate some cases where the former master was unable to call pg_rewind before rejoining as a replica (Oleksii Kliukin)

Previously, we only called pg_rewind if the former master had crashed. Change this to always run pg_rewind for the former master as long as pg_rewind is present in the system. This fixes the case when the master is shut down before the replicas managed to get the latest changes (i.e. during the “smart” shutdown).

Numerous improvements to unit- and acceptance- tests, in particular, enable support for Zookeeper and Consul (Alexander Kukushkin).

Make Travis CI faster and implement support for running tests against Zookeeper (Exhibitor) and Consul (Alexander Kukushkin)

Both unit and acceptance tests run automatically against Etcd, Zookeeper and Consul on each commit or pull-request.

Clear environment variables before calling PostgreSQL commands from Patroni (Feike Steenbergen)

This prevents a possibility of reading system environment variables by connecting to the PostgreSQL cluster managed by Patroni.

Configuration and control changes

Unify patronictl and Patroni configuration (Feike Steenbergen)

patronictl can use the same configuration file as Patroni itself.

Enable Patroni to read the configuration from the environment variables (Oleksii Kliukin)

This simplifies generating configuration for Patroni automatically, or merging a single configuration from different sources.

Include database system identifier in the information returned by the API (Feike Steenbergen)

Implement delete_cluster for all available DCSs (Alexander Kukushkin)

Enables support for DCSs other than Etcd in patronictl.

Version 0.80

Released 2016-03-14

This release adds support for cascading replication and simplifies Patroni management by providing scheduled failovers. One may use older versions of Patroni (in particular, 0.78) combined with this one in order to migrate to the new release. Note that the scheduled failover and cascading replication related features will only work with Patroni 0.80 and above.

Cascading replication

Add support for the replicatefrom and clonefrom tags for the patroni node (Oleksii Kliukin).

The tag replicatefrom allows a replica to use an arbitrary node a source, not necessary the master. The clonefrom does the same for the initial backup. Together, they enable Patroni to fully support cascading replication.

Add support for running replication methods to initialize the replica even without a running replication connection (Oleksii Kliukin).

This is useful in order to create replicas from the snapshots stored on S3 or FTP. A replication method that does not require a running replication connection should supply no_master: true in the yaml configuration. Those scripts will still be called in order if the replication connection is present.

Patronictl, API and DCS improvements

Implement scheduled failovers (Feike Steenbergen).

Failovers can be scheduled to happen at a certain time in the future, using either patronictl, or API calls.

Add support for dbuser and password parameters in patronictl (Feike Steenbergen).

Add PostgreSQL version to the health check output (Feike Steenbergen).

Improve Zookeeper support in patronictl (Oleksandr Shulgin)

Migrate to python-etcd 0.43 (Alexander Kukushkin)

Configuration

Add a sample systems configuration script for Patroni (Jan Keirse).

Fix the problem of Patroni ignoring the superuser name specified in the configuration file for DB connections (Alexander Kukushkin).

Fix the handling of CTRL-C by creating a separate session ID and process group for the postmaster launched by Patroni (Alexander Kukushkin).

Tests

Add acceptance tests with behave in order to check real-world scenarios of running Patroni (Alexander Kukushkin, Oleksii Kliukin).

The tests can be launched manually using the behave command. They are also launched automatically for pull requests and after commits.

Release notes for some older versions can be found on project’s github page [https://github.com/patroni/patroni/releases].

Replication modes

Patroni uses PostgreSQL streaming replication. For more information about streaming replication, see the Postgres documentation [http://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/static/warm-standby.html#STREAMING-REPLICATION]. By default Patroni configures PostgreSQL for asynchronous replication. Choosing your replication schema is dependent on your business considerations. Investigate both async and sync replication, as well as other HA solutions, to determine which solution is best for you.

Asynchronous mode durability

In asynchronous mode the cluster is allowed to lose some committed transactions to ensure availability. When the primary server fails or becomes unavailable for any other reason Patroni will automatically promote a sufficiently healthy standby to primary. Any transactions that have not been replicated to that standby remain in a “forked timeline” on the primary, and are effectively unrecoverable [1].

The amount of transactions that can be lost is controlled via maximum_lag_on_failover parameter. Because the primary transaction log position is not sampled in real time, in reality the amount of lost data on failover is worst case bounded by maximum_lag_on_failover bytes of transaction log plus the amount that is written in the last ttl seconds (loop_wait/2 seconds in the average case). However typical steady state replication delay is well under a second.

By default, when running leader elections, Patroni does not take into account the current timeline of replicas, what in some cases could be undesirable behavior. You can prevent the node not having the same timeline as a former primary become the new leader by changing the value of check_timeline parameter to true.

PostgreSQL synchronous replication

You can use Postgres’s synchronous replication [http://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/static/warm-standby.html#SYNCHRONOUS-REPLICATION] with Patroni. Synchronous replication ensures consistency across a cluster by confirming that writes are written to a secondary before returning to the connecting client with a success. The cost of synchronous replication: increased latency and reduced throughput on writes. This throughput will be entirely based on network performance.

In hosted datacenter environments (like AWS, Rackspace, or any network you do not control), synchronous replication significantly increases the variability of write performance. If followers become inaccessible from the leader, the leader effectively becomes read-only.

To enable a simple synchronous replication test, add the following lines to the parameters section of your YAML configuration files:

synchronous_commit: "on"
synchronous_standby_names: "*"

When using PostgreSQL synchronous replication, use at least three Postgres data nodes to ensure write availability if one host fails.

Using PostgreSQL synchronous replication does not guarantee zero lost transactions under all circumstances. When the primary and the secondary that is currently acting as a synchronous replica fail simultaneously a third node that might not contain all transactions will be promoted.

Synchronous mode

For use cases where losing committed transactions is not permissible you can turn on Patroni’s synchronous_mode. When synchronous_mode is turned on Patroni will not promote a standby unless it is certain that the standby contains all transactions that may have returned a successful commit status to client [2]. This means that the system may be unavailable for writes even though some servers are available. System administrators can still use manual failover commands to promote a standby even if it results in transaction loss.

Turning on synchronous_mode does not guarantee multi node durability of commits under all circumstances. When no suitable standby is available, primary server will still accept writes, but does not guarantee their replication. When the primary fails in this mode no standby will be promoted. When the host that used to be the primary comes back it will get promoted automatically, unless system administrator performed a manual failover. This behavior makes synchronous mode usable with 2 node clusters.

When synchronous_mode is on and a standby crashes, commits will block until next iteration of Patroni runs and switches the primary to standalone mode (worst case delay for writes ttl seconds, average case loop_wait/2 seconds). Manually shutting down or restarting a standby will not cause a commit service interruption. Standby will signal the primary to release itself from synchronous standby duties before PostgreSQL shutdown is initiated.

When it is absolutely necessary to guarantee that each write is stored durably on at least two nodes, enable synchronous_mode_strict in addition to the synchronous_mode. This parameter prevents Patroni from switching off the synchronous replication on the primary when no synchronous standby candidates are available. As a downside, the primary is not be available for writes (unless the Postgres transaction explicitly turns off synchronous_commit), blocking all client write requests until at least one synchronous replica comes up.

You can ensure that a standby never becomes the synchronous standby by setting nosync tag to true. This is recommended to set for standbys that are behind slow network connections and would cause performance degradation when becoming a synchronous standby. Setting tag nostream to true will also have the same effect.

Synchronous mode can be switched on and off using patronictl edit-config command or via Patroni REST interface. See dynamic configuration for instructions.

Note: Because of the way synchronous replication is implemented in PostgreSQL it is still possible to lose transactions even when using synchronous_mode_strict. If the PostgreSQL backend is cancelled while waiting to acknowledge replication (as a result of packet cancellation due to client timeout or backend failure) transaction changes become visible for other backends. Such changes are not yet replicated and may be lost in case of standby promotion.

Synchronous Replication Factor

The parameter synchronous_node_count is used by Patroni to manage the number of synchronous standby databases. It is set to 1 by default. It has no effect when synchronous_mode is set to off. When enabled, Patroni manages the precise number of synchronous standby databases based on parameter synchronous_node_count and adjusts the state in DCS & synchronous_standby_names in PostgreSQL as members join and leave. If the parameter is set to a value higher than the number of eligible nodes it will be automatically reduced by Patroni.

Maximum lag on synchronous node

By default Patroni sticks to nodes that are declared as synchronous, according to the pg_stat_replication view, even when there are other nodes ahead of it. This is done to minimize the number of changes of synchronous_standby_names. To change this behavior one may use maximum_lag_on_syncnode parameter. It controls how much lag the replica can have to still be considered as “synchronous”.

Patroni utilizes the max replica LSN if there is more than one standby, otherwise it will use leader’s current wal LSN. The default is -1, and Patroni will not take action to swap a synchronous unhealthy standby when the value is set to 0 or less. Please set the value high enough so that Patroni won’t swap synchronous standbys frequently during high transaction volume.

Synchronous mode implementation

When in synchronous mode Patroni maintains synchronization state in the DCS (/sync key), containing the latest primary and current synchronous standby databases. This state is updated with strict ordering constraints to ensure the following invariants:

A node must be marked as the latest leader whenever it can accept write transactions. Patroni crashing or PostgreSQL not shutting down can cause violations of this invariant.

A node must be set as the synchronous standby in PostgreSQL as long as it is published as the synchronous standby in the /sync key in DCS..

A node that is not the leader or current synchronous standby is not allowed to promote itself automatically.

Patroni will only assign one or more synchronous standby nodes based on synchronous_node_count parameter to synchronous_standby_names.

On each HA loop iteration Patroni re-evaluates synchronous standby nodes choice. If the current list of synchronous standby nodes are connected and has not requested its synchronous status to be removed it remains picked. Otherwise the cluster members available for sync that are furthest ahead in replication are picked.

Example:

/config key in DCS

synchronous_mode: on
synchronous_node_count: 2
...

/sync key in DCS

{
    "leader": "node0",
    "sync_standby": "node1,node2"
}

postgresql.conf

synchronous_standby_names = 'FIRST 2 (node1,node2)'

In the above examples only nodes node1 and node2 are known to be synchronous and allowed to be automatically promoted if the primary (node0) fails.

Quorum commit mode

Starting from PostgreSQL v10 Patroni supports quorum-based synchronous replication.

In this mode, Patroni maintains synchronization state in the DCS, containing the latest known primary, the number of nodes required for quorum, and the nodes currently eligible to vote on quorum. In steady state, the nodes voting on quorum are the leader and all synchronous standbys. This state is updated with strict ordering constraints, with regards to node promotion and synchronous_standby_names, to ensure that at all times any subset of voters that can achieve quorum includes at least one node with the latest successful commit.

On each iteration of HA loop, Patroni re-evaluates synchronous standby choices and quorum, based on node availability and requested cluster configuration. In PostgreSQL versions above 9.6 all eligible nodes are added as synchronous standbys as soon as their replication catches up to leader.

Quorum commit helps to reduce worst case latencies, even during normal operation, as a higher latency of replicating to one standby can be compensated by other standbys.

The quorum-based synchronous mode could be enabled by setting synchronous_mode to quorum using patronictl edit-config command or via Patroni REST interface. See dynamic configuration for instructions.

Other parameters, like synchronous_node_count, maximum_lag_on_syncnode, and synchronous_mode_strict continue to work the same way as with synchronous_mode=on.

Example:

/config key in DCS

synchronous_mode: quorum
synchronous_node_count: 2
...

/sync key in DCS

{
    "leader": "node0",
    "sync_standby": "node1,node2,node3",
    "quorum": 1
}

postgresql.conf

synchronous_standby_names = 'ANY 2 (node1,node2,node3)'

If the primary (node0) failed, in the above example two of the node1, node2, node3 will have the latest transaction received, but we don’t know which ones. To figure out whether the node node1 has received the latest transaction, we need to compare its LSN with the LSN on at least one node (quorum=1 in the /sync key) among node2 and node3. If node1 isn’t behind of at least one of them, we can guarantee that there will be no user visible data loss if node1 is promoted.

[1]

The data is still there, but recovering it requires a manual recovery effort by data recovery specialists. When Patroni is allowed to rewind with use_pg_rewind the forked timeline will be automatically erased to rejoin the failed primary with the cluster. However, for use_pg_rewind to function properly, either the cluster must be initialized with data page checksums (--data-checksums option for initdb) and/or wal_log_hints must be set to on.

[2]

Clients can change the behavior per transaction using PostgreSQL’s synchronous_commit setting. Transactions with synchronous_commit values of off and local may be lost on fail over, but will not be blocked by replication delays.

Security Considerations

A Patroni cluster has two interfaces to be protected from unauthorized access: the distributed configuration storage (DCS) and the Patroni REST API.

Protecting DCS

Patroni and patronictl both store and retrieve data to/from the DCS.

Despite DCS doesn’t contain any sensitive information, it allows changing some of Patroni/Postgres configuration. Therefore the very first thing that should be protected is DCS itself.

The details of protection depend on the type of DCS used. The authentication and encryption parameters (tokens/basic-auth/client certificates) for the supported types of DCS are covered in settings.

The general recommendation is to enable TLS for all DCS communication.

Protecting the REST API

Protecting the REST API is a more complicated task.

The Patroni REST API is used by Patroni itself during the leader race, by the patronictl tool in order to perform failovers/switchovers/reinitialize/restarts/reloads, by HAProxy or any other kind of load balancer to perform HTTP health checks, and of course could also be used for monitoring.

From the point of view of security, REST API contains safe (GET requests, only retrieve information) and unsafe (PUT, POST, PATCH and DELETE requests, change the state of nodes) endpoints.

The unsafe endpoints can be protected with HTTP basic-auth by setting the restapi.authentication.username and restapi.authentication.password parameters. There is no way to protect the safe endpoints without enabling TLS.

When TLS for the REST API is enabled and a PKI is established, mutual authentication of the API server and API client is possible for all endpoints.

The restapi section parameters enable TLS client authentication to the server. Depending on the value of the verify_client parameter, the API server requires a successful client certificate verification for both safe and unsafe API calls (verify_client: required), or only for unsafe API calls (verify_client: optional), or for no API calls (verify_client: none).

The ctl section parameters enable TLS server authentication to the client (the patronictl tool which uses the same config as patroni). Set insecure: true to disable the server certificate verification by the client. See settings for a detailed description of the TLS client parameters.

Protecting the PostgreSQL database proper from unauthorized access is beyond the scope of this document and is covered in https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/client-authentication.html

Standby cluster

Patroni also support running cascading replication to a remote datacenter (region) using a feature that is called “standby cluster”. This type of clusters has:

“standby leader”, that behaves pretty much like a regular cluster leader, except it replicates from a remote node.

cascade replicas, that are replicating from standby leader.

Standby leader holds and updates a leader lock in DCS. If the leader lock expires, cascade replicas will perform an election to choose another leader from the standbys.

There is no further relationship between the standby cluster and the primary cluster it replicates from, in particular, they must not share the same DCS scope if they use the same DCS. They do not know anything else from each other apart from replication information. Also, the standby cluster is not being displayed in patronictl list or patronictl topology output on the primary cluster.

For the sake of flexibility, you can specify methods of creating a replica and recovery WAL records when a cluster is in the “standby mode” by providing create_replica_methods key in

standby_cluster

section. It is distinct from creating replicas, when cluster is detached and functions as a normal cluster, which is controlled by

create_replica_methods

in

postgresql

section. Both “standby” and “normal”

create_replica_methods

reference keys in

postgresql

section.

To configure such cluster you need to specify the section standby_cluster in a patroni configuration:

bootstrap:
    dcs:
        standby_cluster:
            host: 1.2.3.4
            port: 5432
            primary_slot_name: patroni
            create_replica_methods:
            - basebackup

MySQL uses the same DCS standby_cluster keys (host, port, optional create_replica_methods), but bootstrap is a full clone of the remote primary (default xtrabackup then mysqldump) followed by GTID streaming (MASTER_AUTO_POSITION=1). Do not set PostgreSQL-only keys such as restore_command or primary_slot_name for MySQL. Example:

bootstrap:
    dcs:
        standby_cluster:
            host: primary-site.example
            port: 3306
            create_replica_methods:
            - xtrabackup
            - mysqldump

Note, that these options will be applied only once during cluster bootstrap, and the only way to change them afterwards is through DCS.

Patroni expects to find

postgresql.conf

or

postgresql.conf.backup

in PGDATA of the remote primary and will not start if it does not find it after a basebackup. If the remote primary keeps its

postgresql.conf

elsewhere, it is your responsibility to copy it to PGDATA.

If you use replication slots on the standby cluster, you must also create the corresponding replication slot on the primary cluster. It will not be done automatically by the standby cluster implementation. You can use Patroni’s permanent replication slots feature on the primary cluster to maintain a replication slot with the same name as primary_slot_name, or its default value if primary_slot_name is not provided.

In case the remote site doesn’t provide a single endpoint that connects to a primary, one could list all hosts of the source cluster in the standby_cluster.host section. When standby_cluster.host contains multiple hosts separated by commas, Patroni will:

add target_session_attrs=read-write to the primary_conninfo on the standby leader node.

use target_session_attrs=read-write when trying to determine whether we need to run pg_rewind or when executing pg_rewind on all nodes of the standby cluster.

It is important to note that for pg_rewind to operate successfully, either the cluster must be initialized with data page checksums (--data-checksums option for initdb) and/or wal_log_hints must be set to on. Otherwise, pg_rewind will not function properly.

There is also a possibility to replicate the standby cluster from another standby cluster or from a standby member of the primary cluster: for that, you need to define a single host in the standby_cluster.host section. However, you need to beware that in this case pg_rewind will fail to execute on the standby cluster.

Warning

Member names (the name field in each node’s Patroni configuration) must be unique across the primary cluster and all standby clusters connected to it.

Patroni sets synchronous_standby_names on the primary using member names, which also become the application_name of each replication connection in pg_stat_replication. If a standby cluster node shares the same name as a primary cluster member, PostgreSQL will see two connections with identical application_name values. This ambiguity can cause PostgreSQL to satisfy the synchronous replication requirement using the standby cluster’s connection instead of the intended primary cluster member, leading PostgreSQL to prematurely acknowledge transactions as synchronously committed when they are not durable on the correct standby.

This is a silent failure — replication continues and no errors are logged, but the cluster is effectively operating without a valid synchronous standby, which is a potential data loss scenario if the primary fails.

Integration with other tools

Patroni is able to integrate with other tools in your stack. In this section you will find a list of examples, which although not an exhaustive list, might provide you with ideas on how Patroni can integrate with other tools.

Barman

Patroni delivers an application named patroni_barman which has logic to communicate with pg-backup-api, so you are able to perform Barman operations remotely.

This application currently has a couple of sub-commands: recover and config-switch.

patroni_barman recover

The recover sub-command can be used as a custom bootstrap or custom replica creation method. You can find more information about that in Replica imaging and bootstrap.

patroni_barman config-switch

The config-switch sub-command is designed to be used as an on_role_change callback in Patroni. As an example, assume you are streaming WALs from your current primary to your Barman host. In the event of a failover in the cluster you might want to start streaming WALs from the new primary. You can accomplish this by using patroni_barman config-switch as the on_role_change callback.

Note

That sub-command relies on the barman config-switch command, which is in charge of overriding the configuration of a Barman server by applying a pre-defined model on top of it. This command is available since Barman 3.10. Please consult the Barman documentation for more details.

This is an example of how you can configure Patroni to apply a configuration model in case this Patroni node is promoted to primary:

postgresql:
    callbacks:
        on_role_change: >
            patroni_barman
                --api-url YOUR_API_URL
                config-switch
                --barman-server YOUR_BARMAN_SERVER_NAME
                --barman-model YOUR_BARMAN_MODEL_NAME
                --switch-when promoted

Note

patroni_barman config-switch requires that you have both Barman and pg-backup-api configured in the Barman host, so it can execute a remote barman config-switch through the backup API. Also, it requires that you have pre-configured Barman models to be applied. The above example uses a subset of the available parameters. You can get more information running patroni_barman config-switch --help, and by consulting the Barman documentation.

Watchdog support

Having multiple PostgreSQL servers running as primary can result in transactions lost due to diverging timelines. This situation is also called a split-brain problem. To avoid split-brain Patroni needs to ensure PostgreSQL will not accept any transaction commits after leader key expires in the DCS. Under normal circumstances Patroni will try to achieve this by stopping PostgreSQL when leader lock update fails for any reason. However, this may fail to happen due to various reasons:

Patroni has crashed due to a bug, out-of-memory condition or by being accidentally killed by a system administrator.

Shutting down PostgreSQL is too slow.

Patroni does not get to run due to high load on the system, the VM being paused by the hypervisor, or other infrastructure issues.

To guarantee correct behavior under these conditions Patroni supports watchdog devices. Watchdog devices are software or hardware mechanisms that will reset the whole system when they do not get a keepalive heartbeat within a specified timeframe. This adds an additional layer of fail safe in case usual Patroni split-brain protection mechanisms fail.

Patroni will try to activate the watchdog before promoting PostgreSQL to primary. If watchdog activation fails and watchdog mode is required then the node will refuse to become leader. When deciding to participate in leader election Patroni will also check that watchdog configuration will allow it to become leader at all. After demoting PostgreSQL (for example due to a manual failover) Patroni will disable the watchdog again. Watchdog will also be disabled while Patroni is in paused state.

By default Patroni will set up the watchdog to expire 5 seconds before TTL expires. With the default setup of loop_wait=10 and ttl=30 this gives HA loop at least 15 seconds (ttl - safety_margin - loop_wait) to complete before the system gets forcefully reset. By default accessing DCS is configured to time out after 10 seconds. This means that when DCS is unavailable, for example due to network issues, Patroni and PostgreSQL will have at least 5 seconds (ttl - safety_margin - loop_wait - retry_timeout) to come to a state where all client connections are terminated.

Safety margin is the amount of time that Patroni reserves for time between leader key update and watchdog keepalive. Patroni will try to send a keepalive immediately after confirmation of leader key update. If Patroni process is suspended for extended amount of time at exactly the right moment the keepalive may be delayed for more than the safety margin without triggering the watchdog. This results in a window of time where watchdog will not trigger before leader key expiration, invalidating the guarantee. To be absolutely sure that watchdog will trigger under all circumstances set up the watchdog to expire after half of TTL by setting safety_margin to -1 to set watchdog timeout to ttl // 2. If you need this guarantee you probably should increase ttl and/or reduce loop_wait and retry_timeout.

Currently watchdogs are only supported using Linux watchdog device interface.

Setting up software watchdog on Linux

Default Patroni configuration will try to use /dev/watchdog on Linux if it is accessible to Patroni. For most use cases using software watchdog built into the Linux kernel is secure enough.

To enable software watchdog issue the following commands as root before starting Patroni:

modprobe softdog
# Replace postgres with the user you will be running patroni under
chown postgres /dev/watchdog

For testing it may be helpful to disable rebooting by adding soft_noboot=1 to the modprobe command line. In this case the watchdog will just log a line in kernel ring buffer, visible via

dmesg

.

Patroni will log information about the watchdog when it is successfully enabled.

YAML Configuration Settings

Global/Universal

thread_pool_size: size of thread pool used by Patroni to execute asynchronous tasks and communicate via REST API with other members during leader race or failsafe checks. Minimal value is 5, default value is 5.

thread_stack_size: specifies the stack size to be used for threads started by Patroni. Value must be aligned by 64kB. Minimal value is 64kB, default value (set by Patroni) is 512kB.

name: the name of the host. Must be unique for the cluster.

namespace: path within the configuration store where Patroni will keep information about the cluster. Default value: “/service”

scope: cluster name

Log

type: sets the format of logs. Can be either plain or json. To use json format, you must have the jsonlogger installed. The default value is plain.

level: sets the general logging level. Default value is INFO (see the docs for Python logging [https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#levels])

traceback_level: sets the level where tracebacks will be visible. Default value is ERROR. Set it to DEBUG if you want to see tracebacks only if you enable log.level=DEBUG.

format: sets the log formatting string. If the log type is plain, the log format should be a string. Refer to the LogRecord attributes [https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#logrecord-attributes] for available attributes. If the log type is json, the log format can be a list in addition to a string. Each list item should correspond to LogRecord attributes. Be cautious that only the field name is required, and the %( and ) should be omitted. If you wish to print a log field with a different key name, use a dictionary where the dictionary key is the log field, and the value is the name of the field you want to be printed in the log. Default value is %(asctime)s %(levelname)s: %(message)s

dateformat: sets the datetime formatting string. (see the formatTime() documentation [https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/logging.html#logging.Formatter.formatTime])

static_fields: add additional fields to the log. This option is only available when the log type is set to json.

max_queue_size: Patroni is using two-step logging. Log records are written into the in-memory queue and there is a separate thread which pulls them from the queue and writes to stderr or file. The maximum size of the internal queue is limited by default by 1000 records, which is enough to keep logs for the past 1h20m.

dir: Directory to write application logs to. The directory must exist and be writable by the user executing Patroni. If you set this value, the application will retain 4 25MB logs by default. You can tune those retention values with

file_num

and

file_size

(see below).

mode: Permissions for log files (for example, 0644). If not specified, permissions will be set based on the current umask value.

file_num: The number of application logs to retain.

file_size: Size of patroni.log file (in bytes) that triggers a log rolling.

loggers: This section allows redefining logging level per python module

patroni.postmaster: WARNING

urllib3: DEBUG

deduplicate_heartbeat_logs: If set to true, successive heartbeat logs that are identical shall not be output. Default value is false.

Warning

The time the HA loop executes at can be very valuable information in diagnosing failovers due to resource exhaustion and similar problems. When deduplicate_heartbeat_logs is set to true there will be no log generated for the HA loop execution (unless the leader changes) and hence this potentially useful information will not be available from the logs.

Here is an example of how to config patroni to log in json format.

log:
   type: json
   format:
      - message
      - module
      - asctime: '@timestamp'
      - levelname: level
   static_fields:
      app: patroni

Bootstrap configuration

Note

Once Patroni has initialized the cluster for the first time and settings have been stored in the DCS, all future changes to the bootstrap.dcs section of the YAML configuration will not take any effect! If you want to change them please use either patronictl edit-config or the Patroni REST API.

bootstrap:

dcs: This section will be written into

/<namespace>/<scope>/config

of the given configuration store after initializing the new cluster. The global dynamic configuration for the cluster. You can put any of the parameters described in the Dynamic Configuration settings under bootstrap.dcs and after Patroni has initialized (bootstrapped) the new cluster, it will write this section into

/<namespace>/<scope>/config

of the configuration store.

method: custom script to use for bootstrapping this cluster.

See custom bootstrap methods documentation for details. When initdb is specified revert to the default initdb command. initdb is also triggered when no method parameter is present in the configuration file.

initdb: (optional) list options to be passed on to initdb.

- data-checksums: Must be enabled when pg_rewind is needed on 9.3.

- encoding: UTF8: default encoding for new databases.

- locale: UTF8: default locale for new databases.

post_bootstrap or post_init: An additional script that will be executed after initializing the cluster. The script receives a connection string URL (with the cluster superuser as a user name). The PGPASSFILE variable is set to the location of pgpass file.

Citus

Enables integration Patroni with Citus [https://docs.citusdata.com]. If configured, Patroni will take care of registering Citus worker nodes on the coordinator. You can find more information about Citus support here.

group: the Citus group id, integer. Use 0 for coordinator and 1, 2, etc… for workers

database: the database where citus extension should be created. Must be the same on the coordinator and all workers. Currently only one database is supported.

Consul

Most of the parameters are optional, but you have to specify one of the host or url

host: the host:port for the Consul local agent.

url: url for the Consul local agent, in format: http(s)://host:port.

port: (optional) Consul port.

scheme: (optional) http or https, defaults to http.

token: (optional) ACL token.

verify: (optional) whether to verify the SSL certificate for HTTPS requests.

cacert: (optional) The ca certificate. If present it will enable validation.

cert: (optional) file with the client certificate.

key: (optional) file with the client key. Can be empty if the key is part of cert.

dc: (optional) Datacenter to communicate with. By default the datacenter of the host is used.

consistency: (optional) Select consul consistency mode. Possible values are default, consistent, or stale (more details in consul API reference [https://www.consul.io/api/features/consistency.html/])

checks: (optional) list of Consul health checks used for the session. By default an empty list is used.

register_service: (optional) whether or not to register a service with the name defined by the scope parameter and the tag master, primary, replica, or standby-leader depending on the node’s role. Defaults to false.

service_tags: (optional) additional static tags to add to the Consul service apart from the role (primary/replica/standby-leader). By default an empty list is used.

service_check_interval: (optional) how often to perform health check against registered url. Defaults to ‘5s’.

service_check_tls_server_name: (optional) override SNI host when connecting via TLS, see also consul agent check API reference [https://www.consul.io/api-docs/agent/check#tlsservername].

The token needs to have the following ACL permissions:

service_prefix "${scope}" {
    policy = "write"
}
key_prefix "${namespace}/${scope}" {
    policy = "write"
}
session_prefix "" {
    policy = "write"
}

Etcd

Most of the parameters are optional, but you have to specify one of the host, hosts, url, proxy or srv

host: the host:port for the etcd endpoint.

hosts: list of etcd endpoint in format host1:port1,host2:port2,etc… Could be a comma separated string or an actual yaml list.

use_proxies: If this parameter is set to true, Patroni will consider hosts as a list of proxies and will not perform a topology discovery of etcd cluster.

url: url for the etcd.

proxy: proxy url for the etcd. If you are connecting to the etcd using proxy, use this parameter instead of url.

srv: Domain to search the SRV record(s) for cluster autodiscovery. Patroni will try to query these SRV service names for specified domain (in that order until first success): _etcd-client-ssl, _etcd-client, _etcd-ssl, _etcd, _etcd-server-ssl, _etcd-server. If SRV records for _etcd-server-ssl or _etcd-server are retrieved then ETCD peer protocol is used do query ETCD for available members. Otherwise hosts from SRV records will be used.

srv_suffix: Configures a suffix to the SRV name that is queried during discovery. Use this flag to differentiate between multiple etcd clusters under the same domain. Works only with conjunction with srv. For example, if srv_suffix: foo and srv: example.org are set, the following DNS SRV query is made:_etcd-client-ssl-foo._tcp.example.com (and so on for every possible ETCD SRV service name).

protocol: (optional) http or https, if not specified http is used. If the url or proxy is specified - will take protocol from them.

username: (optional) username for etcd authentication.

password: (optional) password for etcd authentication.

cacert: (optional) The ca certificate. If present it will enable validation.

cert: (optional) file with the client certificate.

key: (optional) file with the client key. Can be empty if the key is part of cert.

Etcdv3

If you want that Patroni works with Etcd cluster via protocol version 3, you need to use the etcd3 section in the Patroni configuration file. All configuration parameters are the same as for etcd.

Warning

Keys created with protocol version 2 are not visible with protocol version 3 and the other way around, therefore it is not possible to switch from etcd to etcd3 just by updating Patroni config file. In addition, Patroni uses Etcd’s gRPC-gateway (proxy) to communicate with the V3 API, which means that TLS common name authentication is not possible.

ZooKeeper

hosts: List of ZooKeeper cluster members in format: [‘host1:port1’, ‘host2:port2’, ‘etc…’].

use_ssl: (optional) Whether SSL is used or not. Defaults to false. If set to false, all SSL specific parameters are ignored.

cacert: (optional) The CA certificate. If present it will enable validation.

cert: (optional) File with the client certificate.

key: (optional) File with the client key.

key_password: (optional) The client key password.

verify: (optional) Whether to verify certificate or not. Defaults to true.

set_acls: (optional) If set, configure Kazoo to apply a default ACL to each ZNode that it creates. ACLs will assume ‘x509’ schema and should be specified as a dictionary with the principal as the key and one or more permissions as a list in the value. Permissions may be one of CREATE, READ, WRITE, DELETE or ADMIN. For example, set_acls: {CN=principal1: [CREATE, READ], CN=principal2: [ALL]}.

auth_data: (optional) Authentication credentials to use for the connection. Should be a dictionary in the form that

scheme

is the key and

credential

is the value. Defaults to empty dictionary.

Note

It is required to install kazoo>=2.6.0 to support SSL.

Exhibitor

hosts: initial list of Exhibitor (ZooKeeper) nodes in format: ‘host1,host2,etc…’. This list updates automatically whenever the Exhibitor (ZooKeeper) cluster topology changes.

poll_interval: how often the list of ZooKeeper and Exhibitor nodes should be updated from Exhibitor.

port: Exhibitor port.

Kubernetes

bypass_api_service: (optional) When communicating with the Kubernetes API, Patroni is usually relying on the

kubernetes

service, the address of which is exposed in the pods via the

KUBERNETES_SERVICE_HOST

environment variable. If

bypass_api_service

is set to true, Patroni will resolve the list of API nodes behind the service and connect directly to them.

namespace: (optional) Kubernetes namespace where Patroni pod is running. Default value is

default

.

labels: Labels in format {label1: value1, label2: value2}. These labels will be used to find existing objects (Pods and either Endpoints or ConfigMaps) associated with the current cluster. Also Patroni will set them on every object (Endpoint or ConfigMap) it creates.

scope_label: (optional) name of the label containing cluster name. Default value is

cluster-name

.

bootstrap_labels: (optional) Labels in format {label1: value1, label2: value2}. These labels will be assigned to a Patroni pod when its state is either initializing new cluster, running custom bootstrap script, starting after custom bootstrap or creating replica.

role_label: (optional) name of the label containing role (

primary

,

replica

, or other custom value). Patroni will set this label on the pod it runs in. Default value is role.

leader_label_value: (optional) value of the pod label when Postgres role is primary. Default value is primary.

follower_label_value: (optional) value of the pod label when Postgres role is replica. Default value is replica.

standby_leader_label_value: (optional) value of the pod label when Postgres role is standby_leader. Default value is primary.

tmp_role_label: (optional) name of the temporary label containing role (

primary

or

replica

). Value of this label will always use the default of corresponding role. Set only when necessary.

use_endpoints: (optional) if set to true, Patroni will use Endpoints instead of ConfigMaps to run leader elections and keep cluster state.

pod_ip: (optional) IP address of the pod Patroni is running in. This value is required when

use_endpoints

is enabled and is used to populate the leader endpoint subsets when the pod’s PostgreSQL is promoted.

ports: (optional) if the Service object has the name for the port, the same name must appear in the Endpoint object, otherwise service won’t work. For example, if your service is defined as {Kind: Service, spec: {ports: [{name: postgresql, port: 5432, targetPort: 5432}]}}, then you have to set kubernetes.ports: [{"name": "postgresql", "port": 5432}] and Patroni will use it for updating subsets of the leader Endpoint. This parameter is used only if

kubernetes.use_endpoints

is set.

cacert: (optional) Specifies the file with the CA_BUNDLE file with certificates of trusted CAs to use while verifying Kubernetes API SSL certs. If not provided, patroni will use the value provided by the ServiceAccount secret.

retriable_http_codes: (optional) list of HTTP status codes from K8s API to retry on. By default Patroni is retrying on 500, 503, and 504, or if K8s API response has retry-after HTTP header.

Raft (deprecated)

self_addr: ip:port to listen on for Raft connections. The self_addr must be accessible from other nodes of the cluster. If not set, the node will not participate in consensus.

bind_addr: (optional) ip:port to listen on for Raft connections. If not specified the self_addr will be used.

partner_addrs: list of other Patroni nodes in the cluster in format: [‘ip1:port’, ‘ip2:port’, ‘etc…’]

data_dir: directory where to store Raft log and snapshot. If not specified the current working directory is used.

password: (optional) Encrypt Raft traffic with a specified password, requires cryptography python module.

Short FAQ about Raft implementation

Q: How to list all the nodes providing consensus?

A: syncobj_admin -conn host:port -status where the host:port is the address of one of the cluster nodes

Q: Node that was a part of consensus and has gone and I can’t reuse the same IP for other node. How to remove this node from the consensus?

A: syncobj_admin -conn host:port -remove host2:port2 where the host2:port2 is the address of the node you want to remove from consensus.

Q: Where to get the syncobj_admin utility?

A: It is installed together with pysyncobj module (python RAFT implementation), which is Patroni dependency.

Q: it is possible to run Patroni node without adding in to the consensus?

A: Yes, just comment out or remove raft.self_addr from Patroni configuration.

Q: It is possible to run Patroni and PostgreSQL only on two nodes?

A: Yes, on the third node you can run patroni_raft_controller (without Patroni and PostgreSQL). In such a setup, one can temporarily lose one node without affecting the primary.

PostgreSQL

postgresql:

authentication:

superuser:

username: name for the superuser, set during initialization (initdb) and later used by Patroni to connect to the postgres.

password: password for the superuser, set during initialization (initdb).

sslmode: (optional) maps to the sslmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLMODE] connection parameter, which allows a client to specify the type of TLS negotiation mode with the server. For more information on how each mode works, please visit the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-ssl.html#LIBPQ-SSL-SSLMODE-STATEMENTS]. The default mode is prefer.

sslkey: (optional) maps to the sslkey [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLKEY] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the secret key used with the client’s certificate.

sslpassword: (optional) maps to the sslpassword [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLPASSWORD] connection parameter, which specifies the password for the secret key specified in sslkey.

sslcert: (optional) maps to the sslcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the client certificate.

sslrootcert: (optional) maps to the sslrootcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLROOTCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing one or more certificate authorities (CA) certificates that the client will use to verify a server’s certificate.

sslcrl: (optional) maps to the sslcrl [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRL] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

sslcrldir: (optional) maps to the sslcrldir [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRLDIR] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a directory with files containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

sslnegotiation: (optional) maps to the sslnegotiation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLNEGOTIATION] connection parameter, which controls how SSL encryption is negotiated with the server, if SSL is used.

gssencmode: (optional) maps to the gssencmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-GSSENCMODE] connection parameter, which determines whether or with what priority a secure GSS TCP/IP connection will be negotiated with the server

channel_binding: (optional) maps to the channel_binding [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-CHANNEL-BINDING] connection parameter, which controls the client’s use of channel binding.

replication:

username: replication username; the user will be created during initialization. Replicas will use this user to access the replication source via streaming replication

password: replication password; the user will be created during initialization.

sslmode: (optional) maps to the sslmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLMODE] connection parameter, which allows a client to specify the type of TLS negotiation mode with the server. For more information on how each mode works, please visit the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-ssl.html#LIBPQ-SSL-SSLMODE-STATEMENTS]. The default mode is prefer.

sslkey: (optional) maps to the sslkey [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLKEY] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the secret key used with the client’s certificate.

sslpassword: (optional) maps to the sslpassword [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLPASSWORD] connection parameter, which specifies the password for the secret key specified in sslkey.

sslcert: (optional) maps to the sslcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the client certificate.

sslrootcert: (optional) maps to the sslrootcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLROOTCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing one or more certificate authorities (CA) certificates that the client will use to verify a server’s certificate.

sslcrl: (optional) maps to the sslcrl [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRL] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

sslcrldir: (optional) maps to the sslcrldir [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRLDIR] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a directory with files containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

sslnegotiation: (optional) maps to the sslnegotiation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLNEGOTIATION] connection parameter, which controls how SSL encryption is negotiated with the server, if SSL is used.

gssencmode: (optional) maps to the gssencmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-GSSENCMODE] connection parameter, which determines whether or with what priority a secure GSS TCP/IP connection will be negotiated with the server

channel_binding: (optional) maps to the channel_binding [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-CHANNEL-BINDING] connection parameter, which controls the client’s use of channel binding.

rewind:

username: (optional) name for the user for pg_rewind; the user will be created during initialization of postgres 11+ and all necessary permissions [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/11/app-pgrewind.html#id-1.9.5.8.8] will be granted.

password: (optional) password for the user for pg_rewind; the user will be created during initialization.

sslmode: (optional) maps to the sslmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLMODE] connection parameter, which allows a client to specify the type of TLS negotiation mode with the server. For more information on how each mode works, please visit the PostgreSQL documentation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-ssl.html#LIBPQ-SSL-SSLMODE-STATEMENTS]. The default mode is prefer.

sslkey: (optional) maps to the sslkey [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLKEY] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the secret key used with the client’s certificate.

sslpassword: (optional) maps to the sslpassword [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLPASSWORD] connection parameter, which specifies the password for the secret key specified in sslkey.

sslcert: (optional) maps to the sslcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of the client certificate.

sslrootcert: (optional) maps to the sslrootcert [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLROOTCERT] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing one or more certificate authorities (CA) certificates that the client will use to verify a server’s certificate.

sslcrl: (optional) maps to the sslcrl [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRL] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a file containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

sslcrldir: (optional) maps to the sslcrldir [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLCRLDIR] connection parameter, which specifies the location of a directory with files containing a certificate revocation list. A client will reject connecting to any server that has a certificate present in this list.

sslnegotiation: (optional) maps to the sslnegotiation [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-SSLNEGOTIATION] connection parameter, which controls how SSL encryption is negotiated with the server, if SSL is used.

gssencmode: (optional) maps to the gssencmode [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-GSSENCMODE] connection parameter, which determines whether or with what priority a secure GSS TCP/IP connection will be negotiated with the server

channel_binding: (optional) maps to the channel_binding [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-connect.html#LIBPQ-CONNECT-CHANNEL-BINDING] connection parameter, which controls the client’s use of channel binding.

callbacks: callback scripts to run on certain actions. Patroni will pass the action, role and cluster name. (See scripts/aws.py as an example of how to write them.)

on_reload: run this script when configuration reload is triggered.

on_restart: run this script when the postgres restarts (without changing role).

on_role_change: run this script when the postgres is being promoted or demoted.

on_start: run this script when the postgres starts.

on_stop: run this script when the postgres stops.

connect_address: IP address + port through which Postgres is accessible from other nodes and applications.

proxy_address: IP address + port through which a connection pool (e.g. pgbouncer) running next to Postgres is accessible. The value is written to the member key in DCS as proxy_url and could be used/useful for service discovery.

create_replica_methods: an ordered list of the create methods for turning a Patroni node into a new replica. “basebackup” is the default method; other methods are assumed to refer to scripts, each of which is configured as its own config item. See custom replica creation methods documentation for further explanation.

data_dir: The location of the Postgres data directory, either existing or to be initialized by Patroni.

config_dir: The location of the Postgres configuration directory, defaults to the data directory. Must be writable by Patroni.

bin_dir: (optional) Path to PostgreSQL binaries (pg_ctl, initdb, pg_controldata, pg_basebackup, postgres, pg_isready, pg_rewind). If not provided or is an empty string, PATH environment variable will be used to find the executables.

bin_name: (optional) Make it possible to override Postgres binary names, if you are using a custom Postgres distribution:

pg_ctl: (optional) Custom name for pg_ctl binary.

initdb: (optional) Custom name for initdb binary.

pgcontroldata: (optional) Custom name for pg_controldata binary.

pg_basebackup: (optional) Custom name for pg_basebackup binary.

postgres: (optional) Custom name for postgres binary.

pg_isready: (optional) Custom name for pg_isready binary.

pg_rewind: (optional) Custom name for pg_rewind binary.

listen: IP address + port that Postgres listens to; must be accessible from other nodes in the cluster, if you’re using streaming replication. Multiple comma-separated addresses are permitted, as long as the port component is appended after to the last one with a colon, i.e. listen: 127.0.0.1,127.0.0.2:5432. Patroni will use the first address from this list to establish local connections to the PostgreSQL node.

use_unix_socket: specifies that Patroni should prefer to use unix sockets to connect to the cluster. Default value is false. If unix_socket_directories is defined, Patroni will use the first suitable value from it to connect to the cluster and fallback to tcp if nothing is suitable. If unix_socket_directories is not specified in postgresql.parameters, Patroni will assume that the default value should be used and omit host from the connection parameters.

use_unix_socket_repl: specifies that Patroni should prefer to use unix sockets for replication user cluster connection. Default value is false. If unix_socket_directories is defined, Patroni will use the first suitable value from it to connect to the cluster and fallback to tcp if nothing is suitable. If unix_socket_directories is not specified in postgresql.parameters, Patroni will assume that the default value should be used and omit host from the connection parameters.

pgpass: path to the .pgpass [https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/static/libpq-pgpass.html] password file. Patroni creates this file before executing pg_basebackup, the post_init script and under some other circumstances. The location must be writable by Patroni.

recovery_conf: additional configuration settings written to recovery.conf when configuring follower.

custom_conf : path to an optional custom postgresql.conf file, that will be used in place of postgresql.base.conf. The file must exist on all cluster nodes, be readable by PostgreSQL and will be included from its location on the real postgresql.conf. Note that Patroni will not monitor this file for changes, nor backup it. However, its settings can still be overridden by Patroni’s own configuration facilities - see dynamic configuration for details.

parameters: configuration parameters (GUCs) for Postgres in format {ssl: "on", ssl_cert_file: "cert_file"}.

pg_hba: list of lines that Patroni will use to generate pg_hba.conf. Patroni ignores this parameter if hba_file PostgreSQL parameter is set to a non-default value. Together with dynamic configuration this parameter simplifies management of pg_hba.conf.

- host all all 0.0.0.0/0 md5

- host replication replicator 127.0.0.1/32 md5: A line like this is required for replication.

pg_ident: list of lines that Patroni will use to generate pg_ident.conf. Patroni ignores this parameter if ident_file PostgreSQL parameter is set to a non-default value. Together with dynamic configuration this parameter simplifies management of pg_ident.conf.

- mapname1 systemname1 pguser1

- mapname1 systemname2 pguser2

pg_ctl_timeout: How long should pg_ctl wait when doing start, stop or restart. Default value is 60 seconds.

use_pg_rewind: try to use pg_rewind on the former leader when it joins cluster as a replica. Either the cluster must be initialized with data page checksums (--data-checksums option for initdb) and/or wal_log_hints must be set to on, or pg_rewind will not work.

remove_data_directory_on_rewind_failure: If this option is enabled, Patroni will remove the PostgreSQL data directory and recreate the replica. Otherwise it will try to follow the new leader. Default value is false.

remove_data_directory_on_diverged_timelines: Patroni will remove the PostgreSQL data directory and recreate the replica if it notices that timelines are diverging and the former primary can not start streaming from the new primary. This option is useful when pg_rewind can not be used. While performing timelines divergence check on PostgreSQL v10 and older Patroni will try to connect with replication credential to the “postgres” database. Hence, such access should be allowed in the pg_hba.conf. Default value is false.

replica_method: for each create_replica_methods other than basebackup, you would add a configuration section of the same name. At a minimum, this should include “command” with a full path to the actual script to be executed. Other configuration parameters will be passed along to the script in the form “parameter=value”.

pre_promote: a fencing script that executes during a failover after acquiring the leader lock but before promoting the replica. If the script exits with a non-zero code, Patroni does not promote the replica and removes the leader key from DCS.

before_stop: a script that executes immediately prior to stopping postgres. As opposed to a callback, this script runs synchronously, blocking shutdown until it has completed. The return code of this script does not impact whether shutdown proceeds afterwards.

REST API

restapi:

thread_pool_size: size of thread pool used by Patroni to process REST API requests. Minimal value is 5, default value is 5.

connect_address: IP address (or hostname) and port, to access the Patroni’s REST API. All the members of the cluster must be able to connect to this address, so unless the Patroni setup is intended for a demo inside the localhost, this address must be a non “localhost” or loopback address (ie: “localhost” or “127.0.0.1”). It can serve as an endpoint for HTTP health checks (read below about the “listen” REST API parameter), and also for user queries (either directly or via the REST API), as well as for the health checks done by the cluster members during leader elections (for example, to determine whether the leader is still running, or if there is a node which has a WAL position that is ahead of the one doing the query; etc.) The connect_address is put in the member key in DCS, making it possible to translate the member name into the address to connect to its REST API.

listen: IP address (or hostname) and port that Patroni will listen to for the REST API - to provide also the same health checks and cluster messaging between the participating nodes, as described above. to provide health-check information for HAProxy (or any other load balancer capable of doing a HTTP “OPTION” or “GET” checks).

authentication: (optional)

username: Basic-auth username to protect unsafe REST API endpoints.

password: Basic-auth password to protect unsafe REST API endpoints.

certfile: (optional): Specifies the file with the certificate in the PEM format. If the certfile is not specified or is left empty, the API server will work without SSL.

keyfile: (optional): Specifies the file with the secret key in the PEM format.

keyfile_password: (optional): Specifies a password for decrypting the keyfile.

cafile: (optional): Specifies the file with the CA_BUNDLE with certificates of trusted CAs to use while verifying client certs.

ciphers: (optional): Specifies the permitted cipher suites (e.g. “ECDHE-RSA-AES256-GCM-SHA384:DHE-RSA-AES256-GCM-SHA384:ECDHE-RSA-AES128-GCM-SHA256:DHE-RSA-AES128-GCM-SHA256:!SSLv1:!SSLv2:!SSLv3:!TLSv1:!TLSv1.1”)

verify_client: (optional): none (default), optional or required. When none REST API will not check client certificates. When required client certificates are required for all REST API calls. When optional client certificates are required for all unsafe REST API endpoints. When required is used, then client authentication succeeds, if the certificate signature verification succeeds. For optional the client cert will only be checked for PUT, POST, PATCH, and DELETE requests.

allowlist: (optional): Specifies the set of hosts that are allowed to call unsafe REST API endpoints. The single element could be a host name, an IP address or a network address using CIDR notation. By default allow all is used. In case if allowlist or allowlist_include_members are set, anything that is not included is rejected.

allowlist_include_members: (optional): If set to true it allows accessing unsafe REST API endpoints from other cluster members registered in DCS (IP address or hostname is taken from the members api_url). Be careful, it might happen that OS will use a different IP for outgoing connections.

http_extra_headers: (optional): HTTP headers let the REST API server pass additional information with an HTTP response.

https_extra_headers: (optional): HTTPS headers let the REST API server pass additional information with an HTTP response when TLS is enabled. This will also pass additional information set in http_extra_headers.

request_queue_size: (optional): Sets request queue size for TCP socket used by Patroni REST API. Once the queue is full, further requests get a “Connection denied” error. The default value is 5.

server_tokens: (optional): Configures the value of the Server HTTP header. - Minimal: The header will contain only the Patroni version, e.g. Patroni/4.0.0. - ProductOnly: The header will contain only the product name, e.g. Patroni. - Original (default): The header will expose the original behaviour and display the BaseHTTP and Python versions, e.g. BaseHTTP/0.6 Python/3.12.3.

Here is an example of both http_extra_headers and https_extra_headers:

restapi:
  listen: <listen>
  connect_address: <connect_address>
  authentication:
    username: <username>
    password: <password>
  http_extra_headers:
    'X-Frame-Options': 'SAMEORIGIN'
    'X-XSS-Protection': '1; mode=block'
    'X-Content-Type-Options': 'nosniff'
  cafile: <ca file>
  certfile: <cert>
  keyfile: <key>
  https_extra_headers:
    'Strict-Transport-Security': 'max-age=31536000; includeSubDomains'

Warning

The restapi.connect_address must be accessible from all nodes of a given Patroni cluster. Internally Patroni is using it during the leader race to find nodes with minimal replication lag.

If you enabled client certificates validation (restapi.verify_client is set to required), you also must provide valid client certificates in the ctl.certfile, ctl.keyfile, ctl.keyfile_password. If not provided, Patroni will not work correctly.

CTL

ctl: (optional)

authentication:

username: Basic-auth username for accessing protected REST API endpoints. If not provided patronictl will use the value provided for REST API “username” parameter.

password: Basic-auth password for accessing protected REST API endpoints. If not provided patronictl will use the value provided for REST API “password” parameter.

insecure: Allow connections to REST API without verifying SSL certs.

cacert: Specifies the file with the CA_BUNDLE file or directory with certificates of trusted CAs to use while verifying REST API SSL certs. If not provided patronictl will use the value provided for REST API “cafile” parameter.

certfile: Specifies the file with the client certificate in the PEM format.

keyfile: Specifies the file with the client secret key in the PEM format.

keyfile_password: Specifies a password for decrypting the client keyfile.

Watchdog

mode: off, automatic or required. When off watchdog is disabled. When automatic watchdog will be used if available, but ignored if it is not. When required the node will not become a leader unless watchdog can be successfully enabled.

device: Path to watchdog device. Defaults to /dev/watchdog.

safety_margin: Number of seconds of safety margin between watchdog triggering and leader key expiration.

Tags

clonefrom: true or false. If set to true other nodes might prefer to use this node for bootstrap (take pg_basebackup from). If there are several nodes with clonefrom tag set to true the node to bootstrap from will be chosen randomly. The default value is false.

noloadbalance: true or false. If set to true the node will return HTTP Status Code 503 for the GET /replica REST API health-check and therefore will be excluded from the load-balancing. Defaults to false.

replicatefrom: The name of another replica to replicate from. Used to support cascading replication.

nosync: true or false. If set to true the node will never be selected as a synchronous replica.

sync_priority: integer, controls the priority this node should have during synchronous replica selection when synchronous_mode is set to on. Nodes with higher priority will be preferred over lower-priority nodes. If the sync_priority is 0 or negative - such node is not allowed to be written to synchronous_standby_names PostgreSQL parameter (similar to nosync: true). Keep in mind, that this parameter has the opposite meaning to sync_priority value reported in pg_stat_replication view.

nofailover: true or false, controls whether this node is allowed to participate in the leader race and become a leader. Defaults to false, meaning this node _can_ participate in leader races.

failover_priority: integer, controls the priority this node should have during failover. Nodes with higher priority will be preferred over lower-priority nodes if they received/replayed the same amount of WAL. However, nodes with higher values of receive/replay LSN are preferred regardless of their priority. If the failover_priority is 0 or negative - such node is not allowed to participate in the leader race and to become a leader (similar to nofailover: true). Known limitation: failover_priority currently doesn’t work with quorum-based synchronous replication.

nostream: true or false. If set to true the node will not use replication protocol to stream WAL. It will rely instead on archive recovery (if restore_command is configured) and pg_wal/pg_xlog polling. It also disables copying and synchronization of permanent logical replication slots on the node itself and all its cascading replicas. Setting this tag on primary node has no effect.

Warning

Provide only one of nofailover or failover_priority. Providing nofailover: true is the same as failover_priority: 0, and providing nofailover: false will give the node priority 1.

In addition to these predefined tags, you can also add your own ones:

key1: true

key2: false

key3: 1.4

key4: "RandomString"

Tags are visible in the REST API and patronictl list You can also check for an instance health using these tags. If the tag isn’t defined for an instance, or if the respective value doesn’t match the querying value, it will return HTTP Status Code 503.